<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Comput Math Methods Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Comput Math Methods Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CMMM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Computational and Mathematical Methods in Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1748-670X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1748-6718</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29250133</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5700558</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/2906282</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Periodically Pulsed Immunotherapy in a Mathematical Model of Tumor, CD4<sup>+</sup> T Cells, and Antitumor Cytokine Interactions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Hsiu-Chuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0674-3556</contrib-id><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Jui-Ling</given-names></name><email>jlyu@gm.pu.edu.tw</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>Chia-Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">
<sup>1</sup>Department of Applied Mathematics, Feng Chia University, Seatwen, Taichung 40724, Taiwan</aff><aff id="I2">
<sup>2</sup>Department of Financial and Computational Mathematics, Providence University, Shalu Dist., Taichung 43301, Taiwan</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editor: Konstantin Blyuss</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>2017</volume><elocation-id>2906282</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2017 Hsiu-Chuan Wei et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Immunotherapy is one of the most recent approaches for controlling and curing malignant tumors. In this paper, we consider a mathematical model of periodically pulsed immunotherapy using CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and an antitumor cytokine. Mathematical analyses are performed to determine the threshold of a successful treatment. The interindividual variability is explored by one-, two-, and three-parameter bifurcation diagrams for a nontreatment case. Numerical simulation conducted in this paper shows that (i) the tumor can be regulated by administering CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells alone in a patient with a strong immune system or who has been diagnosed at an early stage, (ii) immunotherapy with a large amount of an antitumor cytokine can boost the immune system to remit or even to suppress tumor cells completely, and (iii) through polytherapy the tumor can be kept at a smaller size with reduced dosages.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Cancer is one of the most common life-threatening diseases in the 21st century. For example, melanoma is estimated to cause the death of 10,130 people annually in the United States. In 2016, an estimated 76,380 melanoma cases were identified to be invasive; of the 76,380 cases, approximately 46,870 were men and 29,510 were women [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Cancer cells can not only divide and grow abnormally at the primary site but also invade other parts or organs of the body through blood circulation or the lymphatic system.</p><p>Standard therapies for melanoma are surgical resection, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy. Surgery may remove the tumor, but it often needs subsequent surgery to reduce the risk of recurrence. To reduce the rate of tumor recurrence, wide excision is required at the site of the original lesion; this usually leaves a noticeable scar and may result in treatment failure. Moreover, surgery may be difficult for large lesions or in some areas of the body, such as the face and eyelids [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Radiation therapy is often used after surgical resection for patients with locally advanced melanoma or those with inoperable distant metastases. Although this therapy can reduce the rate of local recurrence, it does not compromise survival [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Chemotherapy involves the use of drugs to kill cancer cells by stopping or slowing the fast growth of cancer cells. However, as a side effect, chemotherapy also harms healthy cells that grow and divide rapidly under normal circumstances, such as blood cells and cells in the digestive tract. Chemotherapy-related toxicities can occur acutely, subacutely, chronically, or many years after the treatment [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. To develop treatments with low toxicity, immunotherapies utilizing a patient's own immune system were created [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Cancer immunotherapies have considerably focused on the antitumor activities of white blood cells, especially T cells, natural killer (NK) cells, and macrophages. Among them, adoptive cellular therapy (ACT) that uses CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells is considered a powerful treatment against established tumors. However, a few studies have addressed tumor-specific CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells have traditionally been regarded as helpers to achieve full activation of tumor-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs) [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Most cancer immunotherapies have focused on CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells that recognize a specific antigen and bind to the complex of class I major histocompatibility (MHC) proteins. However, recent evidence has shown that many tumors are immunoselected to evade recognition by CTLs [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, the use of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells to fight cancer has been proposed as an alternative approach and proven to have promising effects.</p><p>Various studies have demonstrated the ability of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells to reject CTL-resistant, MHC class II-negative tumors [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Unlike CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, which mediate the clearance of pathogens by destroying all infected host cells, CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells secrete antiangiogenic cytokines to activate other T cells and recruit other tumoricidal myeloid cells to the tumor site [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Because these destructive mechanisms of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are not affected by the expression level of MHC proteins, they have more advantages in tumor killing than the established effector functions of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Increasing evidence has demonstrated that the adoptive transfer of tumor-specific CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells can exert a stronger antitumor effect than CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells in cancer therapy [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>There are mathematical theoretical studies about tumor-immune dynamics. Eftimie et al. [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] presented a comprehensive overview on the research in this area. In 2010, they proposed models of a tumor, CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, and cytokine interactions to discuss the role of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in melanoma rejection, where CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were separated into Th1 and Th2 cells [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] Anderson et al. explored the dynamics of tumors, CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, and antitumor interactions with or without continuous infusion of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells or antitumor cytokines produced by Th2. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were grouped as one type of cells, and only the effect of tumor suppressor cytokines, such as interleukin IL-4, was considered. The interaction between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and tumor cells is indirect in the sense that the tumor is suppressed through the action of cytokines. Other theoretical investigations about the tumor-immune dynamics have been mentioned in [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>Anderson et al. [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] discussed the effect of the continuous infusion of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells or cytokines produced by Th2 on tumor rejection. In this study, we explore the capacity of periodically pulsed therapies to fight cancer. We turned the continuous system of ordinary differential equations into a discrete dynamical system for the bifurcation analysis of periodically pulsed therapies. Instead of using the typical numerical method for the bifurcation analysis [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], we adopted the adaptive grid technique. Different from the conventional numerical method for the bifurcation analysis, this method is easy to implement because it does not use the continuation technique, normal form, or an initial point to start the trace of bifurcation curves [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>In Sections <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec5">5</xref>, we will first review the mathematical model by Anderson et al. [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The numerical study for a nontreatment case is shown in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3">Section 3</xref>. In <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4">Section 4</xref>, we explore the effect of periodically pulsed therapies delivered at the tumor site. The stability condition of each tumor-free fixed point is analyzed and their dynamics and biological implications are presented. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec5"> Section 5</xref> provides a brief summary and discussion.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. The Mathematical Model</title><p>Although tumor antigen-stimulated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells can produce IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> (Th1) or IL-4 (Th2) and both these cytokines can recruit other tumoricidal cells to the tumor site [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], tumor rejection is mediated by IL-4 [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Some investigations have reported that Th2 cells are more advantageous compared with Th1 cells in the eradication of CTL-resistant tumors [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. A human clinical trial on a vaccine also showed that overall recovery from cancer is related to the ratio of vaccine-induced Th2 immunity and antitumor Th2 cells can be found in cancer patients [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Based on these data showing the potential importance of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells combined with Th2-related antitumor cytokine interactions in tumor clearance, we investigated how these diverse mechanisms interact with periodically pulsed therapies to dictate the antitumor function in this setting.</p><p>Let <italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, and <italic>z</italic> denote tumor cells, CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, and antitumor cytokine (IL-4 or any antitumor cytokine produced by Th2), respectively. The proposed model is given as follows:<disp-formula id="EEq1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable style="T17"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="HCYDAEJ0"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="11.05pt" depth="7.06999pt"/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace height="11.05pt" depth="7.06999pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="WJYZALB1"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="WJYZALB2"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>r</italic>(1 &#x02212; <italic>x</italic>/<italic>K</italic>) is the per capita tumor growth rate and <italic>&#x003b4;xz</italic>/(<italic>m</italic> + <italic>x</italic>) denotes the loss of tumor cells caused by the antitumor cytokine. The fraction <italic>&#x003b2;xy</italic>/(<italic>k</italic> + <italic>x</italic>) is the proliferation of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells through interactions with tumor cells, and <italic>&#x003b1;xy</italic>/(<italic>b</italic> + <italic>x</italic>) denotes the production of antitumor cytokines secreted by CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. The expression <italic>ay</italic> is the apoptosis (natural death) of T cells, <italic>&#x003bc;z</italic> denotes the loss of cytokine, and <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) are immunotherapy treatments that may be time dependent.</p><p>A logistic growth equation for tumor cells and Michaelis-Menten kinetics for all the functional forms with different half saturation constants are used. Consequently, it is assumed that the tumor's growth is limited and the production of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and the antitumor cytokine due to tumor cells is also limited.</p><p>All the parameters, <italic>r</italic>, <italic>K</italic>, <italic>m</italic>, <italic>&#x003b4;</italic>, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, <italic>k</italic>, <italic>a</italic>, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, and <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>, are positive constants. <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02a7e;0 and <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02a7e;0 denote treatments of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and the antitumor cytokine per unit time, respectively. The parameters and their biological interpretations are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>. The time unit is one day and all populations have the unit of volume.</p><p>We will first explore the dynamics of the model (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>) by one-, two-, and three-parameter bifurcation diagrams for nontreatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Numerical Study for No Treatment Case</title><p>According to the analytical study by Anderson et al. [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], there are three equilibriums for a nontreatment case: <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub>(0,0, 0), <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>K</italic>, 0,0), and the interior steady state <italic>E</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>(<italic>x</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, <italic>y</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, <italic>z</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>), where <italic>x</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, <italic>y</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, <italic>z</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> &#x0003e; 0. The steady states <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub>(0,0, 0) and <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>K</italic>, 0,0) exist for all parameter values. The equilibrium <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub>, where the population is zero, is always a local saddle point. The equilibrium <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub> is asymptotically stable if the antigenicity of the tumor (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>) is less than a critical value (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>) and a saddle point if <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> &#x0003e; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, where<disp-formula id="EEq2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>The unique interior equilibrium <italic>E</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>(<italic>x</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, <italic>y</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, <italic>z</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>) exists if and only if <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> &#x0003e; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, where <italic>x</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> &#x0003c; <italic>K</italic>. It means that the tumor size of the interior steady state is always smaller than its carrying capacity [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>To study the stability of <italic>E</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> numerically, we use <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = 0 in the third equation of (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>), which is equivalent to<disp-formula id="EEq3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>When the value of <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> is large, <italic>dz</italic>/<italic>dt</italic> is large unless (1/<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>)<italic>&#x003b1;xy</italic>/(<italic>b</italic> + <italic>x</italic>) &#x02212; <italic>z</italic> &#x02248; 0. Any trajectory tends to approach the surface <italic>S</italic>(<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>) = (1/<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>)<italic>&#x003b1;xy</italic>/(<italic>b</italic> + <italic>x</italic>) rapidly and remains close to the surface, where <italic>S</italic>(<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>) refers to a slow manifold. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1"> Figure 1</xref> shows this phenomenon.</p><p>Because the positive equilibrium <italic>E</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> is located on the slow manifold, <italic>dz</italic>/<italic>dt</italic> &#x0003e; 0 if <italic>z</italic> &#x0003c; <italic>S</italic>(<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>) and <italic>dz</italic>/<italic>dt</italic> &#x0003c; 0 if <italic>z</italic> &#x0003e; <italic>S</italic>(<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>). The stability property of <italic>E</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> can be obtained from the following reduced system:<disp-formula id="EEq4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mtable style="T17"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="WJYZALB3"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="11.05pt" depth="7.06999pt"/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace height="11.05pt" depth="7.06999pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="WJYZALB4"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Let <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> be the positive equilibrium of (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq4">4</xref>). Then,<disp-formula id="EEq5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="13.6pt" depth="9.65999pt"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.32999pt" depth="0.23pt"/><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.32999pt" depth="0.23pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="7.08pt" depth="0.23pt"/><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="7.08pt" depth="0.23pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="6.57999pt" depth="0.23pt"/><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="6.57999pt" depth="0.23pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="13.6pt" depth="9.65999pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>The Jacobian matrix at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is<disp-formula id="EEq6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mtable style="T3"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo id="EAAAA02B0HCCA"/><mml:malignmark/><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="9.899pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace height="9.899pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>The determinant of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">det</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is positive because &#x02202;<italic>S</italic>/&#x02202;<italic>y</italic> = (1/<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>)<italic>&#x003b1;x</italic>/(<italic>b</italic> + <italic>x</italic>) &#x0003e; 0. The trace of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> can be simplified as<disp-formula id="EEq7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="13.6pt" depth="8.91pt"/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace height="13.6pt" depth="8.91pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> When <italic>m</italic> is large, we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. For example, (<italic>K</italic> &#x02212; <italic>x</italic>)/(<italic>m</italic> + <italic>x</italic>) &#x0003c; 1 if <italic>m</italic> &#x0003e; <italic>K</italic> and thus <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. So, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is stable if <italic>m</italic> is large. A Hopf bifurcation occurs if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> because <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">det</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. Therefore, the parameter values satisfy<disp-formula id="EEq8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M19"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>at a Hopf bifurcation point, where <italic>x</italic> = <italic>ka</italic>/(<italic>&#x003b2;</italic> &#x02212; <italic>a</italic>). The stability condition is summarized in the following theorem.</p><p>
<statement id="thm1"><title>Theorem 1 . </title><p>The positive equilibrium <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02217;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is locally stable if <italic>m</italic> is large or if the parameter values satisfy<disp-formula id="EEq9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M21"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>x</italic> = <italic>ka</italic>/(<italic>&#x003b2;</italic> &#x02212; <italic>a</italic>) &#x0003e; 0.</p></statement>
</p><p>Numerical examples showing the dynamics of small or moderate value of <italic>m</italic> will be presented by using the one- and two-parameter bifurcation diagrams, which will be addressed at the end of this section.</p><p>A natural question that follows from the aforementioned study is how other key parameters, such as the maximum CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell production rate (antigenicity of the tumor) (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>), half saturation constant of the tumor killing rate (<italic>m</italic>), and half saturation constant of the antitumor cytokine production rate (<italic>b</italic>), affect the system. To observe these effects, we let <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, <italic>m</italic>, and <italic>b</italic> be the bifurcation parameters and the parameter domain be [<italic>m</italic>, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, <italic>b</italic>] = [1,200]&#x000d7;[0,1]&#x000d7;[1,300]. Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq8">8</xref>) implies <italic>b</italic>(<italic>m</italic>, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>) = <italic>x</italic><sup>2</sup>(<italic>K</italic> &#x02212; <italic>m</italic> &#x02212; 2<italic>x</italic>)/(<italic>x</italic><sup>2</sup> + <italic>mk</italic>), which corresponds to the Hopf bifurcations. Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq2">2</xref>) represents a plane of transcritical bifurcations. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2"> Figure 2</xref> shows a three-parameter bifurcation diagram. The equilibrium <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub> is stable/unstable in the region to the right/left of the plane of transcritical bifurcations. The equilibrium <italic>E</italic><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> exists in the region to the left of the plane and is stable/unstable in the region above/under the surface of Hopf bifurcations.</p><p>From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, we conclude that the tumor is uncontrollable when <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> is extremely small, even though both tumor killing and antitumor production rates are high. This result implies that the health of the immune system activation plays a role in fighting the cancer. Moreover, if <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> is not extremely small, tumor regression and relapse cycles later can occur through enhancing the tumor killing and antitumor cytokine rates. After repeating several cycles, the tumor can be controlled and remains at a smaller size. However, the tumor still cannot be cleared completely without treatment.</p><p>We also investigate the aforementioned phenomenon from different viewpoints. The tumor oscillation for a low tumor killing rate <italic>m</italic> can be clearly seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>. Moreover, we confirm our results by using <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> and <italic>m</italic> as two bifurcation parameters in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>. For <italic>b</italic> = 100, a two-parameter bifurcation diagram shows that a limit cycle exists for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>0</sub> &#x0003c; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> &#x0003c; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>1</sub>. The interval of existence of the limit cycle decreases with an increase in <italic>m</italic>. A large tumor mass occurs when <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> is extremely small (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic> &#x0003c; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>). Notably, the numerical bifurcation curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> validates the theoretical result of (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq9">9</xref>).</p><p>A one-bifurcation parameter by using <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> as the bifurcation parameter is also shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>. When <italic>b</italic> = 100 and <italic>m</italic> = 100, the size of the tumor decreases overall as the strength of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> increases. Moreover, the system undergoes a Hopf bifurcation at <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.113 and 0.247. The amplitude of the limit cycle decreases and then disappears. However, the tumor cannot be eradicated without treatment. Notably, the result of this numerical one-bifurcation parameter diagram agrees with the analytical result by Anderson et al. [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] for this moderate value of <italic>m</italic> (<italic>m</italic> = 100). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref> also confirms the results of the three-parameter bifurcation diagram of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</p><p>Thus, the model does not allow for the eradication of the tumor in the nontreatment case. For this reason, we now study the role of strengthening the immune response through immunotherapy.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>4. Immunotherapy</title><p>Because recent active immunotherapeutic approaches have used cytokine either alone or jointly with adoptive immunotherapy [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and vaccination injections are administered repeatedly, in general [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], we explore the effects of periodically pulsed therapies with either CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells or Th2-related antitumor cytokine IL-4 alone or them together. Mathematically, we assume the therapy is administered at a dosage of <italic>d</italic> every <italic>&#x003c4;</italic> days during a patient's lifetime. We administer either <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> or <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> or both to the tumor site, where <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> represents the implementation of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> indicates the implementation of IL-4. The discussion of injection of IL-4 to the tumor site can be seen in [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The external infusions <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> are modelled by Dirac Delta functions as (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq10">10</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq11">11</xref>), where <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub> are dosages of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and IL-4 per infusion, respectively.</p><p>The parameter values are taken from [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>. These parameter values have been derived from data in the literature. The parameter for the carrying capacity <italic>K</italic> was derived by Kronik et al. [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The parameter value for the intrinsic growth rate <italic>r</italic> of the tumor was calculated from its doubling time by Kronik et al. [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and Plesnicar et al. [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The loss rate of IL-4 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> was estimated from its half-life by Conlon et al. [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and Perez-Diez et al. [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The values of the apoptosis <italic>a</italic> of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells ranging from 0.01 to 0.18 are adopted from various references [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Other parameter values are from Anderson et al. [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] with <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> = 50, <italic>r</italic> = 0.027, and <italic>a</italic> = 0.02.</p><p>The choice of cancer treatment depends on many factors, including the stage and grade at diagnosis, the dosage and frequency of administration, and the strength of a patient's immune system. A treatment strategy may be effective for one patient but fail for another. However, the actual dosage and frequency of T cells and IL-4 are not easily determined because of the wide variation across clinical studies [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Because most of the treatment periods have been weekly, we set the treatment cycle to be one week and adopted the estimation of doses of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and IL-4 from [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].<disp-formula id="EEq10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mtable style="T17"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="IRVMROI5"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.23pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.23pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="EEq11"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="EEq11EAAAAEBCA"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="IRVMROI6"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.23pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.23pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2">Section 2</xref>, we showed that the antigenicity of the tumor (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>) is a key parameter. For the nontreatment case, the tumor tends to reach its maximum burden with very low values of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> and remains at a small size for large values of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>. The critical value is approximately <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> = 0.0202. Therefore, we will present two realizations representing low (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015 &#x0003c; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>) and high tumor antigenicity (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1 &#x0003e; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>) in our numerical studies. Furthermore, we will theoretically explore the stability of the tumor-free solution for each case because it indicates whether a treatment can prevent tumor recurrence after attempting to remove the tumor. We will first study the stability of the tumor-free fixed point and its dynamics when CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are administered alone.</p><sec id="sec4.1"><title>4.1. Adoptive Cellular Immunotherapy Alone (<italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> &#x0003e; 0, <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> = 0)</title><p>Define the map <italic>F</italic>(<italic>X</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>Y</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>Z</italic><sub>0</sub>) = (<italic>X</italic>(<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>), <italic>Y</italic>(<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>), <italic>Z</italic>(<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>)) to be the solution of (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq10">10</xref>) at <italic>t</italic> = <italic>&#x003c4;</italic> with initial condition (<italic>X</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>Y</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>Z</italic><sub>0</sub>).</p><p>
<statement id="thm2"><title>Theorem 2 . </title><p>Let <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = &#x02211;<sub><italic>n</italic>=0</sub><sup><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sup><italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub><italic>&#x003b4;</italic>(<italic>t</italic> &#x02212; <italic>n&#x003c4;</italic>). Then, the tumor-free fixed point (0, <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>, 0) is unstable, where <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub>/(1 &#x02212; <italic>e</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>a&#x003c4;</italic></sup>).</p></statement>
</p><p>
<statement id="proof1"><title>Proof</title><p>Consider the tumor-free case where <italic>x</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = 0. From (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq10">10</xref>), we have <italic>z</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = 0, and <italic>y</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) satisfies<disp-formula id="EEq12"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M23"><mml:mtable style="T17"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02032;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="EBIRLRB7"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.53pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.53pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="EBIRLRB8"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.63599pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace height="8.63599pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="10pt"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0,1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>The tumor-free fixed point (0, <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>, 0), where <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub>/(<italic>e</italic><sup><italic>a&#x003c4;</italic></sup> &#x02212; 1), satisfies <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic>y</italic>(<italic>n&#x003c4;</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup>) for <italic>n</italic> = 0,1, 2,&#x02026;. The periodic solution <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> satisfying (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq12">12</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is given by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> for <italic>t</italic> &#x02208; [<italic>n&#x003c4;</italic>, <italic>n</italic>(<italic>&#x003c4;</italic> + 1)), <italic>n</italic> = 0,1, 2,&#x02026;. To study the stability of the tumor-free fixed point (0, <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>, 0), we assume <italic>x</italic> = <italic>&#x003f5;T</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>O</italic>(<italic>&#x003f5;</italic><sup>2</sup>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <italic>z</italic> = <italic>&#x003f5;E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>O</italic>(<italic>&#x003f5;</italic><sup>2</sup>). So, <italic>x</italic>&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>&#x003f5;T</italic>&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>O</italic>(<italic>&#x003f5;</italic><sup>2</sup>). From (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>), we have <italic>T</italic>&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>rT</italic>(<italic>t</italic>). A small tumor grows with time at a rate <italic>r</italic>. Therefore, the tumor-free fixed point (0, <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>, 0) is unstable.</p></statement>
</p><p>The numerical investigations for <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> &#x0003e; 0 and <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> = 0 with <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015 and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1 are shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10(a)</xref>, respectively. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6(a)</xref>, the case of low tumor antigenicity, it shows that if a small dosage of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells is delivered alone, the tumor will grow to a larger size (<italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>). The model exhibits bistability with a large dosage of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. The tumor can be either controlled to a small size or grown close to its maximum mass. This result indicates that the long-term fate of the tumor with the treatment of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells depends on the size when it is detected. For high antigenicity of the tumor, a globally closed curve exists when the dosage of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells is small. The amplitude of the closed curve decreases with an increase in the dosage of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. As the dosage increases further, the oscillations spiral to a unique globally stable fixed point <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, leading to a small, persistent tumor, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10(a)</xref>. In general, the immunotherapy does not allow for the complete clearance of the tumor when CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are administered alone.</p><p>We now explore the tumor-free stability condition and the dynamics of periodically pulsed therapy when IL-4 is administered independently.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>4.2. Immunotherapy with IL-4 Alone (<italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0, <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; 0)</title><p>The following theorem demonstrates the tumor-free stability condition when <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0, <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; 0.</p><p>
<statement id="thm3"><title>Theorem 3 . </title><p>Let <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = &#x02211;<sub><italic>n</italic>=0</sub><sup><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sup><italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub><italic>&#x003b4;</italic>(<italic>t</italic> &#x02212; <italic>n&#x003c4;</italic>). Then, the tumor-free fixed point (0,0, <italic>z</italic><sub>0</sub>) is stable if <italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub> &#x0003e; <italic>r&#x003c4;&#x003bc;m</italic>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>, where <italic>z</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub>/(1 &#x02212; <italic>e</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>&#x003bc;&#x003c4;</italic></sup>).</p></statement>
</p><p>
<statement id="proof2"><title>Proof</title><p>Consider the tumor-free case where <italic>x</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = 0. From (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq11">11</xref>), we have <italic>y</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = 0, and <italic>z</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) satisfies<disp-formula id="EEq14"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mtable style="T17"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02032;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="EBIRLRB9"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="5.95pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.53pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.53pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo id="EBIRLRB10"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.63599pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace height="8.63599pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="10pt"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0,1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Similar to the proof in <xref ref-type="statement" rid="thm2">Theorem 2</xref>, we have <italic>z</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub>/(1 &#x02212; <italic>e</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>&#x003bc;&#x003c4;</italic></sup>) and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> for <italic>t</italic> &#x02208; [<italic>n&#x003c4;</italic>, <italic>n</italic>(<italic>&#x003c4;</italic> + 1)), <italic>n</italic> = 0,1, 2,&#x02026;. To study the stability of the tumor-free fixed point (0,0, <italic>z</italic><sub>0</sub>), we assume <italic>x</italic> = <italic>&#x003f5;T</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>O</italic>(<italic>&#x003f5;</italic><sup>2</sup>), <italic>y</italic> = <italic>&#x003f5;C</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>O</italic>(<italic>&#x003f5;</italic><sup>2</sup>), and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. From (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>), we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02032;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. Solving for <italic>T</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), the solution at <italic>t</italic> = <italic>&#x003c4;</italic> is given by <italic>T</italic>(<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>) = <italic>T</italic>(0)<italic>e</italic><sup><italic>r&#x003c4;</italic>&#x02212;<italic>&#x003b4;d</italic><sub>IL4</sub>/<italic>m&#x003bc;</italic></sup>. The stability condition satisfies <italic>T</italic>(<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>) &#x0003c; <italic>T</italic>(0). Therefore, the tumor-free fixed point (0,0, <italic>z</italic><sub>0</sub>) is stable if <italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub> &#x0003e; <italic>r&#x003c4;&#x003bc;m</italic>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>.</p></statement>
</p><p>From a study by Anderson et al. [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], we know that the tumor-free state is stable if <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; <italic>r&#x003bc;m</italic>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> for the continuous injection of <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub>. For the periodically pulsed therapy, the stability condition is <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; <italic>rK&#x003c4;&#x003bc;m</italic>/<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>. Using the parameter values in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>, the threshold for the stable tumor-free fixed point is <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; 94.5&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>. This dosage is seven times larger than that used in the continuous infusion of IL-4 [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10(a)</xref> also show that the tumor can be suppressed completely if the dosage is above 94.5&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>. When the dosage is less than 94.5&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>, the tumor will grow to a size near its carrying capacity for a patient with low tumor antigenicity or oscillate for a patient with high tumor antigenicity.</p><p>In the next subsection, we study whether the combined therapy provides a more effective treatment for curing a malignant tumor.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>4.3. Immunotherapy with Both CD4<sup>+</sup> T Cells and IL-4 (<italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> &#x0003e; 0, <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; 0)</title><p>Consider joint periodically pulsed therapy, where a dose of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells at <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub> and a dose of IL-4 at <italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub> are given. One cycle of the treatment is &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> = <italic>&#x003c4;</italic> days. The proof of the stability for the tumor-free fixed point is similar to those of Theorems <xref ref-type="statement" rid="thm2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="statement" rid="thm3">3</xref> and will be omitted.</p><p>
<statement id="thm4"><title>Theorem 4 . </title><p>Let <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = &#x02211;<sub><italic>n</italic>=0</sub><sup><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sup><italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub><italic>&#x003b4;</italic>(<italic>t</italic> &#x02212; <italic>n&#x003c4;</italic>) and <italic>l</italic><sub>2</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = &#x02211;<sub><italic>n</italic>=0</sub><sup><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sup><italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub><italic>&#x003b4;</italic>(<italic>t</italic> &#x02212; <italic>n&#x003c4;</italic>). Then, the tumor-free fixed point (0, <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>z</italic><sub>0</sub>) is stable if <italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub> &#x0003e; <italic>r&#x003c4;&#x003bc;m</italic>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>, where <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub>/(1 &#x02212; <italic>e</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>a&#x003c4;</italic></sup>) and <italic>z</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic>d</italic><sub>IL4</sub>/(1 &#x02212; <italic>e</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>&#x003bc;&#x003c4;</italic></sup>).</p></statement>
</p><p>We will now explore how the combined pulsed treatment of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and IL-4 affects the system numerically. In general, for both <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015 and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1, there are three different regions and four steady states, at the most. We denote these regions as <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, <italic>E</italic><sub>2</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, and <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, respectively, where <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub> is the tumor-free steady state and <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> is a positive steady state, where <italic>i</italic> = 1,2, 3. The tumor size increases with the subindex for the positive steady state. Note that when the treatment of adopting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells is used, the amount of CTL ranges from 1.06&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup> to 72.61&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup> per infusion, according to [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Therefore, we explore the dynamics of the combined pulsed treatment for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015 and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1, with dosages ranging from 0 to 100&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>. The discussion for a low antigenicity (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015) case follows.</p><sec id="sec4.3.1"><title>4.3.1. Dynamics and Biological Implications for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015</title><p>There are mainly three categories for the dynamics from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6(a)</xref>. As the amount of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells increases from R1 to R2, the fold bifurcation occurs. By contrast, the system undergoes transcritical bifurcation when the amount of IL-4 augments from part of R1/R2 to R3. Here is a list showing the dynamics and biological implications for each region.<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>Two steady states, <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, exist in region R1. In R1, the range of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells is from 0 to 32&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup> and the range of IL-4 is from 0 to 94.5&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup> per injection. <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> is the only stable fixed point and the tumor growth is uncontrollable.</p></list-item><list-item><p>As the amount of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells increases from region R1 to R2, two additional fixed points, <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> and <italic>E</italic><sub>2</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, are born due to the fold bifurcation; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6(a)</xref>, where <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> is stable. In R2, two stable fixed points <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> and <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> exist. Tumor burden can either be controlled to a very small size (0.0422&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>) or grow to near its carrying capacity (991.3218&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). However, the tumor cannot be eradicated completely. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6"> Figure 6(b)</xref> shows changes in dynamics for <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub> = 20 as the level of IL-4 changes. At <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub> = 20, the fold bifurcation occurs as the level of IL-4 increases from R1 to R2 and the transcritical bifurcation occurs as the amount of IL-4 changes from R2 to R3.</p></list-item><list-item><p>R3 is a region where the dosage of IL-4 is very large. Three steady states, <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>E</italic><sub>2</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, and <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>, exist, where <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> are stable. Therefore, the solution will tend to either <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub> (the tumor-free state) or <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> (the tumor survives; the tumor size is close to its maximum burden) depending on the initial condition. This result means that the tumor can be cleared only if the tumor size is small when it is detected. Consequently, if the tumor can be detected earlier, the immunotherapy may succeed in clearing the tumor.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="sec4.3.2"><title>4.3.2. Dynamics and Biological Implications for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1</title><p>For a patient with high tumor antigenicity <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, polytherapy is more effective. The bifurcation diagram in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10(a)</xref> shows the different dynamics involved with various dosages of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and IL-4. As the amount of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells increases from the lower/upper part of R1 to R2, the Hopf/fold-homoclinic bifurcation occurs. By contrast, the system undergoes a transcritical bifurcation when the dosage of IL-4 augments from R1 or R2 to R3. The dynamics and the biological relevance are presented as follows:<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p><italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub> is unstable and <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> is a stable closed curve in the region R1. The tumor size oscillates in this region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>). A critical value of IL-4<sub><italic>c</italic></sub> exists. Below/above IL-4<sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, a Hopf/fold-homoclinic bifurcation occurs at the intersection of R1 and R2; see Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10(b)</xref>. When the system undergoes the fold-homoclinic bifurcation, the closed curve breaks and <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> develops to a stable node; see Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10(b)</xref>. The evolution of the fold-homoclinic bifurcation is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Figure 11</xref>. All orbits tend to curve under the iterations of <italic>F</italic> from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Figure 11</xref>. This result means that, with the help of immunotherapy, the tumor will spend a portion of the cycle near its maximal burden and the rest with a mass close to zero. Eventually, the tumor is controlled at a small dormant state. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10"> Figure 10(c)</xref> shows the profile of these diverse dynamics at <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub> = 20 as the amount of IL-4 crosses the different regions.</p></list-item><list-item><p>In region R2, the only stable fixed point <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> is a stable node. Immunotherapy can help to suppress the tumor to a very small size.</p></list-item><list-item><p>As we continue increasing the dosage of IL-4 from R1 to R3, the system experiences a transcritical bifurcation; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10(a)</xref>. The stable state <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> in R1 is lost and the tumor-free steady state <italic>E</italic><sub>0</sub> becomes stable in R3. Thus, the tumor can be eradicated completely in the region of R3.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>5. Results and Discussion</title><p>In this paper, we studied the effects of the periodically pulsed immunotherapy of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and Th2-related tumor suppression cytokine (IL-4) on tumor-immune interactions. Without treatment, for a patient with very low tumor antigenicity <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, the tumor will grow to its carrying capacity even when both the tumor killing <italic>m</italic> rate and antitumor production rate <italic>b</italic> are high. By contrast, tumor recurrence can be observed and its mass can be controlled to a smaller size if <italic>m</italic> or <italic>b</italic> is high and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> is not extremely small. The tumor cannot be eradicated without any treatment.</p><p>The effects of periodically pulsed administration with either CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells or the cytokine IL-4 or both are studied. The administration of the cytokine IL-4 alone can suppress the tumor completely for any level of tumor antigenicity when the dosage of cytokine is above 94.5&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>. When the level of IL-4 is less than 94.5&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup> and a patient has low tumor antigenicity, immunotherapy fails to stop tumor growth. However, if tumor antigenicity is high, a stable closed curve exists and a patient will experience tumor regression and relapse. Notably, these stable closed curves have not been observed in the case of low tumor antigenicity.</p><p>With the periodically pulsed treatment of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells alone, the tumor-free state is not stable and the tumor cannot be eradicated. When an average or a large number of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are infused, the tumor can be reduced to a smaller size for a patient with high tumor antigenicity. The tumor can be either controlled to a very small size or raised near to its maximum burden for a patient with low tumor antigenicity. This result suggests that the tumor can be regulated by administering CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells alone for a patient having a strong immune system or whose tumor has been diagnosed at an early stage.</p><p>Our study shows that periodically pulsed treatment with IL-4 may be more effective either as a monotherapy or along with the CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell treatment. Although implementing a high dose of IL-4 can clear the tumor, this treatment may overboost the immune system and have a detrimental effect on the patient. These side effects may outweigh the benefits of tumor eradication. The treatment with CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells alone does not provide a satisfactory outcome; the tumor-free state does not exist for any level of tumor antigenicity. Nevertheless, an average dose of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells is sufficient to maintain the tumor at a small dormant state. Together with cytokine IL-4, the amount of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells can be reduced to maintain the tumor at a smaller size within host. Thus, the combined effects may be the best option.</p><p>The tumor microenvironment is exceedingly complex. Many issues are worthy of discussion. For example, what is the optimal treatment strategy if we administer drugs for some periods and use various dosages? From our study, administering CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells alone cannot clear the tumor. Nevertheless, research has shown that a blockade of CTL-associated antigen 4 (CTLA-4) on T cells can heighten in vivo cytotoxicity and improve the antitumor activity, including killing a well-established large tumor [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Further investigations of tumor-reactive CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells with cytotoxic activities for more complicated models may provide prominent advantages for the treatment of human malignancies.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>J. L. Yu acknowledges the Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica, in Taiwan, for supporting her summer visiting.</p></ack><sec><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest regarding the publication of this paper.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B29"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><comment>SkinCancerFundation, &#x0201c;What is melanoma?&#x0201d; 2016, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.skincancer.org/skin-cancer-information/melanoma">http://www.skincancer.org/skin-cancer-information/melanoma</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><comment>MedicineNet.com, Melanoma introduction, 1996, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medicinenet.com/script/main/art.asp?articlekey=20093page=9">http://www.medicinenet.com/script/main/art.asp?articlekey=20093page=9</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastiaannet</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beukema</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiation therapy following lymph node dissection in melanoma patients: Treatment, outcome and complications</article-title><source><italic>Cancer Treatment Reviews</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-13844296744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctrv.2004.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15707701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shakir</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasul</surname><given-names>K. I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy induced cardiomyopathy: pathogenesis, monitoring and management</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Medicine Research</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4021/jocmr2009.02.1225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22505958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Restifo</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adoptive cell transfer as personalized immunotherapy for human cancer</article-title><source><italic>Science</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>348</volume><issue>6230</issue><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaa4967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25838374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Lint</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilgenhof</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heirman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimized dendritic cell-based immunotherapy for melanoma: the TriMix-formula</article-title><source><italic>Cancer Immunology, Immunotherapy</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>63</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00262-014-1558-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84906939134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24878889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>S. R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karamalis</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. F. A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of a CD8<sup>+</sup> cytotoxic T lymphocyte response by cross-priming requires cognate CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell help</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</italic></source><year>1997</year><volume>186</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.186.1.65</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0030848161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9206998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafond-Walker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardoll</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitsky</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The central role of CD4+ T cells in the antitumor immune response</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>188</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2357</fpage><lpage>2368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0032433127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.188.12.2357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9858522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunotherapy of cytotoxic T cell-resistant tumors by T helper 2 cells: an eotaxin and STAT6-dependent process</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>197</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20021683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0037415596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>W. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramson</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CD4+ T-cell-mediated anti-tumor immunity can be uncoupled from autoimmunity via the STAT4/STAT6 signaling axis</article-title><source><italic>European Journal of Immunology</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>39</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1252</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-67649966551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eji.200839152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19338001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akpinarli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Naive tumor-specific CD4+ T cells differentiated in vivo eradicate established melanoma</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>207</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-77949530108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20091921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20156973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Diez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joncker</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CD4 cells can be more efficient at tumor rejection than CD8 cells</article-title><source><italic>Blood</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>109</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>5346</fpage><lpage>5354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-34249990107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2006-10-051318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17327412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eftimie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramson</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Earn</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between the immune system and cancer: a brief review of non-spatial mathematical models</article-title><source><italic>Bulletin of Mathematical Biology</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>73</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">MR2770277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11538-010-9526-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">Zbl1209.92028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79151470316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20225137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eftimie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramson</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Earn</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling anti-tumor Th1 and TH2 immunity in the rejection of melanoma</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Theoretical Biology</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>265</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">MR2981535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2010.04.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-77954656225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20450922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.-L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Qualitative behavior of systems of tumor CD4<sup>+</sup> cytokine interactions with treatments</article-title><source><italic>Mathematical Methods in the Applied Sciences</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>38</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>4330</fpage><lpage>4344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mma.3370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">MR3434362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Panetta</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling immunotherapy of the tumo&#x02014;immune interaction</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Mathematical Biology</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002850050127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">Zbl0902.92012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0032160863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9785481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makalkin</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonlinear dynamics of immunogenic tumors: parameter estimation and global bifurcation analysis</article-title><source><italic>Bulletin of Mathematical Biology</italic></source><year>1994</year><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02460644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">Zbl0789.92019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0028388757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8186756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Vladar</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic response of cancer under the influence of immunological activity and therapy</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Theoretical Biology</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>227</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2003.11.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">MR2070271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15019501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>Y. A.</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Elements of Applied Bifurcation Theory</italic></source><year>1997</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="other">MR1711790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.-T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Periodically pulsed immunotherapy in a mathematical model of tumor-immune interaction</article-title><source><italic>International Journal of Bifurcation and Chaos</italic></source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1350068, 13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">MR3063365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">Zbl1270.34143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H.-C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modified numerical method for bifurcations of fixed points of ODE systems with periodically pulsed inputs</article-title><source><italic>Applied Mathematics and Computation</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>236</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amc.2014.03.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">MR3197734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volpert</surname><given-names>O. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of angiogenesis by interleukin 4</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>188</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0032555937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.188.6.1039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9743522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Famatiga</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peripheral blood CD4+ T-cell response before postoperative active immunotherapy correlates with clinical outcome in metastatic melanoma</article-title><source><italic>Annals of Surgical Oncology</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>892</fpage><lpage>899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/aso.2004.02.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-16544371505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15383418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slager</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Minne</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CD4+ Th2 cell recognition of HLA-DR-restricted epitopes derived from CAMEL: A tumor antigen translated in an alternative open reading frame</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Immunology</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>170</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1490</fpage><lpage>1497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0037307840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.170.3.1490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunotherapy and experimental approaches for metastatic melanoma</article-title><source><italic>Hematology/Oncology Clinics of North America</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0031661632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0889-8588(05)70029-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9759585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nestle</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alijagic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vaccination of melanoma patients with peptide- or tumor lysate-pulsed dendritic cells</article-title><source><italic>Nature Medicine</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0031941423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0398-328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Autologous glioma cell vaccine admixed with interleukin-4 gene transfected fibroblasts in the treatment of patients with malignant gliomas</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Translational Medicine</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>5, article no. 67</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-40149090821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-5-67</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Attanucci</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cytokine gene therapy of gliomas: Effective induction of therapeutic immunity to intracranial tumors by peripheral immunization with interleukin-4 transduced glioma cells</article-title><source><italic>Gene Therapy</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>1157</fpage><lpage>1166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0034886741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.gt.3301496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11509946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kronik</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kogan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000f6;lfl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving T-cell immunotherapy for melanoma through a mathematically motivated strategy: efficacy in numbers?</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Immunotherapy</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CJI.0b013e318236054c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84856843608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22306899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plesnicar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klanjscek</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Modic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actual doubling time values of pulmonary metastases from malignant melanoma</article-title><source><italic>ANZ Journal of Surgery</italic></source><year>1978</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1445-2197.1978.tb05799.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0017849455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conlon</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabstein</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interleukin-4 (B-cell stimulatory factor-1) augments the in vivo generation of cytotoxic cells in immunosuppressed animals</article-title><source><italic>Biotechnology Therapeutics</italic></source><year>1989</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0024857899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2562642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrd</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adoptive T cell therapy using antigen-specific CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell clones for the treatment of patients with metastatic melanoma: <italic>in vivo</italic> persistence, migration, and antitumor effect of transferred T cells</article-title><source><italic>Proceedings of the National Acadamy of Sciences of the United States of America</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>16168</fpage><lpage>16173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.242600099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0037058993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunderlich</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer regression and autoimmunity in patients after clonal repopulation with antitumor lymphocytes</article-title><source><italic>Science</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>298</volume><issue>5594</issue><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1076514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0037174674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plautz</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukowski</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>T-cell adoptive immunotherapy of metastatic renal cell carcinoma</article-title><source><italic>Urology</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>54</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0032859879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0090-4295(99)00303-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10510917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><comment>Wikipedia, Whitebloodcell, 2016, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolchok</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AntiCTLA-4 antibody therapy: Immune monitoring during clinical development of a novel immunotherapy</article-title><source><italic>Seminars in Oncology</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>37</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-78449243490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.seminoncol.2010.09.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21074063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quezada</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peggs</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumor-reactive CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells develop cytotoxic activity and eradicate large established melanoma after transfer into lymphopenic hosts</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>207</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20091918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-77949522803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20156971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shklovskaya</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tumour-specific CD4 T cells eradicate melanoma via indirect recognition of tumour-derived antigen</article-title><source><italic>Immunology &#x00026; Cell Biology</italic></source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84959516502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/icb.2016.14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26837456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makarov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merghoub</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic basis for clinical response to CTLA-4 blockade in melanoma</article-title><source><italic>The New England Journal of Medicine</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>2189</fpage><lpage>2199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1406498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25409260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolchok</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saenger</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanism of anti-CTLA-4 activity and the negative regulation of T-cell activation.</article-title><source><italic>The Oncologist</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-58749096691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.13-S4-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19001145</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The slow manifold <italic>z</italic> = (1/<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>)<italic>&#x003b1;xy</italic>/(<italic>b</italic> + <italic>x</italic>) with some selected trajectories.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>A three-parameter bifurcation diagram using <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, <italic>m</italic>, and <italic>b</italic> as bifurcation parameters. Parameter values are taken from [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], where <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 0.01, <italic>a</italic> = 0.03, <italic>b</italic> = 10<sup>2</sup>, <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> = 0.1, <italic>k</italic> = 10<sup>3</sup>, <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> = 50, <italic>m</italic> = 10<sup>2</sup>, <italic>K</italic> = 10<sup>3</sup>, <italic>r</italic> = 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The tumor size oscillates for small <italic>m</italic>. Parameter values used here are the same as those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> except <italic>m</italic> = 50, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1. The initial condition is [0.5,0.01,0].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.003"/></fig><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>A two-parameter bifurcation diagram using <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> and <italic>m</italic> as bifurcation parameters at <italic>b</italic> = 100. Parameter values used here are the same as those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.004"/></fig><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>A phase parameter bifurcation diagram using <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> as the bifurcation parameter. Parameter values adopted here are the same as those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.005"/></fig><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>(a) The bifurcation diagram for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015. (b) The various dynamics at <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub> = 20.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.006"/></fig><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The pictures (a) and (b) represent the evolution of the tumor for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015. The initial condition is [0.5,0.01,0].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.007"/></fig><fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>The pictures (a) and (b) represent the evolution of the tumor for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.015. The initial condition is [0.1,0.01,0].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.008"/></fig><fig id="fig9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>The pictures (a) and (b) represent the time evolution of the tumor for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1. The initial condition is [0.1,0.01,0].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.009"/></fig><fig id="fig10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>(a) The bifurcation diagram for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1. (b) The detailed development of the fold-homoclinic bifurcation. (c) The change of dynamics at <italic>d</italic><sub>CD4<sup>+</sup></sub> = 20.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.010"/></fig><fig id="fig11" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>The evolution of the fold-homoclinic bifurcation for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 0.1, CD4<sup>+</sup> T = 10. (a) A stable closed curve exists when IL-4 &#x0003c; 70. (b) A nonhyperbolic fixed point (<italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>) appears on the curve IL-4 = 76.23, and the curve becomes homoclinic to <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>. (c) <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup> splits into a saddle (<italic>E</italic><sub>2</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>) and a stable node (<italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub><sup><italic>&#x02217;</italic></sup>) when IL-4 &#x0003e; 76.23. All orbits are attracted to the curve under the map <italic>F</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMMM2017-2906282.011"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Parameters, biological meanings, and units.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter </th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Biological meaning </th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unit</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>r</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intrinsic growth rate of the tumor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>K</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Carrying capacity of the tumor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009; cm<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Maximum tumor killing rate by antitumor cytokine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>m</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Half saturation constant of the tumor killing rate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009; cm<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Maximum CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell production rate (antigenicity of the tumor)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009; day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Half saturation constant of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell production rate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009; cm<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>a</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Death rate of the CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Maximum production rate of the antitumor cytokine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>b</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Half saturation constant of antitumor cytokine production rate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009; cm<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antitumor cytokine loss rate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>l</italic>
<sub>1</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Treatment of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cm<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>l</italic>
<sub>2</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment of cytokine (IL-4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cm<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Parameter values.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;<italic>&#x003b1;</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>a</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>b</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>m</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>K</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>r</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.027</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>