<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Syst Biol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Systems Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1752-0509</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477391</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2430945</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1752-0509-2-43</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-2-43</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mathematical modeling and analysis of insulin clearance <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koschorreck</surname><given-names>Markus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>koschorreck@mpi-magdeburg.mpg.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>Ernst Dieter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>gilles@mpi-magdeburg.mpg.de</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Max Planck Institute for Dynamics of Complex Technical Systems, Sandtorstr. 1, 39106 Magdeburg, Germany</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1752-0509/2/43"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Koschorreck and Gilles; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Koschorreck and Gilles; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Koschorreck
               Markus
               
               koschorreck@mpi-magdeburg.mpg.de
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Mathematical modeling and analysis of insulin clearance in vivo
         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Systems Biology 2(1): 43-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1752-0509(2008)2:1&#x0003c;43&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1752-0509</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Analyzing the dynamics of insulin concentration in the blood is necessary for a comprehensive understanding of the effects of insulin <italic>in vivo</italic>. Insulin removal from the blood has been addressed in many studies. The results are highly variable with respect to insulin clearance and the relative contributions of hepatic and renal insulin degradation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We present a dynamic mathematical model of insulin concentration in the blood and of insulin receptor activation in hepatocytes. The model describes renal and hepatic insulin degradation, pancreatic insulin secretion and nonspecific insulin binding in the liver. Hepatic insulin receptor activation by insulin binding, receptor internalization and autophosphorylation is explicitly included in the model. We present a detailed mathematical analysis of insulin degradation and insulin clearance. Stationary model analysis shows that degradation rates, relative contributions of the different tissues to total insulin degradation and insulin clearance highly depend on the insulin concentration.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study provides a detailed dynamic model of insulin concentration in the blood and of insulin receptor activation in hepatocytes. Experimental data sets from literature are used for the model validation. We show that essential dynamic and stationary characteristics of insulin degradation are nonlinear and depend on the actual insulin concentration.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Insulin regulates important physiological processes like cellular glucose uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] and gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The processes triggered by insulin are associated with widely spread diseases. Type I diabetes mellitus results from defective pancreatic insulin secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Insulin resistance, obesity and type II diabetes mellitus may result from defects in the insulin signaling system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] and are often accompanied by abnormalities in insulin degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Improving therapies of these maladies is a topic of intense investigation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><sec><title>Insulin dynamics <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p>A prerequisite for fully understanding the effects of insulin <italic>in vivo </italic>is to enlighten the fate of insulin after the injection or endogenous production. Much work has been done in past decades to study insulin kinetics in the blood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. In the last few years, efforts have been focused on analyzing the dynamics of insulin concentration after the subcutaneous injection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The resulting models describe insulin removal from the blood in a highly reduced way [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], whereas the subcutaneous tissue is usually modeled in more detail. Insulin traverses different compartments (e.g. the injection pocket and the interstitium) after the injection and can be degraded or temporarily stored within these compartments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>Long acting insulins tend to form dimers or hexamers in the subcutaneous tissue, whereas fast acting insulin analogues have a decreased ability to form oligomers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Oligomer formation slows down the transition of insulin from the injection pocket in the subcutaneous tissue to the blood. These effects are included in some models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. In other studies, insulin dynamics are linked with glucose dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. The corresponding models describe all involved processes in a highly reduced way.</p><p>There are also efforts to predict glucose concentration and to automate insulin dosage for individuals with impaired glucose levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. These efforts are first steps towards the development of an artificial pancreas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>In the last few decades, many different kinetics for insulin removal from the blood were proposed. The most frequently used kinetics are linear first order kinetics, Michaelis-Menten kinetics or a combination of both [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Due to the investigation of narrow concentration intervals, nonlinearity was difficult to demonstrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. The presence of nonlinearities due to saturable processes now is widely accepted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. However, insulin degradation is described as a linear first order process in most models. Allocation of insulin degradation to specific tissues is not performed in the models of insulin dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Therefore, no model-based analysis of the contributions of the liver and the kidney to the degradation process has been done. A prerequisite for such an analysis is the availability of a validated model describing all important processes.</p></sec><sec><title>Insulin receptor dynamics <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>There are several models in literature that describe insulin receptor dynamics <italic>in vitro</italic>. Most models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] focus on a subset of the occurring processes and lump several processes into single reaction steps. This reduces the number of model parameters and has to be done if there is only little experimental data and if there are many parameters to estimate. However, two recent <italic>in vitro </italic>models describe insulin receptor dynamics in more detail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>].</p><p>Sedaghat et al. combined models of insulin binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] and receptor internalization, recycling and degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] and extended them to a mathematical model of insulin signaling in adipocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Model parameters were taken from other models and <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments. The receptor part of this model includes the binding of two insulin molecules as well as phosphorylation, internalization, degradation and synthesis of the receptor. A very strong coupling between insulin binding and receptor phosphorylation is assumed. The second insulin molecule can only bind to the receptor if the receptor is phosphorylated. Dephosphorylation of the receptor (with simultaneous insulin dissociation) is only possible if only one insulin molecule is bound to the receptor. Phosphorylated receptors without insulin are not part of the model.</p><p>Hori et al. described receptor phosphorylation, internalization and recycling in Fao hepatoma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] at 100 <italic>nM </italic>insulin. They analyzed several models corresponding to different model assumptions and different levels of detail. Model parameters were estimated using experimental data sets from literature. The main limitations of the models of Hori et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] are that they are only valid at 100 <italic>nM </italic>insulin and that insulin binding is not explicitly included. Due to the high insulin concentration (100 <italic>nM</italic>), all receptors at the plasma membrane are assumed to be liganded. Hori et al. also provide a general model structure without parameterization that includes the binding of one insulin molecule to the receptor and is intended for variable insulin concentrations. As above, receptor dephosphorylation and insulin dissociation are coupled in all models. Insulin dissociation is a prerequisite for receptor dephosphorylation or the processes are lumped into a single step. In addition, most processes are assumed to be irreversible.</p><p>Thus, there are many couplings between different processes in all detailed receptor models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Insulin dynamics and insulin receptor dynamics <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p><italic>In vivo </italic>models from literature predict insulin or glucose concentrations in the blood after the injection of glucose or insulin. The physiological state of the involved insulin-responsive tissues, e.g. the activation of insulin receptors, cannot be obtained from these <italic>in vivo </italic>models, as their level of detail is quite low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Though insulin dynamics in the blood and insulin receptor activation are highly related, no detailed analysis of the interactions between these processes exists in literature. Hovorka et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] took a first step in this direction. However, the receptor part of their model only distinguishes between free receptors and receptors with bound insulin. In addition, the focus of this study is clearly on insulin kinetics.</p><p><italic>In vivo </italic>models describing hepatic processes in such a detailed way as <italic>in vitro </italic>models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] could be of great interest for a deeper understanding and a model based control of insulin and glucose dynamics. Additionally, a detailed model could serve as a starting point for modeling and analysis of the signaling cascades emerging from the hepatic insulin receptor <italic>in vivo</italic>. Due to combinatorial complexity in signal transduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>], reduced order modeling techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] will have to be used to describe insulin signaling comprehensively.</p><p>We present a literature-based mathematical model of insulin dynamics and hepatic insulin receptor activation in rats. Compared to other models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>], we describe receptor processes in more detail to get insights into the processes and into the connections between insulin dynamics and insulin receptor activation in hepatocytes. This enables us to simultaneously analyze insulin dynamics in the blood and insulin receptor dynamics in the liver. In contrast to other studies, we decouple insulin binding and dissociation from receptor phosphorylation, as there is experimental evidence that receptor phosphorylation does not affect insulin binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. In addition, we model receptor phosphorylation as a reversible process if insulin is bound to the receptor. We take experimentally determined <italic>in vitro </italic>parameters for each reaction, wherever this is possible. The result is a physiologically well founded mechanistic model that does not couple or lump different processes. Almost all processes were parameterized by values from literature. The remaining parameter values could be derived from physiological considerations.</p><p>Model validation is performed with experimental data sets from literature. We emphasize that the data sets used for the model validation are not used for parameter estimation. This corresponds to a strict separation of model construction and model validation which is frequently applied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. A very remarkable result of the model validation is that the model with parameters from literature is able to match experimental data sets.</p><p>We perform a detailed stationary analysis of the contributions of the liver and the kidney to insulin degradation and insulin clearance as well as of the activation state of hepatic insulin receptors under varying insulin concentrations.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>The model</title><p>The model consists of ordinary differential equations (ODEs) and describes the dynamic behavior of radioactively labeled and unlabeled insulin in the blood and the physiological state of hepatic insulin receptors. It can also be used for the injection of only labeled or only unlabeled insulin. Distinction between labeled and unlabeled insulin is necessary as unlabeled insulin is synthesized in the pancreas whereas labeled insulin is not. Therefore, in experiments with labeled insulin, the fraction of labeled insulin changes over time.</p><p>Almost all state variables in the model represent concentrations and are given in <italic>nM</italic>. Exceptions are the state variables <italic>Ins</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>and <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub </italic></sub>that represent amounts of substances and are given in <italic>nmol</italic>. All rates are given in <italic>nM</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup>. The rates describing insulin receptor dynamics (<italic>r</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>, <italic>i</italic><sub><italic>j </italic></sub>and <italic>f</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>, <italic>j &#x003b5; </italic>&#x02115;) refer to the hepatocyte volume <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>hep</italic></sub>. All other rates refer to blood plasma volume <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>. The executable model is given in MATLAB format in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>. We also provide the receptor part of the model as an independent model that can be used for the simulation of <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>).</p><sec><title>Important tissues and processes</title><p>The liver and the kidney are the most important insulin degrading tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. However, fat and muscle tissues also contribute to insulin degradation. In the following, we show that the insulin degradation rate of the fat tissue is small compared to the hepatic insulin degradation rate. According to Sedaghat et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>], the total receptor concentration in adipocytes is 10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>nM </italic>and the rate constant of receptor internalization is 3.5&#x000b7;10<sup>-5 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup>. Insulin receptors in hepatocytes have a minimal internalization rate constant of 2&#x000b7;10<sup>-4 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1 </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and a concentration of 40 <italic>nM </italic>(10<sup>5 </sup>receptors per hepatocyte [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], a hepatocyte is assumed to be a sphere with 20 <italic>&#x003bc;m </italic>diameter). 78% of the liver volume is occupied by hepatocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. Liver mass is about 5% of body weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>], the mass of the fat tissue is in the same order of magnitude. We postulate the same insulin binding characteristics to the receptor in both tissues. The product of receptor concentration and the kinetic parameter for receptor internalization in adipocytes is five orders of magnitude lower than in hepatocytes. Therefore, the contribution of the fat tissue to insulin degradation can be neglected. The contribution of the muscle tissue will not be analyzed either. No quantitative data was found and a qualitatively similar behavior in comparison to the liver is expected.</p><p>Hepatic insulin receptors have access to insulin molecules in the space of Disse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. The space of Disse (perisinusoidal space) contains blood plasma and is an extracellular space between liver sinusoids (special blood vessels) and hepatocytes. Insulin molecules from the space of Disse can be bound and are internalized together with the receptor. In the space of Disse, there is also nonspecific insulin binding to hepatocytes. Inside the cell, in the acidic endosomal compartment, insulin dissociates from the receptor and is degraded. The receptor then recycles to the cell surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>Our model explicitly describes dynamic insulin receptor activation in hepatocytes of the liver. Processes considered are insulin binding to the receptor, receptor autophosphorylation, internalization and recycling. Compared to other models of the insulin receptor which also include these processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>], we provide an extended description, model the <italic>in vivo </italic>situation and include reversible nonspecific insulin binding.</p><p>The kidney's contribution to insulin clearance mainly consists of the filtering of insulin from the blood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The filtering function of the kidney is modeled as a degradation rate that, according to experimental data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], does not saturate and is proportional to insulin concentration in the plasma.</p><p>Pancreatic insulin secretion is mainly induced by plasma glucose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. As we focus on insulin degradation, glucose is not included in the model. We model pancreatic insulin secretion in a highly simplified way as a function of insulin concentration. Due to high robustness to changes in the parameters for insulin secretion (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>), this simplification does not lead to significant approximation errors. In addition, insulin secretion is irrelevant for stationary analysis at constant insulin concentrations.</p><p>Altogether, our model describes the following processes: intravenous injection of radioactively labeled and unlabeled insulin, pancreatic insulin secretion, hepatic and renal insulin degradation, hepatic insulin receptor activation and nonspecific insulin binding by the liver.</p></sec><sec><title>Parameterization of the model</title><p><italic>In vivo </italic>model parameters cannot be measured directly in most cases. Taking parameters from <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments or models for <italic>in vivo </italic>processes is a promising alternative. Note that this can be problematic since the <italic>in vitro </italic>parameter values may not be similar to their <italic>in vivo </italic>counterparts. However, it is the only possibility if there is not sufficient experimental data and a model structure that guarantees identifiability. Using <italic>in vitro </italic>parameters or otherwise determined model parameters and linking kinetic models of smaller parts of the overall system together is frequently performed, e.g. by the Silicon Cell project [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. This strategy is structurally supported by modular modeling tools, e.g. ProMoT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p><p>In this study, model parameters (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) are taken from previously published <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>] and small models of insulin binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], receptor internalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and nonspecific hepatic insulin binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. The models from literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] were combined and kinetic parameters for the remaining processes were taken from <italic>in vitro </italic>data.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Model parameters and initial conditions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Parameter</td><td align="center">Value</td><td align="center">Source</td><td align="center">Meaning of the parameter</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><italic>kins</italic></td><td align="center">10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>nM</italic><sup>-1 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[36]</td><td align="center">insulin binding to the receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>kins</italic>1<italic>d</italic></td><td align="center">4&#x000b7;10<sup>-4 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[36]</td><td align="center">insulin dissociation from the receptor (I1, PM)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>kins</italic>2<italic>d</italic></td><td align="center">4&#x000b7;10<sup>-2 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[36]</td><td align="center">insulin dissociation from the receptor (I2, PM)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>kins</italic>1<italic>den</italic></td><td align="center">1.925&#x000b7;10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[49]</td><td align="center">insulin dissociation from the receptor (I1, EN)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>kins</italic>2<italic>den</italic></td><td align="center">3.85&#x000b7;10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[50]</td><td align="center">insulin dissociation from the receptor (I2, EN)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>kyd</italic></td><td align="center">3.85&#x000b7;10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[51]</td><td align="center">receptor dephosphorylation (PM)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>kyden</italic></td><td align="center">7.22&#x000b7;10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[52]</td><td align="center">receptor dephosphorylation (EN)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>kyp</italic></td><td align="center">0.0231 <italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[52]</td><td align="center">autophosphorylation of the receptor (I1 and I2)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>intk</italic>1</td><td align="center">5.5&#x000b7;10<sup>-4 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[34]</td><td align="center">internalization of phosphorylated receptors</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>intk</italic>2</td><td align="center">2&#x000b7;10<sup>-4 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[34]</td><td align="center">internalization of unphosphorylated receptors</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>reck</italic>1</td><td align="center">1.533&#x000b7;10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[34]</td><td align="center">recycling of receptors without insulin</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>k</italic>1<italic>ub</italic></td><td align="center">0.35 <italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[46]</td><td align="center">nonspecific insulin binding in the liver</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>k</italic>2<italic>ub</italic></td><td align="center">0.2 <italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[46]</td><td align="center">dissociation of nonspecifically bound insulin</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>pansec</italic></td><td align="center">0.0016976 <italic>nM</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">calc.</td><td align="center">pancreatic insulin secretion</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>K pan</italic></td><td align="center">0.5 <italic>nM</italic></td><td align="center">ass.</td><td align="center">concentration of half-maximal insulin secretion</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>m</italic><sub><italic>liver</italic></sub></td><td align="center">0.05&#x000b7;<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body</italic></sub></td><td align="center">[46]</td><td align="center">mass of the liver</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>v</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></td><td align="center">0.03375&#x000b7;10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>l</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>g</italic><sup>-1</sup>&#x000b7;<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body</italic></sub></td><td align="center">[54]</td><td align="center">plasma volume</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>&#x003c1;</italic><sub><italic>liver</italic></sub></td><td align="center">1.051&#x000b7;10<sup>3 </sup>g&#x000b7;<italic>l</italic><sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center">[53]</td><td align="center">density of the liver</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>v</italic><sub><italic>hep</italic></sub></td><td align="center">(<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>liver</italic></sub>/<italic>&#x003c1;</italic><sub><italic>liver</italic></sub>)&#x000b7;0.78</td><td align="center">[45]</td><td align="center">total hepatocyte volume</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>v</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub></td><td align="center">0.272&#x000b7;10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>l</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>g</italic><sup>-1</sup>&#x000b7;<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>hep</italic></sub>&#x000b7;<italic>&#x003c1;</italic><sub><italic>liver</italic></sub></td><td align="center">[46]</td><td align="center">volume of the space of Disse</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>m</italic><sub><italic>kidney</italic></sub></td><td align="center">2&#x000b7;0.85 <italic>g</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body</italic>/</sub>(230 <italic>g</italic>)</td><td align="center">[55]</td><td align="center">mass of the kidney</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>K kidney</italic></td><td align="center">0.0225&#x000b7;10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>l</italic>&#x000b7;(<italic>s</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>g</italic>)<sup>-1</sup>&#x000b7;<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>kidney</italic></sub></td><td align="center">[47]</td><td align="center">clearance of the kidney</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note that <italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body </italic></sub>(body weight in <italic>g</italic>), <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>(injection time in <italic>s</italic>), <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>and <italic>n</italic><sub>*,<italic>in </italic></sub>(amounts of injected unlabeled and labeled insulin in <italic>nmol</italic>) are also model parameters. We do not give values for them in this table as they depend on the analyzed scenario. Note that the model can be used for rats of arbitrary body weights as well as for different injection times and amounts of injected labeled and unlabeled insulin. Initial conditions are: <italic>Ins </italic>= 0.07, <italic>Ins</italic>* = 0, <italic>R </italic>= 31.619, <italic>IR </italic>= 0.430007, <italic>I</italic>2<italic>R </italic>= 0.000696311, <italic>Rp </italic>= 0.227528, <italic>IRp </italic>= 2.07275, <italic>I</italic>2<italic>Rp </italic>= 0.00363012, <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>en </italic></sub>= 4.88528, <italic>IR</italic><sub><italic>en </italic></sub>= 0.145537, <italic>I</italic>2<italic>R</italic><sub><italic>en </italic></sub>= 0.000121295, <italic>Rp</italic><sub><italic>en </italic></sub>= 0.122602, <italic>IRp</italic><sub><italic>en </italic></sub>= 0.492464, <italic>I</italic>2<italic>Rp</italic><sub><italic>en </italic></sub>= 0.000433466, <italic>Ins</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>= 1.29948&#x000b7;10<sup>-6</sup>&#x000b7;<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body</italic></sub>, <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub </italic></sub>= 0. The unit of <italic>Ins</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>and <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub </italic></sub>is <italic>nmol</italic>, the unit of all other state variables is <italic>nM</italic>. ass.: assumption, calc.: calculation (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>), EN: in endosomes, PM: at the plasma membrane, <italic>I</italic>1: one insulin molecule bound to the receptor, <italic>I</italic>2: two insulin molecules bound to the receptor.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The parameters from the models of insulin binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] and nonspecific insulin binding in the liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] were directly taken for our model. The relatively simple models for receptor internalization and recycling at high insulin concentrations and without insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] were combined to describe receptor internalization and recycling at arbitrary insulin concentrations.</p><p>The parameters for pancreatic insulin secretion were chosen to guarantee the physiological basal level of insulin (0.07 <italic>nM</italic>, Gisela Drews, personal communication) and to cut off insulin synthesis at peak concentrations in insulin therapy (0.5 <italic>nM </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]).</p><p>This study uses the rat as model organism because much more parameters are known for rats than for humans. The model validation is performed using experimental data sets for rats.</p><p>All volumes are assumed to be constant. In addition, all tissues are assumed to contact the same total insulin concentration, which is the sum of labeled and unlabeled insulin. The physiological justification of this assumption is the high heart rate of rats (320 &#x02013; 480 <italic>bpm </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>]) that guarantees a fast distribution of circulating insulin.</p></sec><sec><title>The liver</title><p>Insulin degradation in hepatocytes is modeled in a very detailed way. The described processes are successive binding of two insulin molecules to the insulin receptor, receptor phosphorylation and receptor internalization (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). In accordance with experimental results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>], the described processes lead to saturation of hepatic insulin degradation at high insulin concentrations.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Insulin receptor activation in hepatocytes</bold>. The receptor is denoted as <italic>R</italic>. One or two insulin molecules can bind to the receptor (green arrows). This is indicated by a prefix <italic>I </italic>or <italic>I</italic>2, respectively. Receptor phosphorylation (blue arrows) is indicated by a suffix <italic>p</italic>, receptor internalization to the endosomal compartment (red arrows) is indicated by a subscript <italic>en</italic>. Arrows with two heads indicate reversible reactions. Arrows with one head indicate irreversible reactions. Filled arrowheads indicate positive direction of rates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-1"/></fig><p>Model assumptions that are supported by studies from literature are:</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Insulin binding and dissociation are independent of the phosphorylation state of the receptor</italic>. This is directly supported by experimental evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>].</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Only receptors with bound insulin show autophosphorylation activity</italic>. Autophosphorylation is induced by insulin binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] and there is no experimental data quantifying autophosphorylation of receptors without bound insulin.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Receptor dephosphorylation is independent of insulin binding</italic>. Receptor dephosphorylation is performed by protein phosphatases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. It seems very unlikely that insulin binding to the extracellular <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-chain of the receptor induces conformational changes in the intracellular <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-chain that are large enough to significantly change the affinity of phosphatases for their phosphorylated substrate sites.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Insulin dissociation from endosomal receptors is irreversible</italic>. Upon internalization, the pH in endosomes decreases rapidly, which promotes insulin dissociation from the receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Free endosomal insulin is degraded by proteases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Only receptors without insulin are recycled</italic>. Receptor recycling is faster if there is no external insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. This leads to the assumption that an additional step for receptors with bound insulin is necessary before recycling is possible. A very promising candidate for this step is insulin dissociation from the receptor. In this case, a single rate constant for recycling, independent of insulin concentration is sufficient to explain the observation.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Phosphorylated receptors are internalized faster than unphosphorylated receptors</italic>. In the presence of higher insulin concentrations, more insulin receptors are phosphorylated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Receptor internalization is faster at high insulin concentrations than without external insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. In addition, there are reports that receptor internalization depends on phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Labeled and unlabeled insulin show the same physiological characteristics</italic>. Labeling of the insulin molecules was performed with <sup>125</sup>I [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. The size of this modification is small compared to the size of the insulin molecule and should not change its binding characteristics, the effect on receptor phosphorylation, the rate of nonspecific insulin binding or the rate of renal insulin filtration.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>All processes in hepatocytes obey mass action kinetics</italic>. The processes that were adopted from other models obey mass action kinetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. Mass action kinetics is a good and frequently used approximation for processes at the molecular level.</p><p>For the following assumptions there is no experimental data in literature supporting them. These assumptions were made to keep the number of parameters as low as possible.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Receptors with one or two bound insulin molecules show the same autophosphorylation activity</italic>.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Receptor recycling is independent of receptor phosphorylation</italic>.</p><p>In the following, the insulin receptor is denoted as <italic>R</italic>. The binding of one or two insulin molecules is indicated by a prefix <italic>I </italic>or <italic>I</italic>2, respectively. A suffix <italic>p </italic>indicates receptor phosphorylation, a subscript <italic>en </italic>indicates internalization to the endosomal compartment. All concentrations of receptor species refer to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>hep</italic></sub>, the total volume of hepatocytes.</p><p>In general, rates denoted by the standard notation <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>j </italic></sub>describe processes at the plasma membrane of hepatocytes or outside the hepatocytes (nonspecific insulin binding, pancreatic insulin secretion and renal insulin removal). Rates denoted by <italic>i</italic><sub><italic>j </italic></sub>describe <italic>internal </italic>processes occurring in endosomes of hepatocytes, and rates denoted by <italic>f</italic><sub><italic>j </italic></sub>describe <italic>flows </italic>between the plasma membrane and endosomes of hepatocytes.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows the reaction scheme of processes in hepatocytes.</p><p>The hepatocyte part of the model does not distinguish between labeled and unlabeled insulin, which reduces the number of necessary ODEs. Hepatocytes have contact to the total insulin concentration <italic>Ins </italic>that is the sum of labeled and unlabeled insulin concentrations. The concentration of labeled insulin is denoted as <italic>Ins</italic><sub>* </sub>. Unlabeled insulin (<italic>Ins </italic>&#x02013; <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*</sub>) has no separate notation. The total contribution of the liver to insulin degradation is</p><p><disp-formula><italic>r</italic><sub><italic>liv </italic></sub>= (-<italic>r</italic><sub>1 </sub>- <italic>r</italic><sub>2 </sub>- <italic>r</italic><sub>3 </sub>- <italic>r</italic><sub>4</sub>)&#x000b7;<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>hep</italic></sub>/<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>.</disp-formula></p><p>The plasma volume is denoted as <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>, the total hepatocyte volume is denoted as <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>hep</italic></sub>. Strictly speaking, <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>liv </italic></sub>defines insulin removal from the blood, whereas insulin degradation is performed in hepatic endosomes. However, <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>liv </italic></sub>is the contribution of the liver to insulin dynamics. In the stationary case, the values of the rates for insulin removal and insulin degradation are identical.</p><p>Rates <italic>r</italic><sub>1 </sub>&#x02013; <italic>r</italic><sub>4 </sub>describe insulin binding to the insulin receptor at the plasma membrane. The values of the parameters <italic>kins</italic>, <italic>kins</italic>1<italic>d </italic>and <italic>kins</italic>2<italic>d </italic>were directly taken from the model of Wanant et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>].</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M1" name="1752-0509-2-43-i9" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Rates <italic>r</italic><sub>5 </sub>&#x02013; <italic>r</italic><sub>7 </sub>describe receptor phosphorylation at the plasma membrane.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M2" name="1752-0509-2-43-i10" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Rates <italic>i</italic><sub>1 </sub>&#x02013; <italic>i</italic><sub>4 </sub>describe insulin dissociation from the receptor in endosomes.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M3" name="1752-0509-2-43-i11" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Rates <italic>i</italic><sub>5 </sub>&#x02013; <italic>i</italic><sub>7 </sub>describe receptor phosphorylation in endosomes.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M4" name="1752-0509-2-43-i12" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>According to our model assumptions, unphosphorylated receptors without insulin (<italic>R </italic>and <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>en</italic></sub>) have no autophosphorylation activity. Therefore, the reactions represented by the rates <italic>r</italic><sub>5 </sub>and <italic>i</italic><sub>5 </sub>are irreversible. Rates <italic>f</italic><sub>1 </sub>&#x02013; <italic>f</italic><sub>6 </sub>describe receptor internalization and recycling.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M5" name="1752-0509-2-43-i13" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The value of the parameter <italic>intk</italic>1 was directly taken from a model of receptor internalization and recycling at high insulin concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The values of the parameters <italic>intk</italic>2 and <italic>reck</italic>1 are from a model of receptor internalization and recycling without insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>].</p><p>Altogether, the described processes result in the following balance equations for hepatic insulin receptor species.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M6" name="1752-0509-2-43-i1" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The liver also performs nonspecific insulin binding. This reversible process does not saturate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] and dampens rapid variations in insulin concentration. The rates <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>and <italic>r</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub </italic></sub>define nonspecific binding of unlabeled and labeled insulin, respectively.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M7" name="1752-0509-2-43-i2" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x0fe37;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathsize="small">unlabeled&#x000a0;insulin</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The values of the parameters <italic>k</italic>1<italic>ub </italic>and <italic>k</italic>2<italic>ub </italic>were directly taken from the model of Hammond et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. The volume of the space of Disse, in which nonspecific insulin binding takes place, is denoted as <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub>. The concentration of unlabeled insulin is <italic>Ins </italic>&#x02013; <italic>Ins</italic><sub>* </sub>(unit: <italic>nM</italic>), while <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub </italic></sub>and <italic>Ins</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>are the amounts of substance (unit: <italic>nmol</italic>) for nonspecifically bound labeled and unlabeled insulin, respectively. The expressions for the forward reactions of the rates <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>and <italic>r</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub </italic></sub>are multiplied by <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>d </italic></sub>(unit: <italic>l</italic>) as <italic>Ins </italic>and <italic>Ins</italic><sub>* </sub>(unit: <italic>nM</italic>) are concentrations, whereas <italic>Ins</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>and <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub </italic></sub>are amounts of substance (unit: <italic>nmol</italic>). The balances of the amounts of nonspecifically bound labeled and unlabeled insulin are given by</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M8" name="1752-0509-2-43-i3" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In order to obtain the unit <italic>nM</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>s</italic><sup>-1 </sup>for all rates, we divide by <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>p </italic></sub>within the rates <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>and <italic>r</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub </italic></sub>and multiply the rates by <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>p </italic></sub>in the ODEs for <italic>Ins</italic><sub><italic>ub </italic></sub>and <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*,<italic>ub</italic></sub>, emphasizing the need for <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>.</p><p>Note that symbols with an asterisk indicate radioactively labeled insulin species. Species with insulin whose symbols do not contain an asterisk can contain labeled or unlabeled insulin, except for <italic>Ins</italic><sub><italic>ub</italic></sub>, which only represents unlabeled nonspecifically bound insulin.</p></sec><sec><title>The kidney</title><p>The kidney performs insulin degradation by filtering insulin from the blood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The degradation rate <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>kid </italic></sub>is proportional to insulin concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>].</p><p><disp-formula><italic>r</italic><sub><italic>kid </italic></sub>= -<italic>K kidney</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>Ins/v</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></disp-formula></p><p>Insulin clearance is defined as the quotient of the degradation rate and the insulin concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Therefore, <italic>K kidney </italic>is the clearance of the kidney.</p><p>There are also reports that receptor-mediated transport in man contributes about one third to total renal insulin removal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. This may result in a slightly nonlinear behavior of renal insulin degradation. However, the nonlinearity resulting from receptor saturation is not visible in the experimentally examined concentration interval [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Therefore, linear first order kinetics are a good approximation of renal insulin degradation.</p></sec><sec><title>Insulin injection and secretion</title><p>Pancreatic insulin secretion is induced by plasma glucose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], which is not included in the model. In the model, pancreatic insulin secretion <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>pan </italic></sub>is modeled as a function of insulin concentration and turned off at high insulin concentrations. This corresponds to the implicit assumption that glucose dynamics are faster than insulin dynamics. Peak concentrations in insulin therapy are about 60 &#x02013; 80 <italic>&#x003bc;U</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>ml</italic><sup>-1 </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], which is about 0.35 &#x02013; 0.5 <italic>nM</italic>. Insulin secretion is assumed to be cut off smoothly at <italic>K pan </italic>= 0.5 <italic>nM </italic>with Hill coefficient 10. The physiological basal insulin concentration (0.07 <italic>nM</italic>) is guaranteed by adjusting the parameter <italic>pansec </italic>such that the secretion rate equals the sum of stationary insulin degradation rates of the liver and the kidney at 0.07 <italic>nM </italic>insulin (Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>).</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M9" name="1752-0509-2-43-i4" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Intravenous injection of labeled and unlabeled insulin (<italic>u</italic><sub>*,<italic>in </italic></sub>and <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>in</italic></sub>) is performed during injection time <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>with a constant injection rate that is sharply, but smoothly cut off with Hill coefficient 50. This is an arbitrarily chosen parameter that realizes a switching procedure. Real step functions may cause numerical problems which can be avoided in this way.</p><p>The amounts of injected unlabeled and labeled insulin are <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>and <italic>n</italic><sub>*,<italic>in </italic></sub>(unit: <italic>nmol</italic>), respectively. Each parameter can be set to zero if no injection of labeled or unlabeled insulin is desired. The corresponding input functions <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>or <italic>u</italic><sub>*,<italic>in </italic></sub>then equal zero.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M10" name="1752-0509-2-43-i5" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Note that <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>and <italic>u</italic><sub>*,<italic>in </italic></sub>are not defined for <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>= 0 <italic>s </italic>which corresponds to a very rapid bolus injection of insulin. If <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>= 0 <italic>s </italic>is nevertheless desired, this infinitely small injection time can be realized by setting the initial conditions directly to the corresponding values. The rates <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>and <italic>u</italic><sub>*,<italic>in </italic></sub>then have to be set to zero.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M11" name="1752-0509-2-43-i6" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.07</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Note that 0.07 <italic>nM </italic>is the basal concentration of insulin.</p></sec><sec><title>Insulin concentration in plasma</title><p>The balances of the concentrations of labeled (<italic>Ins</italic><sub>*</sub>) and total insulin (<italic>Ins</italic>) are given by:</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M12" name="1752-0509-2-43-i7" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Note that <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>liv </italic></sub>and <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>kid </italic></sub>refer to total insulin. Therefore, only their fractions <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*</sub><italic>/Ins </italic>that correspond to labeled insulin have to be considered in the balance of <italic>Ins</italic><sub>*</sub>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Dynamic model validation</title><sec><title>Insulin dynamics</title><p>The dynamic insulin degradation behavior of the model was compared to experimentally determined time courses of insulin concentration in plasma after an intravenous insulin injection. Experimental data sets with extremely high [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] and extremely low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] amounts of injected insulin were used. The extremely low amount (1.65&#x000b7;10<sup>-6 </sup><italic>nmol</italic>) was radioactively labeled. Therefore, the dynamics of injected insulin can be tracked though the amount of injected insulin is small compared to endogenous insulin. Measured concentrations of labeled insulin were about 0.5&#x000b7;10<sup>-4 </sup><italic>nM </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The extremely high amount of injected insulin (47.5 <italic>nmol</italic>) resulted in measured insulin concentrations above 1600 <italic>nM </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Note that the basal concentration of insulin is 0.07 <italic>nM </italic>and peak concentrations in insulin therapy are below 1 <italic>nM </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Dynamic model validation: physiological insulin concentrations</bold>. Simulation of the concentration of radioactively labeled insulin in plasma after the injection of a very low amount of radioactively labeled insulin is shown and compared to experimental data [59].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Dynamic model validation: extremely high insulin concentrations</bold>. Simulation of plasma insulin concentration after the injection of a large amount of insulin is shown and compared to experimental data [58]. Note that the model does not match the experimental data set. This results from the presence of unmodeled effects at highly supraphysiological insulin concentrations and limitations in the detection quality of the experiment. Therefore, the model is not valid at these extremely high insulin concentrations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-3"/></fig><p>Simulated insulin concentrations for low amounts of injected insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] are relatively close to the experimental data set (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). When examining Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> on a log-linear scale, it can be seen that the relatively low absolute errors at later points in time correspond to large relative errors (not shown). Note that these high relative errors for low absolute values could at least partly result from manual extraction of the data points from Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. As the absolute errors are moderate, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> is regarded as a qualitative validation of the dynamic model at physiological insulin concentrations.</p><p>Simulation results for the injection of unphysiologically high amounts of insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] are not very close to the experimental data set (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). When examining Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> on a log-linear scale, it can also be seen that the relative errors at later points in time are large (not shown).</p><p>Note that an insulin concentration of 1600 <italic>nM </italic>is four orders of magnitude higher than peak concentrations in insulin therapy (below 1 <italic>nM</italic>) and far above physiological values. In this concentration range new unmodeled effects occur. As an example, pinocytosis (fluid-phase endocytosis) significantly contributes to hepatic insulin uptake at high concentrations of insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. In correspondence to nonspecific insulin binding by the liver, nonspecific insulin binding could also occur in other tissues. A result of this additional nonspecific binding would be reversible insulin removal at high insulin concentrations and subsequent insulin release at lower insulin concentrations. Furthermore, the assay of Desbuquois et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] is not able to distinguish between insulin fragments and native insulin. However, after a few minutes, insulin fragments contribute significantly to total insulin, as shown for the injection of small amounts of labeled insulin (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]). Assuming that this holds also for the injection of high amounts of insulin, the assay of Desbuquois et al. overestimates insulin concentrations at later points in time. Note that this is surely not sufficient to explain the whole extent of the error at later points in time.</p><p>The effects of pinocytosis and additional nonspecific insulin binding at high insulin concentrations are not quantified in literature and not included in the model. Neglecting these processes (and maybe others that are important at high insulin concentrations) leads to an incorrect model structure for high insulin concentrations. Therefore, the model is not valid at extremely high insulin concentrations.</p></sec><sec><title>Hepatic insulin receptor internalization</title><p>Simulation results for hepatic insulin receptor internalization at 100 <italic>nM </italic>insulin as well as those without insulin were compared to experimental data from literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. As it can be seen in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, simulation results match the experimental data sets very well. Assuming that simulated insulin binding to the receptor mirrors physiological processes well (we show below that it does), receptor internalization can be used as a direct indicator for hepatic insulin degradation.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Dynamic model validation: receptor internalization</bold>. Simulation results for receptor internalization at 100 <italic>nM </italic>insulin (blue) as well as those without insulin (red) are shown and compared to experimental data [34]. Surface receptors were radioactively labeled. This was simulated by setting the initial conditions such that all receptors are in the state <italic>R </italic>at the plasma membrane. Note that the receptor model is linear for constant insulin concentration. Therefore, the assay can be simulated with this choice of initial conditions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-4"/></fig><p>It should be stated that the model parameters for receptor internalization and recycling are from the same source as the experimental data sets in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>. Backer et al. took the experimental data sets to estimate the parameters for two separate models of receptor internalization and recycling at 100 <italic>nM </italic>insulin as well as without insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. We adopted three parameters of these models.</p><p>Note that the experimental data sets for receptor internalization result from experiments with Fao cells that are tumor cells of hepatic origin. Though simulations match the experimental data sets almost quantitatively, this can only be regarded as a qualitative model validation for hepatocytes.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Stationary model validation</title><p>Simulation results for stationary insulin receptor activation and insulin binding were compared to experimental data sets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Klein et al. determined cell-associated radioactively labeled insulin as a function of unlabeled insulin concentration (Figure 4A in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]). This was done in a competition assay with constant concentration of radioactively labeled insulin and variable concentrations of unlabeled insulin. <italic>In silico </italic>reproduction of this assay and projection of the result on the experimental data set results in a high accordance (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, left).</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Stationary model validation: insulin binding and receptor phosphorylation</bold>. <bold>Left</bold>: Cell-associated radioactively labeled insulin is shown as a function of the stationary insulin concentration and compared to experimental data (Figure 4 A in [57]). Almost no labeled insulin should bind to receptors at maximal concentrations of unlabeled insulin. Therefore, the value for the highest concentration of unlabeled insulin was treated as background and subtracted from all values. <bold>Right</bold>: The fraction of phosphorylated receptors is shown as a function of the stationary insulin concentration and compared to experimental data for receptor activation (Figure 4 B in [57]). We regard receptor phosphorylation as a good indicator for receptor activity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-5"/></fig><p>Klein et al. also determined the stationary dependency of receptor activity on the insulin concentration (Figure 4B in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]). We regard receptor activity as an indicator for receptor phosphorylation. Projection of the experimental data set on the stationary fraction of phosphorylated receptors also shows high accordance (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, right). See Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref> for details about the stationary model validation.</p><p>Changes in <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>or in the parameters for the pancreas have no effect on the results of stationary model validation, as the system is analyzed at constant insulin concentrations in the stationary case.</p><p>Altogether, the model is able to match the experimental data sets for receptor activity and insulin binding very well. Note that the model parameters were not estimated to get these results.</p></sec><sec><title>Model analysis</title><sec><title>Insulin degradation</title><p>The fractions of insulin that are degraded by the liver and the kidney were investigated in several studies. Values for the relative contribution of the liver to insulin degradation in man range from below 50% to 70%, and those for the kidney from 30% to above 50% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. We investigate the reason for this diversity by stationary model analysis.</p><p>Renal insulin degradation does not saturate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], whereas hepatic insulin degradation saturates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. The physiological situation is mirrored by the model, where hepatic insulin degradation saturates, whereas renal insulin degradation does not (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). It can be clearly seen that the relative contributions of the liver and the kidney to total insulin degradation strongly depend on the insulin concentration.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Renal and hepatic insulin degradation</bold>. <bold>Left</bold>: Stationary insulin degradation rates of the liver (red) and the kidney (blue) and the total insulin degradation rate (black) are shown as functions of insulin concentration. <bold>Right</bold>: Stationary relative contributions of the liver (red) and the kidney (blue) to total insulin degradation depend on the insulin concentration. Note that these fractions are slightly lower in reality. Other tissues, in particular fat and muscle, also contribute to insulin degradation but are not analyzed here. The fractions in this plot refer to the sum of the degradation rates of liver and kidney.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-6"/></fig><p>In stationary model analysis, the relative contribution of the liver to overall insulin degradation ranges between 81% for insulin concentration tending to zero and 0% for insulin concentration tending to infinity. The relative contribution of the kidney ranges between 19% and 100% (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). A significant part of these changes happens beyond physiological insulin levels. However, the fractions vary strongly in the physiological range of insulin concentrations. Between 0 <italic>nM </italic>and 1 <italic>nM </italic>insulin, the relative contribution of the liver is between 81% and 63%, while the contribution of the kidney is between 19% and about 37% (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). Only the liver and the kidney are considered in the analysis of insulin degradation. Other insulin degrading tissues, in particular fat and muscle, are neglected. Therefore, the sum of the relative contributions of the liver and the kidney to insulin degradation is one (100%).</p><p>Note that changes in <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>or in the parameters for the pancreas do not affect the results of stationary model analysis, as the system is analyzed at constant insulin concentrations. The rate of nonspecific insulin binding equals zero in the unique stationary case. Therefore, it also has no influence on stationary insulin degradation. The stationary analysis of degradation rates and relative contributions to insulin degradation is also independent of the parameter <italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body </italic></sub>(Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>).</p><p>Quantitative results regarding relative contributions to insulin degradation are sensitive to changes in the parameter <italic>K kidney</italic>, as increasing <italic>K kidney </italic>by 10% also increases the renal insulin degradation rate (<italic>r</italic><sub><italic>kid</italic></sub>) by 10%. However, changes in <italic>K kidney </italic>only change the values of the relative contributions to insulin degradation but do not lead to a qualitatively different result.</p><p>Altogether, relative contributions of the tissues to insulin degradation depend on the insulin concentration. At low insulin concentrations, hepatic insulin degradation is predominant, whereas at high insulin concentrations overall insulin degradation is mainly performed by the kidney. Therefore, different results for the relative contributions of the liver and the kidney to insulin degradation are expected for different experimental settings.</p></sec><sec><title>Insulin clearance</title><p>The quotient of insulin degradation rate and insulin concentration is denoted as insulin clearance <italic>c </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], which is a widely used quantity to characterize the state of insulin metabolism.</p><p><disp-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M13" name="1752-0509-2-43-i8" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The physiological range of insulin clearance in man (70 <italic>kg</italic>) is 700 &#x02013; 3350 <italic>ml</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>min</italic><sup>-1 </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. We use stationary model analysis to investigate the reason for this diversity.</p><p>Insulin clearance strongly depends on the insulin concentration (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Due to receptor saturation, hepatic insulin clearance decreases for increasing insulin concentrations. The effect of <italic>Ins</italic><sup>-1 </sup>in hepatic insulin clearance (-<italic>r</italic><sub><italic>liv</italic></sub>&#x000b7;<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>&#x000b7;<italic>Ins</italic><sup>-1</sup>) strongly dominates the effect of the saturating degradation rate <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>liv </italic></sub>(compare Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, left and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Renal insulin clearance is independent of the insulin concentration, as it is a first order process in which the degradation rate is proportional to the insulin concentration. Therefore, the quotient of rate and concentration is constant.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Renal and hepatic insulin clearance</bold>. Insulin clearance is defined as the quotient of insulin degradation rate and insulin concentration. Total stationary insulin clearance (black) is a function of insulin concentration because hepatic insulin clearance (liver, red) depends on the insulin concentration, whereas renal insulin clearance (kidney, blue) is independent of insulin concentration. A body weight of <italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body </italic></sub>= 200 <italic>g </italic>was used in the computations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-7"/></fig><p>As an example, in a rat whose body weight is 200 <italic>g</italic>, insulin clearance ranges between 10.7 <italic>ml</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>min</italic><sup>-1 </sup>for insulin concentration tending to zero and 2.0 <italic>ml</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>min</italic><sup>-1 </sup>for insulin concentration tending to infinity (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>).</p><p>Insulin clearance is often used to characterize the state of insulin metabolism. However, its value for analysis of processes that are dominated by saturable components, in particular hepatic insulin degradation, is very limited. A strong dependence on the insulin concentration hampers precise analysis, especially if one cannot guarantee that the insulin concentration is constant during the experiment. This problem does not occur when analyzing first order processes such as renal insulin degradation, where insulin clearance is independent of insulin concentration (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>).</p><p>Altogether, the strong dependency of insulin clearance on the insulin concentration is able to explain the wide range of reported values.</p></sec><sec><title>Parameter estimation</title><p>As shown above, insulin degradation at high insulin concentrations is mainly performed by the kidney. Nonspecific insulin binding dampens rapid variations in insulin concentration at all insulin concentrations (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Therefore, the most important parameters at high insulin concentrations are those for the kidney and nonspecific insulin binding.</p><p>In order to investigate whether the model structure can reproduce the experimental data set for high amounts of injected insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>], we estimated the parameters for the kidney and nonspecific insulin binding. The model with estimated parameter values matches the experimental data set for high amounts of injected insulin significantly better than the model with parameter values from literature (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). However, from a physiological point of view, we are convinced that this does not reflect increased model quality. As discussed above, there are unmodeled effects which are not important at physiological insulin concentrations and there is detection of insulin fragments in the assay.</p><p>Thus, taking the experimental data set for high amounts of injected insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] to estimate parameter values for our model (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>) results in parameters that reflect more than the processes they represent. The estimated parameter values also include the effects of processes that are not explicitly described in the model and detection errors of the assay. Therefore, we performed our analysis using the parameter values from literature (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Sensitivity analysis</title><p>We showed that the parameters for the kidney and nonspecific insulin binding are most important at high insulin concentrations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Now, we investigate robustness to small changes in these parameters (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Increasing or decreasing the values of <italic>k</italic>1<italic>ub</italic>, <italic>k</italic>2<italic>ub </italic>and <italic>K kidney </italic>by 20% results in moderate differences in simulation results for the injection of high amounts of insulin. Changing <italic>K kidney </italic>by 20% has practically no effect on simulation results for the injection of small amounts of insulin, whereas the effect of small changes (up to 20%) in the parameter values for nonspecific insulin binding is moderate. All simulation results match the experimental data set in an acceptable way (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>).</p><p>On the other hand, the values of <italic>k</italic>1<italic>ub</italic>, <italic>k</italic>2<italic>ub </italic>and <italic>K kidney </italic>cannot be arbitrarily chosen. A nice example for this is that simulation results using an estimated parameter set fail to match the experimental data set for small amounts of injected insulin (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, top in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). This supports our previous argument that the experimental data set for high amounts of injected insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] should not be used for parameter estimation.</p><p>The values from literature of <italic>k</italic>1<italic>ub</italic>, <italic>k</italic>2<italic>ub </italic>and <italic>K kidney </italic>are surely not determined with extremely high precision. Small deviations from their nominal values do not lead to dramatic differences in the simulation results for insulin dynamics (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>), whereas larger changes do. Therefore, the values from literature are at least acceptable estimates for parameterization of the processes they represent.</p><p>The parameters for the pancreas (<italic>pansec</italic>, <italic>K pan</italic>, Hill coefficient) are chosen to guarantee that insulin secretion is turned off at peak concentrations in insulin therapy. They have negligible influence on the simulation results for insulin dynamics, as long as the physiological basal level of insulin (0.07 <italic>nM</italic>) is guaranteed by adjusting <italic>pansec </italic>(Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>).</p><p>Changes in the parameter <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>(for which no value is given) have practically no influence on the simulation results for high amounts of injected insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Simulation results for small amounts of injected insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] are sensitive to changes in <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in</italic></sub>. If one assumes that <italic>t </italic>= 0 <italic>s </italic>corresponds to the end of insulin injection, simulation results are in each case relatively close to the experimental data set (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). However, if one assumes that insulin injection starts at <italic>t </italic>= 0 <italic>s</italic>, simulation results for large injection times are not close to the experimental data set any more (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Unfortunately, the exact procedure of injection is not described in either study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. We assume a bolus injection at <italic>t </italic>= 0 <italic>s </italic>for both experiments.</p><p>Altogether, simulation results for insulin dynamics are sensitive to changes in <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>in</italic></sub>. However, they are robust to changes in the other unknown parameters and in the parameters that are most important at high insulin concentrations.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Comparison with other models</title><p>Comparison of our model predictions for insulin dynamics with those of other models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] (all of which describe insulin dynamics in humans) is only possible if the amount of injected insulin and the model parameters are scaled to reflect differences in body mass between rats and humans. However, compensating the difference between rats and humans solely by scaling body weights and amounts of injected insulin will result in unreliable model predictions because differences in physiology are neglected. Parameter estimation is a possible way of compensating for the differences in physiology between rats and humans, however, experimental data sets used for parameter estimation cannot be reused for the model validation. Therefore, more experimental data sets are necessary to adapt the parameter values from models of insulin dynamics in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] to the physiological situation in rats and to perform the model validation with independent data sets.</p><p>Estimating the parameters of our model to match experimental data sets for humans as accurately as the models of human insulin dynamics should be possible. The reason for this is that our model considers more processes and therefore has more degrees of freedom. However, the model parameters are not identifiable if only experimental data sets for insulin concentration are used. Therefore, the estimated parameter values are not physiologically relevant.</p><p>We investigate whether the analysis of the other models of insulin receptor activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] leads to the same results as the analysis of our model. The receptor model of Sedaghat et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] shows stationary insulin binding characteristics that match the experimental data set of Klein et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>] well, but not as accurately as our model (compare Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). Stationary receptor phosphorylation characteristics show significant deviations from the experimental data set (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). Note that this only indicates that the model of Sedaghat et al., which describes receptor dynamics in adipocytes, cannot be used for hepatocytes. It should be mentioned that the model of Sedaghat et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] is not suited for stationary model analysis as the total receptor concentration in the stationary case is unphysiologically high. The worst case is a total stationary receptor concentration of 100 <italic>M </italic>in the absence of insulin (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). Note that the initial condition for the total receptor concentration (10<sup>-12 </sup><italic>M</italic>) is not a stationary solution of the model equations. However, simulation results converge very slowly to the steady state (not shown) as the first order constant for receptor synthesis is about 10<sup>-17 </sup><italic>M</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>min</italic><sup>-1</sup>.</p><p>Insulin degradation of adipocytes (i.e. with initial conditions taken from the model of Sedaghat et al.) is five orders of magnitude lower than hepatic insulin degradation (see above). At physiological insulin concentrations, insulin degradation is mainly performed by the liver (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Therefore, it is obvious that replacing our receptor model by the model of Sedaghat et al. makes it impossible to match the experimental data set for low amounts of injected insulin.</p><p>The situation is different when considering a modified model of Hori et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Note that all parameterized models of Hori et al. are only valid at 100 <italic>nM </italic>insulin. Only one of the models of Hori et al. can handle variable insulin concentrations. However, no parameterization is given for this model structure. We parameterized each process of this model structure by taking the average value of the estimated parameter values from the other models of Hori et al. As there are no parameters for insulin binding in the study of Hori et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>], we took the parameter values for insulin binding from the model of Wanant et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. This modified model of Hori et al. is not able to reproduce the stationary insulin binding and receptor activation characteristics from literature as well as our model (compare Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). However, all models of Hori et al. reproduce the experimental data set for receptor internalization (compare Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref> in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Note that Hori et al. used this data set to estimate model parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>].</p><p>As the receptor concentrations in the models of Hori et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] are normalized to one, we set the total receptor concentration to 40 <italic>nM </italic>as we do in our model. We replaced the hepatocyte part of our model by the modified model of Hori et al. and left all other processes (nonspecific insulin binding, renal insulin degradation and pancreatic insulin secretion) unchanged. This led to simulation results for low amounts of injected insulin that match the experimental data set [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] about as well as our original model (not shown). The modified model of Hori et al. shows slightly higher hepatic insulin degradation than our model. Therefore, when comparing the simulation results with those of our model, the simulation performs better at the first two points in time, the simulation and our model perform equally well at the third point in time (2 <italic>min</italic>), and our model performs better for the remaining points in time (not shown). For the experiment with high amounts of injected insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>], the difference between the models is negligible (not shown) as insulin degradation at high insulin concentrations is mainly performed by the kidney (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>).</p><p>Note that our model is not able to quantitatively reproduce the dynamic phosphorylation characteristics in endosomes that were measured by Backer et al. in Fao cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and used by Hori et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] for parameter estimation (not shown). However, Fao cells have different physiological characteristics as hepatocytes and therefore quantitative matching of our hepatocyte model to experimental data sets for Fao cells is not necessary. In this case, we rely on the <italic>in vitro </italic>measurements of receptor phosphorylation and dephosphorylation in hepatocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] that we used to parameterize our model.</p><p>Note that the modified model of Hori et al. corresponds to a reduced model of our receptor model where some parameters and the total receptor concentration are identical.</p><p>Both receptor models from literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] are not able to match all experimental data sets. Therefore, we assume that the additional complexity included in our model, in particular binding of the second insulin molecule, could be necessary. We further investigate this by stationary model analysis. The fraction of insulin receptors with two bound insulin molecules rises with insulin concentration (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). At 100 <italic>nM </italic>insulin, which is a common situation in <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments, almost 50% of all receptors have two bound insulin molecules. At the basal insulin concentration, the fraction of receptors with two bound insulin molecules is negligible (0.01%). Therefore, a reduced model structure that neglects all receptor states with two bound insulin molecules is sufficient at low insulin concentrations. However, at insulin concentrations larger that 5 &#x02013; 10 <italic>nM </italic>insulin receptors with two bound insulin molecules represent a significant fraction and should not be neglected. As in many cases simulation speed is not a limiting factor, we recommend to use our model for small insulin concentrations as well.</p></sec><sec><title>Therapeutic insulin concentrations</title><p>The aim of insulin therapy is to achieve sufficient glucose uptake with minimal amounts of insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. An interesting question is whether an upper bound for reasonable insulin concentrations exists. We investigate this by combining the results of stationary model analysis and experimental studies from literature.</p><p>At about 10 <italic>nM </italic>insulin, the insulin receptor in hepatocytes of rats is almost maximally phosphorylated (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Almost 80% of insulin is degraded by the kidney (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>) and does not contribute to insulin receptor activation. The fraction of insulin that is degraded by the kidney further increases with increasing insulin concentration (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>).</p><p>Half-maximal insulin receptor phosphorylation in rat adipocytes is at 7 &#x000b1; 1 <italic>nM </italic>insulin (experimental: [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>], simulation study: [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]). Glucose uptake in adipocytes is half-maximal at 170 <italic>pM </italic>insulin and saturates at about 3 <italic>nM </italic>insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. These findings are expected to hold qualitatively also for human adipocytes. As the aim of insulin therapy is to achieve the desired physiological effect (glucose uptake) with minimal amounts of insulin, an upper bound for therapeutic insulin concentrations in man seems to exist. This upper bound is the insulin concentration where a higher insulin concentration does not result in a higher glucose uptake but only leads to increased insulin degradation. Characteristics of glucose uptake in rats imply that this upper bound is at about 3 <italic>nM </italic>and not at about 10 <italic>nM </italic>as implied by receptor phosphorylation characteristics.</p><p>Relatively large amounts of insulin or insulin analogues are injected or infused in postprandial glucose control. This mimics the physiological response of healthy individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Postprandial insulin concentration after a standard meal peaks at 60 &#x02013; 80 <italic>&#x003bc;U</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>ml</italic><sup>-1 </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], which is about 0.35 &#x02013; 0.5 <italic>nM</italic>. Hepatic insulin degradation is predominant in this concentration interval (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Additionally, glucose uptake is strongly, but not fully activated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Overnight control of glucose concentration is performed with basal insulins that show slow absorption kinetics or with continuous injection of short acting insulins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. In both cases only insulin concentrations close to the physiological basal concentration are expected.</p><p>Therefore, the theoretical upper bound for reasonable therapeutic insulin concentrations in rats (about 3 <italic>nM</italic>) lies significantly above therapeutic insulin levels in humans (about 0.5 <italic>nM</italic>). We suppose that the upper bound for reasonable therapeutic insulin concentrations in man is relatively close to the value postulated for rats.</p><p>Altogether, mathematical analysis and experimental results indicate that peak concentrations in insulin therapy are below the upper bound where a higher insulin concentration does not result in a stronger physiological effect.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We present a detailed dynamic model that describes <italic>in vivo </italic>insulin dynamics and hepatic insulin receptor activation in the rat. Model parameters are taken from <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments and other models. The model is able to reproduce experimental data sets from literature without parameter estimation.</p><p>The vast majority of statements about insulin degradation and insulin clearance in the literature is given without explicitly defining the corresponding insulin concentration, and the reported values widely vary. Mathematical analysis shows that relative contributions of the liver and the kidney to total insulin degradation highly depend on the insulin concentration. At low insulin concentrations, insulin is mainly degraded by the liver, whereas renal insulin degradation is predominant at high insulin concentrations. This explains variations in reported values of relative contributions to insulin degradation.</p><p>Mathematical analysis also shows that insulin clearance strongly depends on the insulin concentration, which explains variations in reported values. Due to the concentration dependence of insulin clearance, its value for characterizing insulin metabolism is very limited.</p><p>The analysis of relative contributions to insulin degradation and the dose-response characteristics of insulin receptor activation and glucose uptake imply the existence of an upper bound for reasonable therapeutic insulin concentrations. Higher insulin concentrations do not result in higher glucose uptake and additional insulin is degraded without having therapeutic effect. However, the upper bound for reasonable therapeutic insulin concentrations is above peak concentrations in insulin therapy.</p><p>The detailed model presented here can be used as a starting point for modeling and analysis of the signaling cascades emerging from the hepatic insulin receptor (e.g. MAP kinase cascade and PI3K pathway). This will significantly contribute to understanding the effect of insulin on hepatocytes <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Model parameters and initial conditions</title><p><italic>In vitro </italic>insulin receptor autophosphorylation has a half-life of about 0.5 <italic>min </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]). Assuming first order kinetics, this corresponds to a rate constant of <italic>kyp </italic>= 0.0231 <italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup>. <italic>In vitro </italic>insulin receptor dephosphorylation at the plasma membrane has a half-life of about 3 <italic>min </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]). Assuming first order kinetics, this corresponds to a rate constant of <italic>kyd </italic>= 0.00385 <italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup>. <italic>In vitro </italic>insulin receptor dephosphorylation at endosomal membranes has a half-life of 1.6 <italic>min </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]). Assuming first order kinetics, this corresponds to a rate constant of <italic>kyden </italic>= 0.00722 <italic>s</italic><sup>-1</sup>.</p><p>We compared weights of livers and bodies given in literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. In average, the liver contributes about 5% to the body weight of rats. There are 10<sup>5 </sup>insulin receptors per hepatocyte [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. Assuming that the hepatocyte is a sphere with a diameter of 20 <italic>&#x003bc;m</italic>, this corresponds to a receptor concentration of 40 <italic>nM</italic>. Basal insulin concentration in fasted mice is 0.3 &#x02013; 0.5 <italic>ng</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>ml</italic><sup>-1 </sup>(Gisela Drews, personal communication). As the molecular weight of insulin is 5.7 <italic>kDa</italic>, 0.4 <italic>ng</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>ml</italic><sup>-1 </sup>corresponds to 0.07 <italic>nM</italic>. The same basal insulin concentration is assumed for rats. All other parameters were directly taken from the cited references. As discussed above, all parameters are taken from previously published smaller models, <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments or chosen to guarantee the physiological basal level of insulin (0.07 <italic>nM</italic>) and to cut off insulin synthesis at high insulin concentrations. A list of all model parameters is given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><p>Stationary model equations (all derivatives set to zero) were solved for the state variables under the basal insulin concentration as a constraint to get initial conditions that correspond to the basal insulin concentration (Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). This resulted in a unique solution and was done with the software package <italic>Mathematica </italic>(Wolfram Research).</p></sec><sec><title>Dynamic model validation</title><p>Kruse et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] used rats with a body weight of 238 &#x000b1; 20 <italic>g</italic>. Insulin injection was 100 <italic>&#x003bc;l </italic>of 12 &#x02013; 21 <italic>pM </italic>radioactively labeled insulin. A body weight of <italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body </italic></sub>= 238 <italic>g </italic>and an insulin injection of <italic>n</italic><sub>*,<italic>in </italic></sub>= 100 <italic>&#x003bc;l</italic>&#x000b7;16.5 <italic>pM </italic>= 1.65&#x000b7;10<sup>-6 </sup><italic>nmol </italic>and <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>= 0 <italic>nmol </italic>was used for the simulation. The experimental data set is given in % dose per <italic>ml </italic>serum. Multiplied by the amount of injected labeled insulin and divided by 100, these values give the concentrations of labeled insulin in plasma [<italic>nmol/ml</italic>]. Desbuquois et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] used rats with a body weight of 180 &#x02013; 200 <italic>g</italic>. Insulin injection was 25 <italic>nmol</italic>/100 <italic>g </italic>body weight. A body weight of <italic>m</italic><sub><italic>body </italic></sub>= 190 <italic>g </italic>and an insulin injection of <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>in </italic></sub>= 47.5 <italic>nmol </italic>and <italic>n</italic><sub>*,<italic>in </italic></sub>= 0 <italic>nmol </italic>was used for the simulation. The experimental data set is already given as concentration values. As the exact procedure of injection is not described in either study, we assumed that the injection was given as a bolus at <italic>t </italic>= 0 <italic>s</italic>.</p><p>Backer et al. investigated receptor internalization in Fao hepatoma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Surface receptors were radioactively labeled at low temperature (on ice), stopping receptor internalization. Incubation at 37&#x000b0;C initiated receptor internalization in the assay. This experiment was simulated by setting initial conditions such that all receptors are at the surface (<italic>R </italic>= 40). If the insulin concentration is constant, the receptor model is linear and the superposition principle holds. Therefore, the assay can be simulated with this choice of initial conditions.</p><p>Dynamic simulation was performed with the software package MATLAB (The MathWorks). The executable <italic>in vivo </italic>and <italic>in vitro </italic>models are given in MATLAB format in Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Stationary analysis</title><p>The liver is a dynamic system. Its physiological state and its contribution to insulin degradation depend on the insulin concentration. However, the rate of hepatic insulin degradation is not uniquely defined by the present insulin concentration. The hepatic insulin degradation rate strongly depends on the amount of free receptors at the plasma membrane. Assume that the system is not in steady state. In this case, for the model, insulin concentrations from all points in time since the system left the steady state affect the physiological state of the liver and in particular the amount of free insulin receptors at the plasma membrane.</p><p>The steady state of our model is uniquely defined by the steady state insulin concentration. Note that the stationary case corresponds to the steady state of the system. In the stationary case, all characteristics of the system (e.g. insulin degradation rates, insulin clearance, receptor activation or insulin binding) can be expressed as functions of the stationary insulin concentration. Thus, stationary analysis gives insights into the system that are not biased by dynamic effects.</p><p>All stationary computations were performed with the software package <italic>Mathematica </italic>(Wolfram Research) and are given in Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>. Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref> is a PDF version of Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>ass: assumption; bpm, beats per minute; calc: calculated; ml: milliliter (10<sup>-3 </sup><italic>l</italic>); nM: nano molar (10<sup>-9 </sup><italic>mol</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>l</italic><sup>-1</sup>); nmol: nano mol (10<sup>-9 </sup><italic>mol</italic>); ODE: ordinary differential equation; EN: in endosomes; PM: at the plasma membrane; I1: one insulin molecule bound to the receptor; I2: two insulin molecules bound to the receptor.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>MK developed the model, performed the analysis and drafted the manuscript. EDG initiated and supervised the study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><italic>In vivo </italic>model. This file contains a MATLAB model to simulate <italic>in vivo </italic>experiments.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-S1.m" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><italic>In vitro </italic>receptor model. This file contains the receptor part of the <italic>in vivo </italic>model and can be taken to simulate <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments with a constant insulin concentration.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-S2.m" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p>Robustness and parameter estimation. This file describes the examination of robustness to changes in parameter values and the estimation of the model parameters.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-S3.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p>Stationary model analysis. In this file, the stationary model equations are analyzed.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-S4.nb" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional file 5</title><p>Stationary model analysis in portable document format. This file is equivalent to Additional file 4 but results from a conversion to PDF.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-S5.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6"><caption><title>Additional file 6</title><p>Stationary analysis of the model of Sedaghat et al. The stationary model equations of Sedaghat et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] are analyzed.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-S6.nb" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7"><caption><title>Additional file 7</title><p>Stationary analysis of a modified model of Hori et al. The stationary model equations of a modified model of Hori et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] are analyzed.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-43-S7.nb" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Johannes Witt (Institute for System Dynamics, Universit&#x000e4;t Stuttgart), Michael Ederer, Holger Conzelmann (Max Planck Institute for Dynamics of Complex Technical Systems, Magdeburg) and Duncan Payne (Department of Computer Science, Shefield University) for inspiring discussions and proofreading the manuscript. We acknowledge Gisela Drews (Pharmazeutisches Institut, Eberhard Karls Universit&#x000e4;t T&#x000fc;bingen) and Michael Heinrich (Center for Biotechnology and Biomedicine, Universit&#x000e4;t Leipzig) for valuable hints. This work was supported by the Network Systems Biology HepatoSys, which is funded by the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (Bundesministerium f&#x000fc;r Bildung und Forschung, BMBF).</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saltiel</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin signaling and the regulation of glucose transport</article-title><source>Mol Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16307172</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saltiel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin signalling and the regulation of glucose and lipid metabolism</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>414</volume><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/414799a</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plum</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Belgardt</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000fc;ning</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Central insulin action in energy and glucose homeostasis</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2006</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>1761</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16823473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI29063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mounier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation by insulin: from the receptor to the gene</article-title><source>Can J Physiol Pharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16998535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/Y05-152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salsali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of types 1 and 2 diabetes mellitus and their treatment with insulin</article-title><source>Am J Ther</source><year>2006</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16858171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00045391-200607000-00012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludvigsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why diabetes incidence increases-a unifying theory</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>1079</volume><fpage>374</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17130582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1196/annals.1375.058</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>HKR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zierath</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin signaling defects in type 2 diabetes</article-title><source>Rev Endocr Metab Disord</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15041786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:REMD.0000021432.84588.f6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and molecular basis of insulin resistance</article-title><source>Curr Protein Pept Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16611137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/138920306776359759</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duckworth</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin degradation: progress and potential</article-title><source>Endocr Rev</source><year>1998</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>608</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9793760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/er.19.5.608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tartaglia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal strategies in the treatment of obesity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>404</volume><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10766254</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stumvoll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Haeften</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Type 2 diabetes: principles of pathogenesis and therapy</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2005</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>1333</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15823385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(05)61032-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turnheim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldh&#x000e4;usl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essentials of insulin pharmacokinetics</article-title><source>Wien Klin Wochenschr</source><year>1988</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3281377</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorsteinsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetic models for insulin disappearance from plasma in man</article-title><source>Dan Med Bull</source><year>1990</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2188802</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hovorka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Powrie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f6;nksen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Five-compartment model of insulin kinetics and its use to investigate action of chloroquine in NIDDM</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>E162</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8338148</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mosekilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pramming</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorsteinsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling absorption kinetics of subcutaneous injected soluble insulin</article-title><source>J Pharmacokinet Biopharm</source><year>1989</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2654357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01059088</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puckett</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lightfoot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model for multiple subcutaneous insulin injections developed from individual diabetic patient data</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>E1115</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8572205</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilinska</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Chassin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaupp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieber</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovorka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin kinetics in type-I diabetes: continuous and bolus delivery of rapid acting insulin</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Biomed Eng</source><year>2005</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15651559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TBME.2004.839639</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodbard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computer simulation of plasma insulin and glucose dynamics after subcutaneous insulin injection</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>1989</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2693012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diacare.12.10.725</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trajanoski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotanko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skraba</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic model for the absorption of subcutaneously injected soluble insulin and monomeric insulin analogues</article-title><source>Biomed Tech (Berl)</source><year>1993</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8218870</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cobelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Caumo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Omenetto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minimal model SG overestimation and SI underestimation: improved accuracy by a Bayesian two-compartment model</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>E481</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10484360</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Natali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gastaldelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Camastra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sironi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Toschi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Masoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrannini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dose-response characteristics of insulin action on glucose metabolism: a non-steady-state approach</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2000</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>E794</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10780934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hann</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integral-based parameter identification for long-term dynamic verification of a glucose-insulin system model</article-title><source>Comput Methods Programs Biomed</source><year>2005</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15721654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2004.10.006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toffolo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Campioni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizza</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A minimal model of insulin secretion and kinetics to assess hepatic insulin extraction</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2006</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>E169</fpage><lpage>E176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16144811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00473.2004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimoda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Konno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichinose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uehara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shichiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Closed-loop subcutaneous insulin infusion algorithm with a short-acting insulin analog for long-term clinical application of a wearable artificial endocrine pancreas</article-title><source>Front Med Biol Eng</source><year>1997</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9444512</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorhead</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated insulin infusion trials in the intensive care unit</article-title><source>Diabetes Technol Ther</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15117582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/152091504773731348</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hovorka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Canonico</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chassin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haueter</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Massi-Benedetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Federici</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieber</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaupp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vering</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilinska</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonlinear model predictive control of glucose concentration in subjects with type 1 diabetes</article-title><source>Physiol Meas</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15382830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0967-3334/25/4/010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plank</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordingley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilinska</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Chassin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Squire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haluzik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Svacina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Toller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Plasnik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellmerer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovorka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieber</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multicentric, randomized, controlled trial to evaluate blood glucose control by the model predictive control algorithm versus routine glucose management protocols in intensive care unit patients</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2006</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diacare.29.02.06.dc05-1689</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaupp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodenlenz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilinska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chassin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vering</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovorka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On-line adaptive algorithm with glucose prediction capacity for subcutaneous closed loop control of glucose: evaluation under fasting conditions in patients with Type 1 diabetes</article-title><source>Diabet Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16409572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1464-5491.2006.01695.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hovorka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Continuous glucose monitoring and closed-loop systems</article-title><source>Diabet Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16409558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1464-5491.2005.01672.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hovorka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilinska</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Chassin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunger</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roadmap to the artificial pancreas</article-title><source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2006</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>S178</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-8227(06)70027-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorsteinsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fugleberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-linearity of insulin kinetics</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>1986</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>898</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3552816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00870148</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Donner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin receptors convert to a higher affinity state subsequent to hormone binding. A two-state model for the insulin receptor</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1982</year><volume>257</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7031059</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Standaert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Equilibrium model for insulin-induced receptor down-regulation. Regulation of insulin receptors in differentiated BC3H-1 myocytes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1984</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>2346</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6365910</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Backer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation of the insulin receptor during insulin-stimulated internalization in rat hepatoma cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1989</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>1694</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2463986</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Campfield</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mathematical model and computer simulation study of insulin receptor regulation</article-title><source>J Theor Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1890848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5193(05)80475-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wanant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin receptor binding kinetics: modeling and simulation studies</article-title><source>J Theor Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jtbi.2000.2069</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sedaghat</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mathematical model of metabolic insulin signaling pathways</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2002</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>E1084</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376338</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurland</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>DiStefano</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of endosomal trafficking dynamics on the regulation of hepatic insulin receptor activity: models for Fao cells</article-title><source>Ann Biomed Eng</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>879</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16708271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10439-005-9065-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hlavacek</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Faeder</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blinov</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The complexity of complexes in signal transduction</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2004</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14708119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.10842</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conzelmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Saez-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kholodenko</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A domain-oriented approach to the reduction of combinatorial complexity in signal transduction networks</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>34</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16430778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-7-34</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koschorreck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Conzelmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ederer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced modeling of signal transduction &#x02013; a modular approach</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>336</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17854494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-8-336</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gherzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Andraghetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Versari</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of insulin receptor autophosphorylation on insulin receptor binding</article-title><source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source><year>1986</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3519315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0303-7207(86)90154-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snoep</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruggeman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerhoff</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards building the silicon cell: a modular approach</article-title><source>Biosystems</source><year>2006</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16242236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biosystems.2005.07.006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rother</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beguinot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Formisano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Accili</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that IRS-2 phosphorylation is required for insulin action in hepatocytes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>17491</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9651339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.28.17491</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blouin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolender</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weibel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of organelles and membranes between hepatocytes and nonhepatocytes in the rat liver parenchyma. A stereological study</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1977</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">833203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.72.2.441</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model of insulin distribution and uptake in the perfused rat liver</article-title><source>J Theor Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1881142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5193(05)80075-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlatter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schurek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Renal handling of homologous and heterologous insulin in the isolated perfused rat kidney</article-title><source>Pflugers Arch</source><year>1982</year><volume>393</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7048243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00584074</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ginkel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nutsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modular modeling of cellular systems with ProMoT/Diva</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1169</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12801880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg128</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective degradation of insulin within rat liver endosomes</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2404022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.110.1.35</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Backer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dissociation and degradation of internalized insulin occur in the endosomes of rat hepatoma cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1990</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>14828</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2203763</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for tyrosine phosphorylation in both activation and inhibition of the insulin receptor tyrosine kinase in vivo</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1996</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>4960</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8895369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.137.11.4960</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baquiran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dephosphorylation of insulin and epidermal growth factor receptors. Role of endosome-associated phosphotyrosine phosphatase(s)</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1992</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>11215</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1375938</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overmoyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brittenham</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uniformity of liver density and nonheme (storage) iron distribution</article-title><source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source><year>1987</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3579513</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pass</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rat</article-title><source>ANZCCART News</source><year>1993</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000f8;rup</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative morphology of the rat kidney during diabetes mellitus and insulin treatment</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>1997</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>802</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9243101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001250050752</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schade</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatic removal of insulin in normal man: dose response to endogenous insulin secretion</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1983</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1294</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6341392</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Drenckhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimmsmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Unthan-Fechner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential modulation of insulin actions by dexamethasone: studies in primary cultures of adult rat hepatocytes</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2002</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12217595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-8278(02)00217-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desbuquois</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burlet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ligand-induced translocation of insulin receptors in intact rat liver</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1982</year><volume>257</volume><fpage>10852</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7050122</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Permin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Heding</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fate of insulin analogs in intact and nephrectomized rats determined by their receptor binding constants</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>E1089</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9227456</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Loten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarett</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonreceptor mediated nuclear accumulation of insulin in H35 rat hepatoma cells</article-title><source>J Cell Physiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1447321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcp.1041530323</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stagsted</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between insulin receptor occupancy and tyrosine kinase activity at low insulin concentrations and effect of major histocompatibility complex class I-derived peptide</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>1993</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8246175</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ristic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of rapid-acting insulin analogs on overall glycemic control in type 1 and type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Diabetes Technol Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12725708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/152091503763816472</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin analogues</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15647580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra040832</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


