<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">12771127</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2199375</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200301070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200301070</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Kinetic analysis of receptor-activated phosphoinositide turnover</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Chang</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watras</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Loew</surname><given-names>Leslie M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x19971b0N0x1ec1330">Department of Physiology and Center for Biomedical Imaging Technology, University of Connecticut Health Center, Farmington, CT 06030</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Leslie M. Loew, Dept. of Physiology and Center for Biomedical Imaging Technology, University of Connecticut Health Center, Farmington, CT 06030. Tel.: (860) 679-3568. Fax: (860) 679-1039. E-mail: <email>les@volt.uchc.edu</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>26</day><month>5</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><volume>161</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2002</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2003, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We studied the bradykinin-induced changes in phosphoinositide composition of N1E-115 neuroblastoma cells using a combination of biochemistry, microscope imaging, and mathematical modeling. Phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate (PIP<sub>2</sub>) decreased over the first 30 s, and then recovered over the following 2&#x02013;3 min. However, the rate and amount of inositol-1,4,5-trisphosphate (InsP<sub>3</sub>) production were much greater than the rate or amount of PIP<sub>2</sub> decline. A mathematical model of phosphoinositide turnover based on this data predicted that PIP<sub>2</sub> synthesis is also stimulated by bradykinin, causing an early transient increase in its concentration. This was subsequently confirmed experimentally. Then, we used single-cell microscopy to further examine phosphoinositide turnover by following the translocation of the pleckstrin homology domain of PLC&#x003b4;1 fused to green fluorescent protein (PH-GFP). The observed time course could be simulated by incorporating binding of PIP<sub>2</sub> and InsP<sub>3</sub> to PH-GFP into the model that had been used to analyze the biochemistry. Furthermore, this analysis could help to resolve a controversy over whether the translocation of PH-GFP from membrane to cytosol is due to a decrease in PIP<sub>2</sub> on the membrane or an increase in InsP<sub>3</sub> in cytosol; by computationally clamping the concentrations of each of these compounds, the model shows how both contribute to the dynamics of probe translocation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>lipid signaling; bradykinin; phospholipase C; mathematical modeling; confocal microscopy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PIP<sub>2</sub>)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref> which represents &#x0003c;1% of membrane phospholipids, is the predominant (&#x0003e;99%) doubly phosphorylated phosphoinositide in mammalian cells (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Vanhaesebroeck et al., 2001</xref>). It plays important roles in PLC-mediated cellular processes because hydrolysis of PIP<sub>2</sub> by PLC generates DAG and inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (InsP<sub>3</sub>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Berridge and Irvine, 1984</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Berridge, 1993</xref>), which serve as second messengers for intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization and PKC activation, respectively. Recent papers show PIP<sub>2</sub> also plays important roles in membrane trafficking (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Huijbregts et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Manifava et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Martin, 2001</xref>), interactions with cytoskeletons (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Nebl et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Rozelle et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Sechi and Wehland, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">van Rheenen and Jalink, 2002</xref>), and modulation of ion transporters and channels (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Czech, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Hilgemann et al., 2001</xref>).</p><p>We have been interested in the activation of the PLC signaling pathway, particularly in a neuronal context, and have examined this extensively in a murine neuroblastoma cell line, N1E-115. In these cells, activation of the endogenously expressed bradykinin B2, a G protein&#x02013;coupled receptor, results in a significant elevation of the intracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] and [InsP<sub>3</sub>] (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>), and M current inhibition (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Higashida and Brown, 1987</xref>). We have found that M current inhibition does depend on activation of PLC, but has much slower kinetics than either InsP<sub>3</sub> or Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Xu and Loew, 2003</xref>). Also recently, it has been shown that membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> level plays an important role in M current modulation (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Suh and Hille, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2003</xref>).</p><p>Although InsP<sub>3</sub> increase is a direct consequence of PIP<sub>2</sub> hydrolysis induced by PLC activation, it was noted in several papers that the InsP<sub>3</sub> kinetics are generally more rapid compared with the decrease and subsequent recovery in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Kaya et al., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Willars et al., 1998</xref>). It should be pointed out that the level of cellular PIP<sub>2</sub> is actually regulated by the balance between the degradative and synthetic enzymes. The recovery of membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> is probably mediated by PIP<sub>2</sub> resynthesis at the plasma membrane. The majority of PIP<sub>2</sub> is synthesized via the sequential phosphorylation of phosphatidylinositol (PI) at the 4&#x02032; position by PI 4-kinases to produce PI 4-phosphate, and then at the 5&#x02032; position by type I phosphoinositide 5-kinases (for reviews see <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Toker, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Tolias and Cantley, 1999</xref>). Recently, it has been found that PIP<sub>2</sub> can also be synthesized via the phosphorylation of PI 5-phosphate at the 4&#x02032; position by type II phosphoinositide 5-kinases (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Rameh et al., 1997</xref>). On the other hand, other than PLC, the degradation of PIP<sub>2</sub> can be mediated either by PI 3-kinases or PIP<sub>2</sub> 5-phosphatases such as synaptojanin (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Nemoto et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Sakisaka et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Takenawa et al., 1999</xref>).</p><p>It has been noted that activation of PLC by &#x003b1;1-adrenergic and muscarinic agonists caused an increased <sup>32</sup>P incorporation into polyphospho-PIs in myocardium (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kiss and Farkas, 1975</xref>; <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Quist, 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Quist and Sanchez, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Sekar and Roufogalis, 1984</xref>), as well as an increased generation of InsP<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 1981</xref>). Additionally, it has been found that both InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub> increase at the time of fertilization in sea urchin, <italic>Xenopus</italic>, and mouse eggs (<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 1984</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Ciapa et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Stith et al., 1993</xref>, <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Snow et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Halet et al., 2002</xref>), and during the stimulation of platelets with thrombin (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Lassing and Lindberg 1990</xref>). All these findings suggest that hydrolysis and synthesis of plasma membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> may be tightly coupled such that PIP<sub>2</sub> synthesis rapidly compensates for, or is independently stimulated by, its hydrolysis. Moreover, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chahwala et al. (1987)</xref> found that the guanine nucleotide analogue guanosine 5&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-(3-thiotriphosphate) (GTP&#x003b3;S), which could stimulate G proteins, activated PLC in [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol-labeled fibroblast cells. They also found that the GTP&#x003b3;S-induced increase in InsP<sub>3</sub> was 10 times over the decrease in PIP<sub>2</sub>, suggesting that a stimulated PIP<sub>2</sub> synthesis by PI and PIP kinases might accompany activation of PLC.</p><p>Recently, a GFP fusion protein, which consists of the pleckstrin homology (PH) domain of PLC&#x003b4;1 fused to GFP (PH-GFP), was developed as a probe for PIP<sub>2</sub> in single cells (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Stauffer et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Varnai and Balla, 1998</xref>). This indicator has a high affinity for PIP<sub>2</sub> and InsP<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Rebecchi et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lemmon et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Kavran et al., 1998</xref>) because of multiple hydrogen bond formations between its PH domain residues and the 4-and 5-phosphates on the inositol ring (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 1995</xref>). The expressed fluorescent probe predominantly associates with the plasma membrane in unstimulated cells (consistent with the distribution of PIP<sub>2</sub> in mammalian cells), and translocates to the cytosol on activation of PLC. Because PLC&#x003b4;-PH shows 10&#x02013;20-fold higher affinity for InsP<sub>3</sub> than PIP<sub>2</sub> in vitro (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">McLaughlin et al., 2002</xref>), there are disputes about whether the translocation of PH-GFP from membrane to cytosol is due to a decrease in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> level or an increase in cytosolic InsP<sub>3</sub>. Although <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Halet et al. (2002)</xref> and <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al. (2001)</xref> showed that 10&#x02013;100 &#x003bc;M of photoreleased InsP<sub>3</sub> was required to induce the translocation of PH-GFP from the plasma membrane, suggesting physiological increases of InsP<sub>3</sub> on activation of PLC (e.g., 3 &#x003bc;M in N1E-115 cells, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; or 0.3 &#x003bc;M in smooth muscle cells, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999b</xref>) could not be solely responsible for translocation of PH-GFP; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al. (1999)</xref> found intracellular injection of small amount of InsP<sub>3</sub> (&#x0003c;10 &#x003bc;M) caused significant translocation of PH-GFP; they also showed that rapid degradation of InsP<sub>3</sub> by overexpression of an InsP<sub>3</sub> 5-phosphatase abolished agonist-induced PH-GFP translocation (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Okubo et al., 2001</xref>), suggesting translocation of PH-GFP was monitoring changes in InsP<sub>3</sub>.</p><p>In this paper, we compared biochemical experiments measuring the kinetics of the bradykinin-induced changes in PIP<sub>2</sub> mass in suspensions of N1E-115 neuroblastoma cells with the results of single-cell measurements of PH-GFP translocation. This extends our earlier work on the bradykinin-induced InsP<sub>3</sub> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> dynamics in these cells (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). In these works, we make extensive use of the &#x0201c;Virtual Cell&#x0201d; modeling environment (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Schaff et al., 1997</xref>, <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Loew and Schaff 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Slepchenko et al., 2002</xref>) to analyze the data and to develop a quantitative mechanistic understanding of the system. We show that the analysis predicts, and subsequent experiments confirm, an initial stimulated increase in PIP<sub>2</sub> concomitant with activation of PLC-mediated PIP<sub>2</sub> hydrolysis. Furthermore, the kinetic analysis offers an approach toward reconciling the conflicting works on the behavior of PH-GFP.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Phosphoinositide content in N1E-115 cells</title><p>Phosphoinositides, the majority of which include PI, lyso-PI, PI 4-phosphate, and PIP<sub>2</sub>, are minor constituents of membrane lipids in eukaryotic cells, yet play important roles in signal transduction (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Berridge and Irvine, 1984</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Payrastre et al., 2001</xref>). First, we determined the [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol incorporation into phosphoinositides that were separated on oxalate-impregnated silica gel thin-layer plates using a developing solvent system of chloroform/methanol/4 N NH<sub>4</sub>OH (45:35:10, vol/vol/vol). Over the first 24 h, incubation of N1E-115 cells with [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol led to marked changes in the distribution of <sup>3</sup>H radioactivity in PI, lyso-PI, PIP, and PIP<sub>2</sub> under unstimulated conditions (unpublished data). However, no significant differences between cells labeled for 24, 44, 48, or 52 h were found under either unstimulated or stimulated conditions (unpublished data). Therefore, the phosphoinositide pools were believed to be in equilibrium after 48 h incubation with [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>, the Rf values of the four major phosphoinositides were consistent with the Rf values previously reported (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez-Sastre and Folch-Pi, 1968</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Racagni et al., 1992</xref>). The relative distribution of <sup>3</sup>H radioactivity in PI, lyso-PI, PIP, and PIP<sub>2</sub> in the unstimulated N1E-115 cells prelabeled with [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol for 48 h is also shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>. Although [<sup>3</sup>H]PI was the major component of the [<sup>3</sup>H]phosphoinositide (85.4 &#x000b1; 2.8%), [<sup>3</sup>H]PIP<sub>2</sub> and [<sup>3</sup>H]PIP only represented 2.3 &#x000b1; 0.6% and 2.0 &#x000b1; 0.2%, respectively (<italic>n</italic> = 7). When labeled to equilibrium by [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol, [<sup>3</sup>H]phosphoinositides have a similar distribution as the endogenous inositol lipids (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Kaya et al., 1989</xref>). Therefore, our paper indicates that PI is the most abundant phosphoinositide in N1E-115 cells, whereas PIP and PIP<sub>2</sub> occur in trace amounts only.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table I.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Relative levels and Rfs of [</bold>
<sup>3</sup>
<bold>H]phosphoinositides in [</bold>
<sup>3</sup>
<bold>H]inositol-prelabeled N1E-115 cells determined by TLC</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">Radioactivity</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">Rf</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">100 &#x000b1; 0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">0.49 &#x000b1; 0.02</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Lyso-PI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">12.6 &#x000b1; 3.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">0.41 &#x000b1; 0.02</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PIP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">2.4 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">0.27 &#x000b1; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PIP<sub>2</sub>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">2.8 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">0.11 &#x000b1; 0.02</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>[<sup>3</sup>H]phosphoinositide distribution in [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol-prelabeled N1E-115 cells was prepared and analyzed as described in Materials and methods. Values shown are mean &#x000b1; SEM of seven experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To examine the relative content of PIP<sub>2</sub> in the cell membrane, cells were labeled to equilibrium with [<sup>32</sup>P]PO<sub>4</sub>
<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>. We used the same TLC system as described in the previous paragraph to resolve PIP<sub>2</sub> from the other phosphoinositides (PI, PI 4-phosphate) and all other plasma membrane phospholipids (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez-Sastre and Folch-Pi, 1968</xref>). Our data showed that PIP<sub>2</sub> comprised 0.43 &#x000b1; 0.02% of total cellular phospholipids. We assume 50% of total cellular phospholipids are present in the plasma membrane (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lange et al., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Warnock et al., 1993</xref>). Additionally, recent evidence from one cell line indicates that &#x0223c;40% of total cellular PIP<sub>2</sub> is present in the plasma membrane (<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Watt et al., 2002</xref>). Thus, the basal level of PIP<sub>2</sub> can be estimated at 0.3% of phospholipids in the plasma membrane. Furthermore, the percentage of PIP<sub>2</sub> relative to the phospholipids in the inner leaflet of the plasma membrane would be 0.5% because 80% of PIP<sub>2</sub> is found in the inner leaflet of the plasma membrane. Assuming that phospholipids cover 60% of the inner surface (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Jain, 1980</xref>), and that a single lipid molecule occupies 70&#x000c5;<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">McLaughlin et al., 1981</xref>), a surface density of 4,000 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup> for PIP<sub>2</sub> can be estimated. This will be taken as the basal level of PIP<sub>2</sub>; the basal levels of the other inositides can then be calculated from <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Bradykinin-induced decrease in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> level</title><p>On addition of a 1-&#x003bc;M concentration of bradykinin that is maximal for the bradykinin receptor-mediated InsP<sub>3</sub> generation (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>), there was a relative decrease of PIP<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, black diamonds), which was detectable by 10 s, and reached a minimum (&#x02212;36.0 &#x000b1; 6.0%, <italic>n</italic> = 5) by 20 s. Levels of [<sup>3</sup>H]PIP<sub>2</sub> recovered to basal levels in &#x0223c;150 s in the continued presence of bradykinin. The rate of recovery of PIP<sub>2</sub> was much slower than that of InsP<sub>3</sub>, which reaches its maximum before 10 s and returns to basal levels by 30 s at 37&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Also shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> are the experimental data for PIP, which show relatively little change after bradykinin stimulation.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Experimental and simulated time courses of bradykinin-induced changes of PIP<sub>2</sub> and PIP in N1E-115 cells.</bold> [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol-prelabeled N1E-115 cells were incubated in the presence of 1 &#x003bc;M bradykinin for the indicated times. Membrane lipids were extracted and analyzed as described in Materials and methods. Each data point is the mean &#x000b1; SEM of three to five experiments. All experiments were performed at RT. Black diamonds represent our initial determination of PIP<sub>2</sub> changes; purple triangles are the PIP data. These data, along with our prior study of InsP<sub>3</sub> dynamics in this cell, were used to constrain a model that produced the respective black and purple solid curves. The pathways that were modeled are shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, and the model equations and parameters are described in the . The prediction of the model that there was an initial increase in [PIP<sub>2</sub>] led us to determine the change in PIP<sub>2</sub> at 5 s, shown as a red diamond. The model calculation of the change in [InsP<sub>3</sub>] is shown in the inset.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f1"/></fig><p>It should be mentioned that, in some earlier works, absolute PIP<sub>2</sub> mass was determined by assay of InsP<sub>3</sub> released by alkaline hydrolysis (<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Willars et al., 1998</xref>). In our work, [<sup>3</sup>H]PIP<sub>2</sub> mass was determined from the radioactivity of the PIP<sub>2</sub> spot on a silica gel TLC plate (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Kaya et al., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Racagni et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Lukacova and Marsala, 1997</xref>), which might contain radioactivity from other doubly phosphorylated phosphoinositides such as PI 3,4-bisphosphate. However, because PIP<sub>2</sub> is the predominant (&#x0003e;99%) doubly phosphorylated phosphoinositide in mammalian cells (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Vanhaesebroeck et al., 2001</xref>), the contribution to [<sup>3</sup>H]PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> radioactivity from [<sup>3</sup>H]PI(3,4)-bisphosphate should be negligible.</p></sec><sec><title>Bradykinin stimulates membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> synthesis, resulting in an initial increase in PIP<sub>2</sub>
</title><p>We analyzed the experiments in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> using the Virtual Cell software with a simple model consisting of a transient activation of PLC-mediated PIP<sub>2</sub> hydrolysis followed by a slow recovery to basal levels via phosphorylation of PI and PIP (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Mathematical details of the model are provided in the , along with a list of the parameters and how they were chosen. The results of the simulation are shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> so as to permit ready comparison to the experiment.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Reaction scheme for the synthesis and hydrolysis of PIP<sub>2</sub>.</bold> The membrane-associated reactions are shown at the top, and the cytosol reactions on the bottom. These reaction schemes form the basis of the mathematical models that were developed to analyze the data. Details of the rate expressions for each of the reactions (shown in red) are provided in the .</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f2"/></fig><p>A key constraint on the model was the previously determined level and kinetics of InsP<sub>3</sub> produced during bradykinin-induced activation of PLC. Previous findings in this lab indicated that bradykinin-induced generation of InsP<sub>3</sub> in N1E-115 cells reached its peak of several &#x003bc;M before 10 s (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). This previous work used quantitative photorelease of caged InsP<sub>3</sub> and calcium imaging to establish the amount of InsP<sub>3</sub> required to attain a level of calcium release equivalent to that obtained with maximal stimulation with bradykinin. We also directly determined the bradykinin-induced InsP<sub>3</sub> kinetics using a combination of modeling and direct biochemical InsP<sub>3</sub> mass determinations. In the present model, we adjusted some of the parameters to reflect the slower kinetics of bradykinin-induced calcium dynamics (<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Xu and Loew, 2003</xref>) and slower InsP<sub>3</sub> degradation at RT. But our experimentally determined decrease of PIP<sub>2</sub> simply couldn't account for sufficient InsP<sub>3</sub> unless a stimulated synthesis of PIP<sub>2</sub> was resupplying this substrate. This stimulated synthesis was added to the model using PIP as the required precursor. However, because basal PIP was itself even lower than PIP<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>), PIP resupply through stimulated phosphorylation of PI also had to be incorporated into the model. PI is in abundant supply, so its depletion is insignificant and would not affect the kinetics of either PIP or PIP<sub>2</sub>.</p><p>The resultant model predicted a transient increase of PIP<sub>2</sub> at times earlier than our initial experimental time points (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, the rise of the black simulation curve above the baseline between 0 and 8 s). To investigate this possibility, we measured the bradykinin-induced change in [<sup>3</sup>H]PIP<sub>2</sub> at 5 s. Indeed, we found that bradykinin caused a relative increase in [<sup>3</sup>H]PIP<sub>2</sub> (36.3 &#x000b1; 8.6%, <italic>n</italic> = 3) compared with that before stimulation (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, red diamond). To confirm that the increase in PIP<sub>2</sub> is due to PIP<sub>2</sub> synthesis, we pretreated the cells with micromolar wortmannin (30 &#x003bc;M, 15 min). Wortmannin at nanomolar concentrations inhibits PI 3-kinases, but at micromolar concentrations, it also inhibits the activity of most PI 4-kinases (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Nakanishi et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Downing et al., 1996</xref>). In cells treated with wortmannin, the increase in [<sup>3</sup>H]PIP<sub>2</sub> at 5 s was abolished; instead, a relative decrease in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> (&#x02212;5.1 &#x000b1; 1.1%, <italic>n</italic> = 4) was obtained.</p></sec><sec><title>Bradykinin-induced PH-GFP translocation</title><p>Knowing that the kinetics of bradykinin-induced decrease in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> and increase in cytosolic InsP<sub>3</sub> were very different in terms of both time-to-peak and recovery, we tried to determine whether PH-GFP translocation mimicked changes in PIP2 or InsP3 in single cells. When expressed in N1E-115 cells, PH-GFP showed a strong accumulation at the plasma membrane and a low and homogenous distribution in the cytosol (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>), consistent with the idea that PH-GFP primarily binds to membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> at rest. Several explanations for the low resting intracellular PH-GFP fluorescence are possible: (1) intracellular pools of PIP<sub>2</sub> are not accessible to PH-GFP (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Balla et al., 2000</xref>); (2) some intracellular PIP<sub>2</sub> phosphatases (e.g., synaptojanin) have hydrolyzed the PIP<sub>2</sub> on the internal membranes and restricted the steady-state accumulation of PIP<sub>2</sub> to the plasma membrane (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Stefan et al., 2002</xref>); or (3) a significant amount of PIP<sub>2</sub> is on the organelle membranes and can bind PH-GFP (<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Watt et al., 2002</xref>), but its lower volumetric density compared with the plasma membrane produces a lower fluorescence. In this work, we measured fluorescence from membrane GFP, segmented by a combination of threshold operations and manual editing, and cytosolic fluorescence regions of interest individually for each time point; we did not use the more common procedure of measuring the amplitude of the fluorescence signal at the plasma membrane and cytosol region along a line across the cell for all time points because we found that bradykinin could induce cell shape changes, and hence, changes of the originally assigned membrane regions. After addition of bradykinin, there was a decrease in plasma membrane PH-GFP fluorescence and a concomitant increase in cytosolic fluorescence (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). The maximum relative change in membrane GFP fluorescence was &#x02212;11.3 &#x000b1; 1.7% (<italic>n</italic> = 19), whereas the relative change in cytosolic fluorescence was 41.1 &#x000b1; 4.7% (<italic>n</italic> = 19). The kinetics of bradykinin-induced PH-GFP translocation is characterized by a rapid onset, with translocation peaking at &#x0223c;20 to 30 s and returning to the baseline in &#x0223c;3 min in the continued presence of bradykinin (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). This time course is very similar to the time course of PIP<sub>2</sub> hydrolysis detected biochemically from [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol-labeled cells, in line with the previous finding that PH-GFP translocation primarily reports changes in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> content (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al., 2001</xref>). However, the bradykinin-induced PH-GFP translocation did not exhibit an initial increase in PIP<sub>2</sub>, raising the possibility that PH-GFP translocation might not be determined solely by changes in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub>.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Bradykinin-induced translocation of PH-GFP from the plasma membrane in a single N1E-115 cell.</bold> A single N1E-115 cell was stimulated with 1 &#x003bc;M bradykinin. PH-GFP translocation was reflected as a decrease in the membrane GFP fluorescence and a concomitant increase in cytosolic fluorescence. The experiment was performed at RT. (A) Time series of images with the time indicated on each frame in seconds. Bradykinin was added at time 0 (after the third frame). (B) Relative change in GFP fluorescence at two locations in the cytosol of the cell in the images in A. Region 1 is indicated in the first frame of A by the rectangle just above the nucleus; region 2 is indicated by the rectangle in the larger area of cytosol below the nucleus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f3"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Kinetics of bradykinin-induced PH-GFP translocation.</bold> The average changes in membrane and cytosol fluorescence after addition of 1 &#x003bc;M bradykinin are plotted versus time. Each point was the mean &#x000b1; SEM of 19 experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f4"/></fig><p>The expression level of PH-GFP may be an important factor in determining the extent to which membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> and cytosolic InsP<sub>3</sub> affect the distribution of the PH-GFP. We estimated intracellular GFP concentrations by comparing the cytosolic fluorescence intensities of individual cells in situ to those of a series of dilutions of purified GFP protein of known concentration (see Materials and methods). The basal levels of cytosolic PH-GFP ranged from 3 to 12 &#x003bc;M, with an average of 5.9 &#x000b1; 0.5 &#x003bc;M (<italic>n</italic> = 19). However, we did not find any significant correlation between the basal cytosolic PH-GFP concentration and either the time constants or the amplitudes of the bradykinin-induced PH-GFP translocation, possibly because the range of PH-GFP expression levels was not sufficient.</p><p>We elaborated the model used to analyze the biochemical data on inositide turnover to see if it could also predict the PH-GFP translocation experiments. The basal concentration of total PH-GFP in the cytosol (free plus bound to InsP<sub>3</sub>) was taken as 6 &#x003bc;M from our measurements. Binding constants to InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub> were taken from in vitro measurements reported in the literature (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>). Taken with the basal levels of InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub>, these determined the basal levels of the bound forms of PH-GFP. Thus, all the additional model parameters were completely based on measured values (albeit in vitro), and no parameters were adjusted to fit the results of <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>. All these parameters are provided in Table AII of the . The results of a compartmental model, elaborated from the one used in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, are shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>. The results of a two-dimensional spatial simulation, based on the geometry of one of the cells of <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, are shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Simulation of PH-GFP translocation.</bold> The compartmental model used in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> was expanded to include PH-GFP binding. Additional parameters are in Table AII, and model equations are in the . The blue curve represents the relative change in total cytosolic GFP (free PH-GFP + InsP<sub>3</sub>&#x02013;PH-GFP), and can be directly compared with the corresponding experimental results in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>. The pink curve corresponds to the relative change in PIP<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;PH-GFP surface density on the plasma membrane. Because the confocal imaging system detects both fluorescence from the membrane and the adjacent cytosol, the PIP<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;PH-GFP results were adjusted by an appropriate contribution from the total cytosolic signal in the yellow curve, as detailed in the text, to allow comparison with the experimental result in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f5"/></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Results of an image-based spatial simulation of PH-GFP translocation after bradykinin-induced stimulation.</bold> The image of the cell on the right side of the images in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> was used as the basis of the two-dimensional geometry. The cytosolic resting level of PH-GFP that was measured for this cell was 4.6 &#x003bc;M, and this was the value used in the simulation. Other parameters were similar to the compartmental simulations (Table AI and Table AII). Details of the simulation are given in the . (Top row) Selected time points for the relative changes in total cytosolic PH-GFP (free + bound to InsP<sub>3</sub>). (Second row) Percent change in PH-GFP associated with PIP<sub>2</sub> in the plasma membrane. (Third row) Concentration of free InsP<sub>3</sub>, indicated by the color bar in unit of &#x003bc;M, in the cytosol showing the buffering effect of PH-GFP as described in the text. (Fourth row) Surface density of PIP<sub>2</sub>, indicated by the color scale in molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>, also showing the buffering effect of the indicator.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f6"/></fig><p>The change in the cytosolic concentration in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> and the top row of <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> can be directly compared with the corresponding experimental results in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, respectively; this is because the intensity measured within a confocal volume correctly reflects the concentration of a fluorophore whenever the confocal voxel is well within the volume of the container that surrounds the fluorophore, i.e., the volume contained by the cell (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1998</xref>). We estimate our confocal volume to be &#x0223c;0.7 &#x000d7; 0.7 &#x003bc;m within the focal plane, and 2.1 &#x003bc;m in the axial dimension. In our experiments, we placed the focal plane near the center of the cell, and the cell dimensions are significantly larger than the confocal volume. However, this same consideration precludes direct comparison of the measured fluorescence change from the cell periphery and the simulation results from the plasma membrane (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, pink curve; <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, second row). The confocal volume encompassing the thin monolayer of membrane fluorescence also contains essentially all of the adjacent cytosolic fluorescence. To account for this, we estimated the total PH-GFP species within a 1-&#x003bc;m<sup>3</sup> (0.7 &#x000d7; 0.7 &#x000d7; 2.1 &#x003bc;m<sup>3</sup>) volume encompassing the membrane by adding the PIP<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;PH-GFP molecules in a vertical patch of membrane 0.7 &#x000d7; 2.1 &#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup> to the PH-GFP and IP<sub>3</sub>&#x02013;PH-GFP in a 0.7 &#x000d7; 0.7 &#x000d7; 2.1 &#x003bc;m<sup>3</sup> region adjacent to the membrane. The relative change of this quantity is depicted in yellow in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>.</p><p>As can be seen, all three curves in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> show that the simulated translocation of PH-GFP only slightly reflects the initial increase in PIP<sub>2</sub> determined from both the model and the experiment of <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. Of course, this initial increase is still present in the simulation results for unbound PIP<sub>2</sub> in the presence of PH-GFP (shown for the spatial simulation in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). Indeed, the fact that the simulation results in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> for the PH-GFP translocation are reasonably close to the experimental observations in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> provides additional support for the overall model. Of course, there are some discrepancies, and it would be important to explore potential sources of error in the model. The most important implicit assumptions in the model are that PH-GFP&#x02013;bound forms of both InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub> are protected from degradation. That is, as shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, PIP<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;PH-GFP does not directly hydrolyze to InsP<sub>3</sub>, and IP<sub>3</sub>&#x02013;PH-GFP does not directly become degraded. This has the effect of slowing inositide turnover by sequestering a dynamic fraction in the PH-GFP bound forms. That the turnover of these molecules is inhibited by PH-GFP is clear (<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Varnai and Balla 1998</xref>), but that the extent of inhibition is complete in both bound form may be an oversimplification. The assumption of complete inhibition of InsP<sub>3</sub> degradation in the bound form is probably the primary source of the slower recovery of translocation in the simulation compared with the experiment. Clearly, another important approximation of the model is the application of in vitro biochemically determined Kd's for binding of PH-GFP to InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub> to an analysis of in vivo experiments, but no in vivo measurements are available. Additionally, the possibility of special binding mechanisms in vivo has recently been suggested to explain the different binding behavior of various PH isoforms (<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Varnai et al., 2002</xref>).</p><p>The results for the PH-GFP translocation in the spatial model (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, top row) also capture the features of the experimental results from that cell (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, right-hand cell). In particular, the nucleus creates a small diffusion barrier that effectively creates a high surface-to-volume region of cytosol to its upper right compared with the larger cytosolic region below the nucleus. The nuclear diffusion barrier creates a temporary buildup of released PH-GFP in the upper right that is seen both experimentally (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B, compare the respective plots for region 1 and 2) and in the simulation (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>; namely, the faster and higher rise of PH-GFP in that region of the cell revealed by the pseudocolor display in the top row).</p><p>It is also instructive to compare the changes in PIP<sub>2</sub> and InsP<sub>3</sub> in the presence of PH-GFP, shown in the bottom two rows of <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, with the changes that the model calculates when the PH-GFP is removed, shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>. The simulation results in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> are the result of simply setting the concentrations of all of the PH-GFP molecular species to zero and are mathematically equivalent to the application of the nonspatial model of <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> to our two-dimensional geometry. As can be seen, both the rates and the amplitudes of the changes in InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub> are severely reduced in the presence of 6 &#x003bc;M PH-GFP, which effectively acts as a buffer for both of these molecules. These simulations suggest that caution is required in interpreting the physiology of PH-GFP&#x02013;transfected cells. Indeed, the ability of PH-GFP to impede access of PLC to PIP<sub>2</sub> was recognized in one of the original papers that described this probe (<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Varnai and Balla, 1998</xref>). Whether PH&#x003b4;1-GFP inhibits InsP<sub>3</sub>-dependent calcium release has not been reported to our knowledge, although it has been reported for another PH domain isoform (<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Varnai et al., 2002</xref>).</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Results of an image-based spatial simulation of phosphoinositide turnover after bradykinin-induced stimulation.</bold> The simulations were performed as in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, except that PH-GFP was not included in the system. (Top row) Concentration of InsP<sub>3</sub> in the cytosol. (Second row) Selected time points for the surface density of PIP<sub>2</sub>. The same scales were used as in the bottom two rows of <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> to facilitate comparison.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f7"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Is PH-GFP translocation reporting changes in PIP<sub>2</sub> or InsP<sub>3</sub>?</title><p>There has been considerable uncertainty in the literature as to whether PH-GFP translocation monitors changes in PIP<sub>2</sub> or InsP<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al., 2001</xref>). Physiologically, a decrease in PIP<sub>2</sub> will be accompanied by an increase in InsP<sub>3</sub>, so it is difficult to know which is the primary source for translocation of the probe from the plasma membrane to the cytosol. Experiments where the concentration of one molecule is clamped while the other molecule is changed can give seemingly contradictory results. For example, microinjection of InsP<sub>3</sub> led to translocation (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>), whereas photorelease of similar intracellular concentrations from a caged precursor (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al., 2001</xref>) did not.</p><p>However, in our mathematical model, we can design thought experiments in which each of these molecules is clamped at its initial concentration, and then perform simulations to see how the system would respond to the bradykinin stimulus. The changes in total cytosolic PH-GFP from such calculations are shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, with the results for the regular compartmental model shown for comparison. The calculation labeled &#x0201c;Fixed InsP<sub>3</sub>&#x0201d; included all the reactions in the regular model, but the concentration of InsP<sub>3</sub> in the cytosol was clamped to its initial value of 0.16 &#x003bc;M; this is equivalent to introducing a new InsP<sub>3</sub> degradation mechanism with a perfect feedback control to assure a rate that is precisely tuned to maintain 0.16 &#x003bc;M at all rates of PIP<sub>2</sub> hydrolysis. Similarly, the calculation labeled &#x0201c;Fixed PIP<sub>2</sub>&#x0201d; clamps the PIP<sub>2</sub> surface density at its initial value of 4,000 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>, while allowing InsP<sub>3</sub> production to proceed at a rate identical to that in the regular model. As can be seen, both of these circumstances produce significant translocation of the probe, suggesting that PH-GFP translocation is independently sensitive to both changes in PIP<sub>2</sub> and InsP<sub>3</sub>. Of the two cases, the change in InsP<sub>3</sub> (i.e., clamped PIP<sub>2</sub>) produces a PH-GFP translocation that is closer to that produced by the full simulation. However, it should be emphasized that these results would be particularly sensitive to the relative affinities of the probe for InsP<sub>3</sub> vs. PIP<sub>2</sub>, and again the values were taken from in vitro experiments.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Compartmental simulations with fixed InsP<sub>3</sub> or PIP<sub>2</sub>.</bold> The model of <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> was used, except that InsP<sub>3</sub> (green) or PIP<sub>2</sub> (blue) are clamped at their initial values. Only the change in total cytosolic PH-GFP is shown because this is the only model output that may be directly compared with the corresponding experimental result (shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) as explained in the text. Also shown for comparison is the result produced by the full model in which all molecules are allowed to vary (black curve).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f8"/></fig><p>We also used the model to examine the contrasting results that were reported when InsP<sub>3</sub> is introduced into cells in the absence of receptor-mediated activation of PLC. <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al. (1999)</xref> reported that injection of 1 &#x003bc;M InsP<sub>3</sub> could produce large translocation of PH-GFP, whereas <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al. (2001)</xref> used photorelease of caged InsP<sub>3</sub> to reach the opposite conclusion. <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> shows a series of simulations of the translocation response to a 1-&#x003bc;M instantaneous bolus of InsP<sub>3</sub> at time 0 in the absence of phosphoinositide turnover. The three traces correspond to differing initial concentrations of total cytosolic PH-GFP, with the central concentration (6 &#x003bc;M) corresponding to the average concentration of the probe measured in our experiments. As can be seen, the translocation produced by 1 &#x003bc;M InsP<sub>3</sub> in the presence of 6 &#x003bc;M total cytosolic PH-GFP is predicted to be much smaller than that produced in the full model of receptor-activated phosphoinositide turnover (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, black trace). However, the effect is very sensitive to the expression level of the indicator over a 10-fold range. <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al. (1999)</xref> and <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al. (2001)</xref> did not report the concentrations of indicator in their respective experiments. So, the difference in their results may be a consequence of a low PH-GFP expression level in the former and a high expression level in the latter. In conclusion, our results suggest that the relative or percent change in translocation after stimulated phosphoinositide turnover will be higher with lower concentrations of PH-GFP, when the PH-GFP will not buffer a significant fraction of either membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> or cytosolic IP<sub>3</sub>. However, at very low concentrations, the intensity of the fluorescence may, of course, become limiting.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Compartmental simulation of the response of the steady-state system to an instantaneous bolus of 1</bold> &#x003bc;<bold>M InsP<sub>3</sub>.</bold> The same compartmental model was used, except that the bradykinin stimulus was never applied. Instead, InsP<sub>3</sub> was stepped from the basal level of 0.16 &#x003bc;M to 1.16 &#x003bc;M at time 0. This was equivalent to a rapid injection or a pulse of photorelease. The response of PH-GFP translocation is displayed for three initial total cytosolic concentrations of the indicator. The central value of 6 &#x003bc;M (blue curve) corresponds to the average expression level in our cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200301070f9"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In this paper, we showed that bradykinin induced first an increase, then a decrease, in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> in N1E-115 neuroblastoma cells. Micromolar wortmannin, which blocks most PI 4-kinases (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Nakanishi et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Downing et al., 1996</xref>) and PI 3-kinases, completely abolished the initial increase and even revealed an immediate decrease in PIP<sub>2</sub>. Because PI 4-kinases are required for PIP<sub>2</sub> synthesis, these results could indicate that bradykinin leads to a rapid activation of PIP<sub>2</sub>-synthesizing kinases, and that this effect precedes the hydrolysis of PIP<sub>2</sub> mediated by PLC. The rapid synthesis of PIP<sub>2</sub> can also explain why the maximum decrease in PIP<sub>2</sub> occurs at 20 s, 10 s behind the maximum increase in both InsP<sub>3</sub> and intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Xu and Loew, 2003</xref>). Bradykinin binds to B<sub>2</sub> receptor (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Coggan and Thompson, 1995</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>) in N1E-115 cells, which use a GTP-binding protein, G<sub>q</sub>, to activate phospholipase C&#x003b2;1. Whether bradykinin uses the same signal pathway to activate PI 4-kinase and PLC is not known. It should be pointed out, though, that a decrease in the activity of PIP<sub>2</sub> phosphatases could also lead to an increase of PIP<sub>2</sub>. Whether bradykinin inhibits PIP<sub>2</sub> phosphatase in N1E-115 cells remains to be determined.</p><p>Consistent with our findings, <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Yorek et al. (1994)</xref> found that bradykinin stimulated <sup>32</sup>P incorporation into PIP and PIP<sub>2</sub> as well as InsP<sub>3</sub> release in neuroblastoma cells. Similarly, it was found that binding of thrombin to its receptors caused a synthesis of PIP and PIP<sub>2</sub>, preceded by degradation of these phosphoinositides in platelets (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Lassing and Lindberg, 1990</xref>). In fibroblasts, net synthesis of the phosphoinositides was revealed when hydrolysis of PIP<sub>2</sub> was blocked by neomycin (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Carney et al., 1985</xref>). Also in fibroblasts, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chahwala et al. (1987)</xref> found that the GTP&#x003b3;S-stimulated hydrolysis of PIP<sub>2</sub> concomitant with an increase in InsP<sub>3</sub> that was 10 times over the decrease in PIP<sub>2</sub>, suggesting PIP<sub>2</sub> synthesis was also accelerated after GTP&#x003b3;S addition. In a very different system, it was shown in sea urchin (<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 1984</xref>) and <italic>Xenopus</italic> (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Snow et al., 1996</xref>) eggs that inositol lipid levels increased on fertilization, but this may be due to a later event associated with cortical granule exocytosis, as has been recently shown for mouse egg fertilization (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Halet et al., 2002</xref>). In any case, the generality of a concurrent receptor-mediated stimulation of PIP<sub>2</sub> hydrolysis and synthesis is certainly not established. This may be because the early transient nature of the phenomenon, as well as its unexpectedness, has made it elusive.</p><p>We further investigated the turnover of phosphoinositides by following the translocation of PH-GFP. In unstimulated cells, the PH-GFP was concentrated at the plasma membrane as seen before (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Stauffer et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Varnai and Balla, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Holz et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al., 2001</xref>), indicating it preferentially binds to the plasma membrane PIP<sub>2</sub>, possibly because there is a much higher cellular concentration of PIP<sub>2</sub> in the plasma membrane (4 &#x003bc;M in our cells and &#x0223c;10 &#x003bc;M in general; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">McLaughlin et al., 2002</xref>) than cytosolic InsP<sub>3</sub> in N1E-115 cells (0.16 &#x003bc;M; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>). PH-GFP translocation induced by bradykinin showed similar kinetics as the membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> change measured by TLC, consistent with the finding of <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al. (2001)</xref> that PH-GFP primarily reported membrane PIP<sub>2</sub>. However, the initial increase in membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> was not reflected in PH-GFP translocation. There may be several explanations for this discrepancy. First, overexpression of PH-GFP may interfere with cellular signals and inhibit synthesis of PIP<sub>2</sub>. However, simultaneous recording of PH-GFP translocation and intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> in N1E-115 cells showed that PH-GFP translocation also lagged behind the increase in intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> induced by bradykinin (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al., 2001</xref>), which correlated spatiotemporally with the InsP<sub>3</sub> increase (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>), suggesting synthesis of PIP<sub>2</sub> was still stimulated in the presence of PH-GFP. Another possible explanation is that PH-GFP translocation can be affected by both membrane PIP<sub>2</sub> and cytosolic InsP<sub>3</sub>, and the translocation induced by the initial synthesis of PIP<sub>2</sub> is masked by binding of PH-GFP to increased InsP<sub>3</sub>. There is compelling evidence that PH-GFP can monitor InsP<sub>3</sub> under some circumstances (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Nash et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Okubo et al., 2001</xref>) in that the amount of InsP<sub>3</sub> increase produced by PIP<sub>2</sub> hydrolysis is by itself sufficient to induce PH-GFP translocation. However, in the work of <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al. (2001)</xref>, it was found that interfering with PIP<sub>2</sub> resynthesis, but not InsP<sub>3</sub> generation, changed the kinetics of PH-GFP translocation in N1E-115 cells; this supports the idea that PH-GFP monitors PIP<sub>2</sub>. In both our experiments (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) and simulations (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>), the initial fast increase in PIP<sub>2</sub> is not reflected in the PH-GFP translocation, but the overall time course does more closely resemble the behavior of PIP<sub>2</sub> than InsP<sub>3</sub>.</p><p>A thorough analysis of the model helped to resolve some of these apparent contradictions, showing that PH-GFP translocation is sensitive to physiologically relevant changes in both InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub>. First, the model results for PH-GFP translocation (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) produce reasonably good agreement with the experiment (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Because the parameters associated with PH-GFP binding to InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub> were taken directly from the literature, and no parameters were adjusted to accommodate the incorporation of PH-GFP translocation into the phosphoinositide turnover model of <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, the close agreement between experiment and simulation is further support for the hypotheses that underlie the model. The model does reveal that translocation is sensitive to both InsP<sub>3</sub> and PIP<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>), and that the presence of the indicator distorts the amplitude and time course of changes in both of these molecules through a buffering effect (compare <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> with <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). That this buffering effect can, in turn, severely diminish the sensitivity of the translocation to changes in phosphoinositide levels was illustrated in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>, where a 1-&#x003bc;M change in InsP<sub>3</sub> was calculated to give an insignificant translocation at high PH-GFP concentrations. Therefore, we suggest the expressed PH-GFP be kept at low concentrations so as not to buffer a significant fraction of either PIP<sub>2</sub> or IP<sub>3</sub>. By highlighting the sensitivity of the assay to PH-GFP expression level, <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> could also help to explain the apparent conflicts in the literature on the amount of translocation elicited by InsP<sub>3</sub> alone (e.g., <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al., 2001</xref>). It should also be pointed out that the receptor-mediated PLC activation may produce vastly differing amounts of InsP<sub>3</sub> for a given change in PIP<sub>2</sub> surface density in the plasma membrane in different cell lines. This would depend on the surface-to-volume ratio and the contribution of stimulated PIP<sub>2</sub> synthesis. For example, we have shown that bradykinin stimulates only a few hundred nM InsP<sub>3</sub> in a smooth muscle cell line even though this is still sufficient to elicit robust calcium release from the ER (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999b</xref>). With differing initial concentrations and differing surface-to-volume ratios, the translocation behavior of PH-GFP would have to be analyzed for each cell system to dissect the sensitivity to PIP<sub>2</sub> vs. InsP<sub>3</sub>.</p><p>We wish to conclude by emphasizing that this paper exemplifies the value of combining quantitative models with quantitative experiments. The initial results of our TLC experiments (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, black diamonds) could only be fit to a model that predicted an initial increase in PIP<sub>2</sub>. The hypothesis that was generated from this modeling result then prompted us to take an additional early experimental time point (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; red diamond) that confirmed the prediction. But additional experiments using the PH-GFP translocation assay on individual cells (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) failed to reveal this initial increase in PIP<sub>2</sub>. However, an expanded model that included binding of PH-GFP to both PIP<sub>2</sub> and InsP<sub>3</sub> based on in vitro literature binding constants (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) was largely consistent with the experiments, failing also to reveal an initial increase in PH-GFP association with the membrane even though the initial increase in PIP<sub>2</sub> was still present. Thus, the modeling result showed that the PH-GFP translocation experiment could not be used to argue against our initial hypothesis; indeed, it further supported it. Once we had this model, we could use it to visualize molecules that were not accessible experimentally (the spatiotemporal cellular distribution of PIP<sub>2</sub> and InsP<sub>3</sub> either in the presence, <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, or absence, <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, of PH-GFP). The model also allowed us to perform thought experiments (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> and <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>) that helped illuminate an important controversy in the literature on how to interpret results from this valuable and increasingly accepted live-cell assay for phosphoinositide turnover.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Preparation and treatment of cells prelabeled with [<sup>3</sup>H]inositol</title><p>N1E-115 cells were grown to 30&#x02013;40% confluency in 35-mm culture dishes. Approximately 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells per culture dish were incubated with 4 &#x003bc;Ci/ml of myo-[2-<sup>3</sup>H]inositol (PerkinElmer) in Eagle's basal medium containing 0.5% dialyzed heat-inactivated FBS for 48 h. After two rinses to remove the unincorporated <sup>3</sup>H radioactivity, the cells from each culture dish were scraped and suspended in 1 ml Eagle's balanced salt solution (EBSS). A 0.5-ml portion was homogenized and used for protein assay. Aliquots of 1.0 ml were transferred to 12-ml disposable screw cap polypropylene centrifuge tubes and used for each timed incubation (0, 5, 10, 20, 30, 60, 120, and 150 s) with EBSS containing 1 &#x003bc;M bradykinin. The incubation was terminated by pipetting 2 ml methanol to the tube. Then, 3 ml chloroform was added, followed by 1 ml 2.4 N HCl. The mixture was suspended by vortexing, and was centrifuged at 400 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min to separate the aqueous and organic phases. The lower layer was withdrawn, and the aqueous phase was reextracted with 2 ml chloroform. The two organic extracts were combined.</p></sec><sec><title>[<sup>3</sup>H]phosphoinositide analysis</title><p>Separation of phosphoinositides was performed as described by <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Kaya et al. (1989)</xref>. In brief, the lipid solution was dried under N<sub>2</sub>, redissolved in chloroform/methanol (7:3, vol/vol) and applied to a TLC plate (LK5D, Whatman) impregnated with 1% potassium oxalate and 2 mM EDTA, followed by development with an alkaline solvent system of chloroform, methanol, and 4 N NH<sub>4</sub>OH (45:35:10, vol/vol/vol; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez-Sastre and Folch-Pi, 1968</xref>) to separate phosphoinositides. All procedures were conducted at RT. The phosphoinositides were identified by co-migration with authentic lipid standards that were visualized with phosphomolybdic acid spray reagent (Sigma-Aldrich). The silica gel area containing radioactivity was scraped, incubated with 100 &#x003bc;l Soluene<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>-350 overnight (Packard Instrument Co.), and then suspended in CytoScint ES (ICN Biomedicals) and assayed for radioactivity with a scintillation counter (model 2000 CA; Packard Instrument Co.). After treatment with Soluene<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>-350, recovery of the <sup>3</sup>H radioactivity applied to the silica gel was almost 100%.</p></sec><sec><title>[<sup>32</sup>P]PIP<sub>2</sub> analysis</title><p>To examine the relative PIP<sub>2</sub> content of membrane, N1E-115 cells were grown to 30&#x02013;40% confluency in 35-mm culture dishes. Approximately 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells per culture dish were labeled to equilibrium (48 h) with 25 &#x003bc;Ci/ml [<sup>32</sup>P]PO<sub>4</sub> (carrier free; ICN Biomedicals) at 37&#x000b0;C in EBSS. After washing twice to remove the unincorporated <sup>32</sup>P, the cells were scraped and suspended with EBSS. Cell lipids were extracted with acidic chloroform-methanol as described previously (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Agranoff et al., 1983</xref>). A 20-&#x003bc;l aliquot of the lipid extract was subjected to TLC using TLC plates (LK5D; Whatman) impregnated with 1% potassium oxalate and 2 mM EDTA, and the mobile phase chloroform/methanol/4 N NH<sub>4</sub>OH (45:35:10; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez-Sastre and Folch-Pi, 1968</xref>). Radioactive bands were identified by co-chromatography of a PIP<sub>2</sub> standard. TLC spots were transferred to scintillation vials, suspended in CytoScint ES (ICN Biomedicals), and radioactivity was determined by liquid scintillation counting (model 2000 CA scintillation counter; Packard Instrument Co.). A second 20-&#x003bc;l aliquot of the lipid extract was applied to a piece of silica gel scraped from a blank TLC plate with area similar to the scraped PIP<sub>2</sub> spots, and suspended in CytoScint ES to determine radioactivity of the total lipids spotted.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell culture and transfections</title><p>N1E-115 neuroblastoma cells were seeded in 35-mm culture dishes at &#x0223c;15,000 cells per dish on 22-mm glass coverslips, and cultured in 2.5 ml of DME supplemented with 10% FCS and antibiotics. PH-GFP constructs (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Stauffer et al., 1998</xref>; a gift from Dr. Kees Jalink, The Netherlands Cancer Institute, Amsterdam, Netherlands) were transfected for 3 h using LipofectAMINE&#x02122; at 1 &#x003bc;g DNA/dish. After transfection, cells were incubated in DME containing 0.5% FBS and 1% DMSO for 36&#x02013;48 h.</p></sec><sec><title>Confocal microscopy and image analysis</title><p>For confocal imaging, culture dishes with coverslips were mounted on an inverted confocal microscope (LSM 510; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.) equipped with a 63&#x000d7; 1.40 oil objective (Plan-Apochromat<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.). Excitation of GFP was with the 488-nm argon ion laserline, and GFP fluorescence from the PH-GFP fusion protein was recorded through an emission filter (LP505; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.). For all experiments, the pinhole size was kept the same (axial resolution of &#x0223c;1.2 &#x003bc;M). Bradykinin was added in 20-&#x003bc;l aliquots to the culture dish, so that the addition (final concentration was 1 &#x003bc;M) was nearly instantaneous, but with as little cellular disturbance as possible. For translocation studies, a series of confocal images were taken at 5-s intervals. Direct determination of the ratio of membrane to cytosolic fluorescence by post-acquisition linescan profiles across each of the cells was confounded by the shape changes of cells during experiments (see Results). Using MetaMorph<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> software (Universal Imaging Corp.), a region of interest was assigned for each cell including part of the membrane, cytosol, and background. To measure the fluorescence of the membrane section inside a region of interest, a thresholding step was used to segment the membrane region, and the average fluorescence above this threshold was measured as the membrane fluorescence. The same region of interest and threshold were then applied for each image in a series. We found this approach could resolve the problem caused by cell movements and shape changes, and let us reliably detect changes in membrane fluorescence. The cytosolic fluorescence was measured by directly assigning regions of interests for cytosol.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitation of cytosolic PH-GFP levels</title><p>The cytosolic PH-GFP concentration was determined in situ by using calibration slides containing known concentrations of purified, bacterially expressed PH-GFP (a gift from Dr. Laurinda Jaffe, University of Connecticut Health Center, Farmington, CT, and Dr. Tamas Balla, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD). The purity of PH-GFP protein was confirmed by SDS-PAGE analysis, and the stock concentration (1 &#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l) was measured by the BCA Protein Assay (Pierce Chemical Co.). Calibration slides were made by preparing various dilutions of the stock PH-GFP in EBSS, and imaging the fluorophore between two coverslips with the same parameters as used for the cellular PH-GFP imaging (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1998</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Computational modeling</title><p>The Virtual Cell software environment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="availableathttp://www.nrcam.uchc.edu">availableathttp://www.nrcam.uchc.edu</ext-link>) was used to develop a model of PIP<sub>2</sub> turnover. The mathematical details of the model are provided in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> and the . The model may be accessed and copied by logging in to the Virtual Cell and opening the &#x0201c;published&#x0201d; model called &#x0201c;PIP<sub>2</sub> hydrolysis.&#x0201d; This will permit visualization of the time course and/or spatial distribution of all the variables in the model including those that were not presented in this paper. A set of instructions for downloading the model in either an XML-compliant format or as in the VCMDL format is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nrcam.uchc.edu/applications.html">http://www.nrcam.uchc.edu/applications.html</ext-link>.</p><p>
<table-wrap id="tbl2" position="anchor"><label>Table</label><caption><p>AI. <bold>Parameter values for the simulation in</bold>
<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Parameter</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">Value</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">Comments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">IP<sub>3</sub>_basal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.16 &#x003bc;M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al., 1999a</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">IP<sub>3</sub>_Diff</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">283 &#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>/s</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allbritton et al., 1992</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">KfPLCact</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">5.0E-4 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Best fit to <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PIP<sub>2</sub>_basal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">4,000.0 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Measured</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PIP<sub>2</sub>syndecay, PIPsyndecay, stimdecay</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2,857.0 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Best fit to <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> and appropriate for required rate<break/>of InsP<sub>3</sub> production</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PIP_basal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">1.0 s</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Measured</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PI_PM_init</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">142,857.0 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Measured</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PLC_PM_init</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">100.0 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Best fit to <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> (dependent on kfPLCact)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PLC_act_PM_init</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.0 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Basal activity is implicit in maintenance of basal InsP<sub>3</sub>
<break/>of 0.16 &#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">SurfToVol_NM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">1.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Spherical nucleus of radius 3 &#x003bc;m</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">SurfToVol_PM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Calculated for a hemispherical cell of radius 9 &#x003bc;m;<break/>the N1E-115 neuroblastoma cells are often significantly larger, but their many processes and convoluted membrane makes this a good estimate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">kBasalSynPIP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.0055 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Chosen to maintain near-constant supply of PIP</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">kBasalSynPIP<sub>2</sub>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.048 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Chosen to reproduce recovery phase of PIP<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">kIP<sub>3</sub>deg</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.08 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Based on value of 0.16 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at 37&#x000b0;C from <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fink et al. (1999a)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">kStimSynPIP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.019 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Fit to experimental data in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">kStimSynPIP<sub>2</sub>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.92 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Fit to experimental data in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">k_PIP2hyd</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2.4 (s&#x000b7;molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Appropriate for required rate of InsP<sub>3</sub> production</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">krPLCact</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.1 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Appropriate for required rate of InsP<sub>3</sub> production</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">tau0, tauPIP<sub>2</sub>syn, tauPIPsyn</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">0.05 s</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Stimulation introduced at 50 ms</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>
<table-wrap id="tbl3" position="anchor"><label>Table</label><caption><p>AII. <bold>Additional parameters for model of PH-GFP translocation</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Parameter</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">Value</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">Comments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">KdPIP<sub>2</sub>PH</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2.0 &#x003bc;M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">KdIP<sub>3</sub>PH</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.1 &#x003bc;M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PH_GFP_Cyt_init</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2.31 &#x003bc;M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Calculated from measured total PH-GFP of 6 &#x003bc;M, basal InsP<sub>3</sub> of 0.16 &#x003bc;M, and literature value of KdIP<sub>3</sub>PH of 0.1 &#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">IP<sub>3</sub>_PHGFP_Cyt_init</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">3.70 &#x003bc;M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Calculated from measured total PH-GFP of 6 &#x003bc;M, basal InsP<sub>3</sub> of 0.16 &#x003bc;M, and literature value of KdIP<sub>3</sub>PH of 0.1 &#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PHGFP_Diff</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">50 &#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>/s</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Diffusion coefficient estimated from molecular weight</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">IP<sub>3</sub>_PHGFP_Diff</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">50 &#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>/s</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Diffusion coefficient estimated from molecular weight</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PIP<sub>2</sub>_PHGFP_PM_init</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">4,617.4 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Calculated from measured total PH_GFP_Cyt_init of 2.30769 &#x003bc;M, basal PIP<sub>2</sub> of 4,000 molecules/&#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>, and literature value of KdPIP<sub>2</sub>PH of 2 &#x003bc;M (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hirose et al., 1999</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">kf_IP<sub>3</sub>PH</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">10.0 (&#x003bc;M&#x000b7;s)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Near diffusion controlled</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">kf_PIP<sub>2</sub>PH</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">0.12 (&#x003bc;M&#x000b7;s)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">van der Wal et al., 2001</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr. Kees Jalink and Dr. Laurinda Jaffe for supplying samples of probes. We are also pleased to acknowledge Jim Schaff, Ion Moraru, and Boris Slepchenko for providing advice and help in various aspects of this research.</p><p>We are grateful for the support of the National Institute of General Medical Science through grant no. GM35063 (to L.M. Loew), the National Center for Research Resource through grant no. RR13186 (to L.M. Loew), and the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke through grant no. NS40158 (to J. Watras).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>*</label><p>Abbreviations used in this paper: GTP&#x003b3;S, guanosine 5&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-(3-thiotriphosphate); InsP<sub>3</sub>, inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate; PH, pleckstrin homology; PI, phosphatidylinositol; PIP<sub>2</sub>, phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Agranoff, B.W., P. Murthy, and E.B. Seguin. <year>1983</year>. Thrombin-induced phosphodiesteratic cleavage of phosphatidylinositol bisphosphate in human platelets. <source>J. Biol. Chem</source>. <volume>258</volume>:<fpage>2076</fpage>&#x02013;2078.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6296123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Allbritton, N.L., T. Meyer, and L. Stryer. <year>1992</year>. Range of messenger action of calcium ion and inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>258</volume>:<fpage>1812</fpage>&#x02013;1815.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1465619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Balla, T., T. Bondeva, and P. Varnai. <year>2000</year>. How accurately can we image inositol lipids in living cells? <source>Trends Pharmacol. Sci.</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;241.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10871889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Berridge, M.J. <year>1993</year>. Cell signalling. A tale of two messengers. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>365</volume>:<fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;389.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8413581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Berridge, M.J., and R.F. Irvine. <year>1984</year>. Inositol trisphosphate, a novel second messenger in cellular signal transduction. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>312</volume>:<fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;321.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6095092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carney, D.H., D.L. Scott, E.A. Gordon, and E.F. LaBelle. <year>1985</year>. Phosphoinositides in mitogenesis: neomycin inhibits thrombin-stimulated phosphoinositide turnover and initiation of cell proliferation. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;488.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2992800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chahwala, S.B., L.F. Fleischman, and L. Cantley. <year>1987</year>. Kinetic analysis of guanosine 5&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-(3-thiotriphosphate) effects on phosphatidylinositol turnover in NRK cell homogenates. <source>Biochemistry.</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>612</fpage>&#x02013;622.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3548823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ciapa, B., B. Borg, and M. Whitaker. <year>1992</year>. Polyphosphoinositide metabolism during the fertilization wave in sea urchin eggs. <source>Development.</source>
<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;195.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1322270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Coggan, J.S., and S.H. Thompson. <year>1995</year>. Intracellular calcium signals in response to bradykinin in individual neuroblastoma cells. <source>Am. J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>C841</fpage>&#x02013;C848.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7485451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Coggan, J.S., and S.H. Thompson. <year>1997</year>. Cholinergic modulation of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> response to bradykinin in neuroblastoma cells. <source>Am. J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>273</volume>:<fpage>C612&#x02212;C617</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9277358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Czech, M.P. <year>2000</year>. PIP2 and PIP3: complex roles at the cell surface. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>603</fpage>&#x02013;606.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10761925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Downing, G.J., S. Kim, S. Nakanishi, K.J. Catt, and T. Balla. <year>1996</year>. Characterization of a soluble adrenal phosphatidylinositol 4-kinase reveals wortmannin sensitivity of type III phosphatidylinositol kinases. <source>Biochemistry.</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>3587</fpage>&#x02013;3594.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8639510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ferguson, K.M., M.A. Lemmon, J. Schlessinger, and P.B. Sigler. <year>1995</year>. Structure of the high affinity complex of inositol trisphosphate with a phospholipase C pleckstrin homology domain. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>1037</fpage>&#x02013;1046.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8521504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fink, C., F. Morgan, and L.M. Loew. <year>1998</year>. Intracellular fluorescent probe concentrations by confocal microscopy. <source>Biophys. J</source>. <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>1648</fpage>&#x02013;1658.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9746507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fink, C.C., B. Slepchenko, I.I. Moraru, J. Schaff, J. Watras, and L.M. Loew. <year>1999</year>a. Morphological control of inositol-1,4,5-trisphosphate-dependent signals. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>929</fpage>&#x02013;936.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10579714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fink, C.C., B. Slepchenko, and L.M. Loew. <year>1999</year>b. Determination of time-dependent inositol-1,4,5-trisphosphate concentrations during calcium release in a smooth muscle cell. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;628.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fink, C.C., B. Slepchenko, I.I. Moraru, J. Watras, J.C. Schaff, and L.M. Loew. <year>2000</year>. An image-based model of calcium waves in differentiated neuroblastoma cells. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;183.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10866945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gonzalez-Sastre, F., and J. Folch-Pi. <year>1968</year>. Thin-layer chromatography of the phosphoinositides. <source>J. Lipid Res.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>532</fpage>&#x02013;533.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4302257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Halet, G., R. Tunwell, T. Balla, K. Swann, and J. Carroll. <year>2002</year>. The dynamics of plasma membrane PtdIns(4,5)P(2) at fertilization of mouse eggs. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>2139</fpage>&#x02013;2149.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11973355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Higashida, H., and D.A. Brown. <year>1987</year>. Bradykinin inhibits potassium (M) currents in N1E-115 neuroblastoma cells. Responses resemble those in NG108-15 neuroblastoma x glioma hybrid cells. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>220</volume>:<fpage>302</fpage>&#x02013;306.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2440728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hilgemann, D.W., S. Feng, and C. Nasuhoglu. 2001. The complex and intriguing lives of PIP2 with ion channels and transporters. <italic>Sci. STKE.</italic> 2001:RE19.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hirose, K., S. Kadowaki, M. Tanabe, H. Takeshima, and M. Iino. <year>1999</year>. Spatiotemporal dynamics of inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate that underlies complex Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization patterns. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>284</volume>:<fpage>1527</fpage>&#x02013;1530.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10348740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Holz, R.W., M.D. Hlubek, S.D. Sorensen, S.K. Fisher, T. Balla, S. Ozaki, G.D. Prestwich, E.L. Stuenkel, and M.A. Bittner. <year>2000</year>. A pleckstrin homology domain specific for phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PtdIns-4,5-P2) and fused to green fluorescent protein identifies plasma membrane PtdIns-4,5-P2 as being important in exocytosis. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>17878</fpage>&#x02013;17885.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Huijbregts, R.P., L. Topalof, and V.A. Bankaitis. <year>2000</year>. Lipid metabolism and regulation of membrane trafficking. <source>Traffic.</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;202.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11208102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jain, M.K. 1980. Membrane components: isolation, composition, and metabolism. Introduction to Biological Membranes. M.K. Jain and R.C. Wagner, editors. John Wiley and Sons, Inc., New York. 25&#x02013;52.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kaya, H., G.M. Patton, and S.L. Hong. <year>1989</year>. Bradykinin-induced activation of phospholipase A2 is independent of the activation of polyphosphoinositide-hydrolyzing phospholipase C. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>264</volume>:<fpage>4972</fpage>&#x02013;4977.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2538467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kavran, J.M., D.E. Klein, A. Lee, M. Falasca, S.J. Isakoff, E.Y. Skolnik, and M.A. Lemmon. <year>1998</year>. Specificity and promiscuity in phosphoinositide binding by pleckstrin homology domains. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>273</volume>:<fpage>30497</fpage>&#x02013;30508.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9804818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kiss, Z., and T. Farkas. <year>1975</year>. The effect of isoproterenol on the metabolism of phosphatidylinositol by rat heart in vitro. <source>Biochem. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>999</fpage>&#x02013;1002.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">168904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lange, Y., M.H. Swaisgood, B.V. Ramos, and T.L. Steck. <year>1989</year>. Plasma membranes contain half the phospholipid and 90% of the cholesterol and sphingomyelin in cultured human fibroblasts. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>264</volume>:<fpage>3786</fpage>&#x02013;3793.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2917977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lassing, I., and U. Lindberg. <year>1990</year>. Polyphosphoinositide synthesis in platelets stimulated with low concentrations of thrombin is enhanced before the activation of phospholipase C. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>262</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;233.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2159414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lemmon, M.A., K.M. Ferguson, R. O'Brien, P.B. Sigler, and J. Schlessinger. <year>1995</year>. Specific and high-affinity binding of inositol phosphates to an isolated pleckstrin homology domain. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>10472</fpage>&#x02013;10476.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7479822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Loew, L.M., and J.C. Schaff. <year>2001</year>. The Virtual Cell: A software environment for computational cell biology. <source>Trends Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;406.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11587765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lukacova, N., and J. Marsala. <year>1997</year>. Regional distribution of phospholipids and polyphosphatidyl inositides in the rabbit's spinal cord. <source>Neurochem. Res.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>687</fpage>&#x02013;692.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9178951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Manifava, M., J.W. Thuring, Z.Y. Lim, L. Packman, A.B. Holmes, and N.T. Ktistakis. <year>2001</year>. Differential binding of traffic-related proteins to phosphatidic acid- or phosphatidylinositol (4,5)-bisphosphate-coupled affinity reagents. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>8987</fpage>&#x02013;8994.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11124268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martin, T.F. <year>2001</year>. PI(4,5)P(2) regulation of surface membrane traffic. <source>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>&#x02013;499.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11454457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McLaughlin, S., N. Mulrine, T. Gresalfi, G. Vaio, and A. McLaughlin. <year>1981</year>. Adsorption of divalent cations to bilayer membranes containing phosphatidylserine. <source>J. Gen. Physiol</source>. <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>&#x02013;473.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7241089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McLaughlin, S., J. Wang, A. Gambhir, and D. Murray. <year>2002</year>. PIP(2) and proteins: interactions, organization, and information flow. <source>Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struct.</source>
<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;175.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mitchell, C.A., S. Brown, J.K. Campbell, A.D. Munday, and C.J. Speed. <year>1996</year>. Regulation of second messengers by the inositol polyphosphate 5-phosphatases. <source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>994</fpage>&#x02013;1000.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8968499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mitchell, R.H., C.J. Kirk, L.M. Jones, C.P. Downes, and J.A. Creba. <year>1981</year>. The stimulation of inositol lipid metabolism that accompanies calcium mobilization in stimulated cells: defined characteristics and unanswered questions. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci.</source>
<volume>296</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;138.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6121338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nakanishi, S., K.J. Catt, and T. Balla. <year>1995</year>. A wortmannin-sensitive phosphatidylinositol 4-kinase that regulates hormone-sensitive pools of inositolphospholipids. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>5317</fpage>&#x02013;5321.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7777504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nash, M.S., K.W. Young, G.B. Willars, R.A. Challiss, and S.R. Nahorski. <year>2001</year>. Single-cell imaging of graded Ins(1,4,5)P3 production following G-protein-coupled-receptor activation. <source>Biochem. J</source>. <volume>356</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;142.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11336645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nebl, T., S.W. Oh, and E.J. Luna. <year>2000</year>. Membrane cytoskeleton: PIP(2) pulls the strings. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>R351</fpage>&#x02013;R354.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10801429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nemoto, Y., M. Arribas, C. Haffner, and P. DeCamilli. <year>1997</year>. Synaptojanin 2, a novel synaptojanin isoform with a distinct targeting domain and expression pattern. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>272</volume>:<fpage>30817</fpage>&#x02013;30821.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9388224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Okubo, Y., S. Kakizawa, K. Hirose, and M. Iino. <year>2001</year>. Visualization of InsP(3) dynamics reveals a novel AMPA receptor-triggered InsP(3) production pathway mediated by voltage-dependent Ca(2+) influx in Purkinje cells. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;122.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11604143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Quist, E.E. <year>1982</year>. Evidence for a carbachol stimulated phosphatidylinositol effect in heart. <source>Biochem. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>3130</fpage>&#x02013;3133.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7150339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Quist, E., and M. Sanchez. <year>1983</year>. Alpha adrenergic drugs induce a phospholipid effect in canine heart. <source>Proc. West. Pharmacol. Soc.</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;335.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6136982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Payrastre, B., K. Missy, S. Giuriato, S. Bodin, M. Plantavid, and M. Gratacap. <year>2001</year>. Phosphoinositides: key players in cell signalling, in time and space. <source>Cell. Signal.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;387.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11384836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Racagni, G., M. Garcia de Lema, C.E. Domenech, and E.E. Machado de Domenech. <year>1992</year>. Phospholipids in <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>: phosphoinositide composition and turnover. <source>Lipids.</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;278.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1325592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rameh, L.E., K.F. Tolias, B.C. Duckworth, and L.C. Cantley. <year>1997</year>. A new pathway for synthesis of phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>390</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>&#x02013;196.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9367159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rebecchi, M., A. Peterson, and S. McLaughlin. <year>1992</year>. Phosphoinositide-specific phospholipase C-delta 1 binds with high affinity to phospholipid vesicles containing phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate. <source>Biochemistry.</source>
<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>12742</fpage>&#x02013;12747.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1334429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rozelle, A.L., L.M. Machesky, M. Yamamoto, M.H. Driessens, R.H. Insall, M.G. Roth, K. Luby-Phelps, G. Marriott, A. Hall, and H.L. Yin. <year>2000</year>. Phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate induces actin-based movement of raft-enriched vesicles through WASP-Arp2/3. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;320.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10744973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sakisaka, T., T. Itoh, K. Miura, and T. Takenawa. <year>1997</year>. Phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate phosphatase regulates the rearrangement of actin filaments. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>3841</fpage>&#x02013;3849.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9199318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schaff, J., C.C. Fink, B. Slepchenko, J.H. Carson, and L.M. Loew. <year>1997</year>. A general computational framework for modeling cellular structure and function. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1135</fpage>&#x02013;1146.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9284281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schaff, J.C., B.M. Slepchenko, Y. Choi, J.M. Wagner, D. Resasco, and L.M. Loew. <year>2001</year>. Analysis of non-linear dynamics on arbitrary geometries with the Virtual Cell. <source>Chaos.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;131.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12779447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sechi, A.S., and J. Wehland. <year>2000</year>. The actin cytoskeleton and plasma membrane connection: PtdIns(4,5)P(2) influences cytoskeletal protein activity at the plasma membrane. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>3685</fpage>&#x02013;3695.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sekar, M.C., and B.D. Roufogalis. <year>1984</year>. Comparison of muscarinic and alpha-adrenergic receptors in rat atria based on phosphoinositide turnover. <source>Life Sci.</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1527</fpage>&#x02013;1533.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6090840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Slepchenko, B.M., J.C. Schaff, J.H. Carson, and L.M. Loew. <year>2002</year>. Computational cell biology: spatiotemporal simulation of cellular events. <source>Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struct.</source>
<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;441.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Snow, P., D.L. Yim, J.D. Leibow, S. Saini, and R. Nuccitelli. <year>1996</year>. Fertilization stimulates an increase in inositol trisphosphate and inositol lipid levels in Xenopus eggs. <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;118.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8948578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stauffer, T.P., S. Ahn, and T. Meyer. <year>1998</year>. Receptor-induced transient reduction in plasma membrane PtdIns(4,5)P2 concentration monitored in living cells. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;346.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9512420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stefan, C.J., A. Audhya, and S.D. Emr. <year>2002</year>. The yeast synaptojanin-like proteins control the cellular distribution of phosphatidylinositol (4,5)-bisphosphate. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>542</fpage>&#x02013;557.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11854411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stith, B.J., M. Goalstone, S. Silva, and C. Jaynes. <year>1993</year>. Inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate mass changes from fertilization through first cleavage in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;443.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8507898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stith, B.J., R. Espinoza, D. Roberts, and T. Smart. <year>1994</year>. Sperm increase inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate mass in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> eggs preinjected with calcium buffers or heparin. <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>165</volume>:<fpage>206</fpage>&#x02013;215.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8088439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Suh, B.C., and B. Hille. <year>2002</year>. Recovery from muscarinic modulation of M current channels requires phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate synthesis. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;520.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12165472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Takenawa, T., T. Itoh, and K. Fukami. <year>1999</year>. Regulation of phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate levels and its roles in cytoskeletal re-organization and malignant transformation. <source>Chem. Phys. Lipids</source>. <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;22.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10358924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tolias, K.F., and L.C. Cantley. <year>1999</year>. Pathways for phosphoinositide synthesis. <source>Chem. Phys. Lipids.</source>
<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;77.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10358929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Toker, A. <year>1998</year>. The synthesis and cellular roles of phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate. <source>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>254</fpage>&#x02013;261.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9561850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Turner, P.R., M.P. Sheetz, and L.A. Jaffe. <year>1984</year>. Fertilization increases the polyphosphoinositide content of sea urchin eggs. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>310</volume>:<fpage>414</fpage>&#x02013;415.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6087155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van der Wal, J., R. Habets, P. Varnai, T. Balla, and K. Jalink. <year>2001</year>. Monitoring agonist-induced phospholipase C activation in live cells by fluorescence resonance energy transfer. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>15337</fpage>&#x02013;15344.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van Rheenen, J., and K. Jalink. <year>2002</year>. Agonist-induced PIP(2) hydrolysis inhibits cortical actin dynamics: regulation at a global but not at a micrometer scale. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>3257</fpage>&#x02013;3267.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12221130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vanhaesebroeck, B., S.J. Leevers, K. Ahmadi, J. Timms, R. Katso, P.C. Driscoll, R. Woscholski, P.J. Parker, and M.D. Waterfield. <year>2001</year>. Synthesis and function of 3-phosphorylated inositol lipids. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>&#x02013;602.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11395417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Varnai, P., and T. Balla. <year>1998</year>. Visualization of phosphoinositides that bind pleckstrin homology domains: calcium- and agonist-induced dynamic changes and relationship to myo-[<sup>3</sup>H]inositol-labeled phosphoinositide pools. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>143</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>&#x02013;510.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9786958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Varnai, P., X. Lin, S.B. Lee, G. Tuymetova, T. Bondeva, A. Spat, S.G. Rhee, G. Hajnoczky, and T. Balla. <year>2002</year>. Inositol lipid binding and membrane localization of isolated pleckstrin homology (PH) domains. Studies on the PH domains of phospholipase C delta 1 and p130. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>27412</fpage>&#x02013;27422.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12019260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Warnock, D.E., C. Roberts, M.S. Lutz, W.A. Blackburn, W.W. Young, Jr., and J.U. Baenziger. <year>1993</year>. Determination of plasma membrane lipid mass and composition in cultured Chinese hamster ovary cells using high gradient magnetic affinity chromatography. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>268</volume>:<fpage>10145</fpage>&#x02013;10153.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8387513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Watt, S.A., G. Kular, I.N. Fleming, C.P. Downes, and J.M. Lucocq. <year>2002</year>. Subcellular localization of phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate using the pleckstrin homology domain of phospholipase C delta1. <source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>363</volume>:<fpage>657</fpage>&#x02013;666.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11964166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Willars, G.B., S.R. Nahorski, and R.A.J. Challiss. <year>1998</year>. Differential regulation of muscarinic acetylcholine receptor-sensitive polyphosphoinositide pools and consequences for signaling in human neuroblastoma cells. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>273</volume>:<fpage>5037</fpage>&#x02013;5046.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9478953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Xu, C., and L.M. Loew. <year>2003</year> Activation of phospholipase C increases intramembrane electric fields in N1E-115 neuroblastoma cells. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>In press</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yorek, M.A., J.A. Dunlap, M.R. Stefani, E.P. Davidson, X. Zhu, and J. Eichberg. <year>1994</year>. Decreased myo-inositol uptake is associated with reduced bradykinin-stimulated phosphatidylinositol synthesis and diacylglycerol content in cultured neuroblastoma cells exposed to L-fucose. <source>J. Neurochem.</source>
<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;158.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8263514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhang, H., L.C. Craciun, T. Mirshahi, T. Rohacs, C.M. Lopes, T. Jin, and D.E. Logothetis. <year>2003</year>. PIP(2) activates KCNQ channels, and its hydrolysis underlies receptor-mediated inhibition of M currents. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>963</fpage>&#x02013;975.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12670425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><app-group><app id="app1"><title>Appendix</title><sec><title>Model equations and parameters</title><p>The reactions labeled in red in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> are governed by the rates as follows: Brackets, [], surround molecular species that are variables in the model. Plasma membrane species are designated by PM suffixes, and cytosolic species with Cyt suffixes.</p><p>PIPsyn: (Ratebasal_PIPsyn + Ratestim_PIPsyn) * [PI_PM]</p><p>Ratestim_PIPsyn = kStimSynPIP * exp(&#x02212;((t &#x02212; tauPIPsyn)/PIPsyndecay)) * (t &#x0003e; tauPIPsyn)</p><p>Ratebasal_PIPsyn = (kBasalSynPIP * 0.581 * (&#x02212;1.0 + exp(((PIP_init &#x02212; [PIP_PM])/PIP_init)))) * ([PIP_PM] &#x0003c; PIP_init)</p><p>PIP<sub>2</sub>syn: (Rate_PIP<sub>2</sub>Synbasal + Rate_PIP<sub>2</sub>SynStim) * [PIP_PM]</p><p>Rate_PIP<sub>2</sub>SynStim = kStimSynPIP<sub>2</sub> * exp(&#x02212;((t &#x02212; tauPIP<sub>2</sub>syn)/PIP<sub>2</sub>syndecay)) * (t &#x0003e; tauPIP<sub>2</sub>syn)</p><p>Rate_PIP<sub>2</sub>Synbasal = (kBasalSynPIP<sub>2</sub> * 0.581 * (&#x02212;1.0 + exp(((PIP<sub>2</sub>_basal &#x02013; [PIP2_PM])/PIP<sub>2</sub>_basal)))) * ([PIP<sub>2</sub>_PM] &#x0003c; PIP<sub>2</sub>_basal)</p><p>PLCact: (kfPLCact * ([PLC_PM] * signal)) &#x02212; (krPLCact * [PLC_act_PM])</p><p>Signal = (t &#x0003e; tau0) * exp(&#x02212;((t &#x02212; tau0)/stimdecay))</p><p>PIP<sub>2</sub>_hyd: k_PIP<sub>2</sub>hyd * [PIP<sub>2</sub>_PM] * [PLC_act_PM]</p><p>PIP<sub>2</sub>_PH: (kf_PIP<sub>2</sub>PH * [PH_GFP_Cyt] * [PIP<sub>2</sub>_PM]) &#x02212; (kf_PIP<sub>2</sub>PH * Kd_PIP<sub>2</sub>PH * [PIP<sub>2</sub>_PHGFP_PM])</p><p>IP<sub>3</sub>_PHGFP: (kf_IP<sub>3</sub>PH * [PH_GFP_Cyt] * [IP<sub>3</sub>_Cyt]) &#x02212; (kf_IP<sub>3</sub>PH * KdIP<sub>3</sub>PH * [IP<sub>3</sub>_PHGFP_Cyt])</p><p>IP<sub>3</sub>deg: kIP<sub>3</sub>deg * ([IP<sub>3</sub>_Cyt] &#x02212; IP<sub>3</sub>_basal)</p><p>IP<sub>3</sub>_uncaging: intensity * [IP<sub>3</sub>X_Cyt] * [hv_Cyt]</p><p>The rate of change of any molecular species is given by the sum of all the individual reaction rates that produce it minus all the rates that degrade it. For a spatial model, diffusion of molecules in the cytosol also has to be to be taken into account. For example, the partial differential equation governing the temporal and spatial variation of InsP<sub>3</sub> is: <disp-formula><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{gather*}\frac{{\mathrm{{\partial}}} \left \left[IP3\right] \right }{{\mathrm{{\partial}}}t}=IP3\_Diff{\cdot}{\mathrm{{\bigtriangledown}}}^{2} \left \left[ \left \left[IP3\right] \right  \right +PIP2\_hyd 
\\
-IP3\_PHGFP-IP3deg\end{gather*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>For compartmental (i.e., nonspatial) models, diffusion is considered to be instantaneous on the time scale of interest, and the equations reduce to a set of ordinary differential equations containing just the reaction rates with appropriate adjustments for the surface-to-volume ratio of the plasma membrane to the cytosol (SurfToVol_PM). Both spatial and compartmental models for the pathways in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> were developed in this work. The set of ordinary differential equations generated for the compartmental models were solved numerically using the LSODA stiff solver (variable time step) available within the Virtual Cell. Spatial models were solved with the finite volume method using a time step of 1 ms and a two-dimensional spatial mesh of 116 &#x000d7; 172 elements (x,y), each with dimensions of 0.42 &#x000d7; 0.42 &#x003bc;m. A fourfold correction for the lower surface-to-volume ratio of the two-dimensional geometry compared with the actual three-dimensional geometry of the cell was also included in the model. The model and all the simulation results may be examined by logging into the Virtual Cell at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nrcam.uchc.edu">http://www.nrcam.uchc.edu</ext-link>; the model is named &#x0201c;PIP<sub>2</sub> Hydrolysis&#x0201d; and can be accessed by unchecking &#x0201c;Private only&#x0201d; under the &#x0201c;View menu.&#x0201d; By copying the model into a new workspace, the reader may modify the model by changing parameters or adding new model components.</p></sec></app></app-group></back></article>