<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Syst Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Syst. Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Systems Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1744-4292</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16729048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1681447</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">msb4100018</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb4100018</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Extension of a genetic network model by iterative experimentation and mathematical analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>James C W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>Megan M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kozma-Bogn&#x000e1;r</surname><given-names>L&#x000e1;szl&#x000f3;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>Victoria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Paul E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>Matthew S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>Andrew J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label>
<institution>Department of Biological Sciences, University of Warwick</institution>, Coventry, <country>UK</country>
</aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label>
<institution>Department of Physics, University of Warwick</institution>, Coventry, <country>UK</country>
</aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label>
<institution>Interdisciplinary Programme for Cellular Regulation, University of Warwick</institution>, Coventry, <country>UK</country>
</aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label>
Present address: <institution>Institute of Molecular Plant Sciences, University of Edinburgh</institution>, Rutherford Building, Mayfield Road, Edinburgh
EH9 3JH, <country>UK</country>
</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label>
Institute of Molecular Plant Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Rutherford Building, Mayfield Road, Edinburgh EH9 3JH, UK. Tel.: +44 1316513325; Fax: +44 1316505392; E-mail: <email>andrew.millar@ed.ac.uk</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>06</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>2005.0013</fpage><lpage>2005.0013</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>04</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>06</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005, EMBO and Nature Publishing Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>EMBO and Nature Publishing Group</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract abstract-type="hidden-highlights"><p>
<list id="l1" list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>We extend the current model of the plant circadian clock, in order to accommodate new and published data. Throughout our model development we use a global parameter search to ensure that any limitations we find are due to the network architecture and not to our selection of the parameter values, which have not been determined experimentally. Our final model includes two, interlocked loops of gene regulation and is reminiscent of the circuit structures previously identified by experiments on insect and fungal clocks. It is the first Arabidopsis clock model to show such good correspondence to experimental data.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Our interlocked feedback loop model predicts the regulation of two unknown components. Experiments motivated by these predictions identify the GIGANTEA gene as a strong candidate for one component, with an unexpected pattern of light regulation.*</p></list-item></list>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"/>
</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="hidden-synopsis"><p>This study involves an iterative approach of mathematical modelling and experiment to develop an accurate mathematical model of the circadian clock in the higher plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. Our approach is central to systems biology and should lead to a greater, quantitative understanding of the circadian clock, as well as being more widely relevant to research into genetic networks.</p><p>The day&#x02013;night cycle caused by the Earth's rotation affects most organisms, and has resulted in the evolution of the circadian clock. The circadian clock controls 24-h rhythms in processes from metabolism to behaviour; in higher eukaryotes, the circadian clock controls the rhythmic expression of 5&#x02013;10&#x00025; of genes. In plants, the clock controls leaf and petal movements, the opening and closing of stomatal pores, the discharge of floral fragrances and many metabolic activities, especially those associated with photosynthesis.</p><p>The relatively small number of components involved in the central circadian network makes it an ideal candidate for mathematical modelling of complex biological regulation. Genetic studies in a variety of model organisms have shown that the circadian rhythm is generated by a central network of between 6 and 12 genes. These genes form feedback loops generating a rhythm in mRNA production. One negative feedback loop in which a gene encodes a protein that, after several hours, turns off transcription is, in principle, capable of creating a circadian rhythm. However, real circadian clocks have proven to be more complicated than this, with interlocked feedback loops. Networks of this complexity are more easily understood through mathematical modelling.</p><p>The clock mechanism in the model plant, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, was first proposed to comprise a feedback loop in which two partially redundant genes, <italic>LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL</italic> (<italic>LHY</italic>) and <italic>CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED 1</italic> (<italic>CCA1</italic>), repress the expression of their activator, <italic>TIMING OF CAB EXPRESSION 1</italic> (<italic>TOC1</italic>). We previously modelled this preliminary network and showed that it was not capable of recreating several important pieces of experimental data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>). Here, we extend the LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1 network in new mathematical models. To check the effects of each addition to the network, the outputs of the extended models are compared to published data and to new experiments.</p><p>As is the case for most biological networks, the parameter values in our model, such as the translation rate of TOC1 protein, are unknown. We employ here an optimisation method, which works well with noisy and varied data and allows a global search of parameter space. This should ensure that the limitations we find in our networks are due to the network structure, and not to our parameter choices.</p><p>Our final interlocked feedback loop model requires two hypothetical components, genes <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>), but is the first <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> clock model to exhibit such a good correspondence with experimental data. The model simulates a residual short-period oscillation in the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> mutant, as characterised by our experiments. No single-loop model is able to do this. Our model also matches experimental data under constant light (LL) conditions and correctly senses photoperiod. The model predicts an interlocked feedback loop structure similar to that seen in the circadian clock mechanisms of other organisms.</p><p>The interlocked feedback loop model predicts a distinctive pattern of <italic>Y</italic> mRNA accumulation in the wild type (WT) and in the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant, with <italic>Y</italic> mRNA levels increasing transiently at dawn. We designed an experiment to identify <italic>Y</italic> based on this prediction. <italic>GIGANTEA</italic> (<italic>GI</italic>) mRNA levels fit very well to our predicted profile for <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>), identifying <italic>GI</italic> as a strong candidate for <italic>Y</italic>.</p><p>The approach described here could act as a template for experimental biologists seeking to extend models of small genetic networks. Our results illustrate the usefulness of mathematical modelling in guiding experiments, even if the models are based on limited data. Our method provides a way of identifying suitable candidate networks and quantifying how these networks better describe a wide variety of experimental measurements. The characteristics of new putative genes are thereby obtained, facilitating the experimental search for new components. To facilitate future experimental design, we provide user-friendly software that is specifically designed for numerical simulation of circadian experiments using models for several species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Brown, 2004b</xref>).</p><p>
<bold>*Footnote: </bold>Synopsis highlights were added on 5 July 2005.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Circadian clocks involve feedback loops that generate rhythmic expression of key genes. Molecular genetic studies in the higher plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> have revealed a complex clock network. The first part of the network to be identified, a transcriptional feedback loop comprising <italic>TIMING OF CAB EXPRESSION 1 (TOC1)</italic>, <italic>LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL</italic> (<italic>LHY</italic>) and <italic>CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED 1</italic> (<italic>CCA1</italic>), fails to account for significant experimental data. We develop an extended model that is based upon a wider range of data and accurately predicts additional experimental results. The model comprises interlocking feedback loops comparable to those identified experimentally in other circadian systems. We propose that each loop receives input signals from light, and that each loop includes a hypothetical component that had not been explicitly identified. Analysis of the model predicted the properties of these components, including an acute light induction at dawn that is rapidly repressed by LHY and CCA1. We found this unexpected regulation in RNA levels of the evening-expressed gene <italic>GIGANTEA</italic> (<italic>GI</italic>), supporting our proposed network and making <italic>GI</italic> a strong candidate for this component.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>biological rhythms</kwd><kwd>gene network</kwd><kwd>mathematical modelling</kwd><kwd>parameter estimation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>A circadian system that generates biological rhythms with a period of approximately 24 h is found in organisms ranging from cyanobacteria to mammals. The system is capable of sustained oscillations under constant environmental conditions and maintains synchrony with the environment by entraining to rhythmic cues of the day/night cycle, especially input signals from light. Circadian rhythms allow diverse biological processes to occur at times in the day/night cycle (phases) that confer a selective advantage: it might be important, for example, that a particular process occurs in anticipation of a light/dark transition. The molecular mechanism of the circadian clock has been studied in several model organisms. A shared feature of these systems appears to be that the rhythms are generated by the interactions of rhythmically expressed genes that form positive and negative feedback loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Dunlap, 1999</xref>).</p><p>Computational models of these feedback loops have been developed for a variety of organisms including the fungus <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">Leloup et al, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">Ruoff et al, 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">2001</xref>), the fruitfly <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">Tyson et al, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">Ueda et al, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">Smolen et al, 2004</xref>) and the mouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Forger and Peskin, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">Leloup and Goldbeter, 2003</xref>). These models have shown that, within defined parameter ranges, the regulatory networks proposed from experimental data are capable of reproducing the main characteristics of circadian rhythms. Simple models indicate that a single feedback loop is sufficient to generate robust 24 h oscillations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">Leloup et al, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">Ruoff et al, 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">2001</xref>), although the experimental data show that a series of interlocked feedback loops are important for generating the observed circadian rhythms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Glossop et al, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Lee et al, 2000</xref>). It is an open question why circadian systems have evolved a more complex structure. Recent mathematical studies proposed that interlocked feedback loops increase the flexibility of regulation during evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Rand et al, 2004</xref>) and enhance precision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">Stelling et al, 2004</xref>).</p><p>In higher plants, the circadian system controls many processes, including leaf movement, photoperiodism, and photosynthesis. The first part of the clock mechanism in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to be identified was proposed to comprise a feedback loop, in which two partially redundant genes encoding similar DNA-binding proteins, <italic>LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL</italic> (<italic>LHY</italic>) and <italic>CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED 1</italic> (<italic>CCA1</italic>), repress the expression of their activator, <italic>TIMING OF CAB EXPRESSION 1</italic> (<italic>TOC1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Alabadi et al, 2001</xref>). We refer to this single loop as the <italic>LHY</italic>/<italic>CCA1</italic>&#x02013;<italic>TOC1</italic> network. Light can activate <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression, possibly by several mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">Wang and Tobin, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">Martinez-Garcia et al, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Kim et al, 2003</xref>), providing a potential pathway for light input to the clock. Several other rhythmically expressed genes have been associated with the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> circadian system (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">Eriksson and Millar, 2003</xref>). For example, <italic>EARLY FLOWERING 3</italic> (<italic>ELF3</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">McWatters et al, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Covington et al, 2001</xref>), <italic>GIGANTEA</italic> (<italic>GI</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Fowler et al, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">Park et al, 1999</xref>) and <italic>EARLY FLOWERING 4</italic> (<italic>ELF4</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Doyle et al, 2002</xref>) are genes expressed in the evening. Mutations in these genes strongly affect circadian rhythms and reduce <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> gene expression, but their functions have not been located in more detail within the <italic>LHY</italic>/<italic>CCA1</italic>&#x02013;<italic>TOC1</italic> network.</p><p>The <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> network alone did not readily account for some aspects of circadian behaviour, such as the long delay between <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription in the evening and <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> activation the following morning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Alabadi et al, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">Salome and McClung, 2004</xref>). Our previous differential equation model of the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> loop confirmed that this network failed to fit certain experimental data and quantitatively tested a range of its predicted behaviours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>). For example, we showed that the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> loop could not reproduce the short-period phenotype of plants that carry loss-of-function mutations in either <italic>LHY</italic> or <italic>CCA1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Green and Tobin, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>). The delay required for the model to fit appropriate phases of gene expression was estimated at 12 h between <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription and <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>). There is no obvious mechanism for this delay, reinforcing the suggestion that TOC1 protein may activate <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression indirectly.</p><p>Here, we extend the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> network beyond the structures inferred solely from data, in new mathematical models that we use to direct further experimentation. To check the effects of each addition to the network, the outputs of the extended models are compared to published data and to the new experiments. The biochemical parameter values required in the model are constrained by the time-series data but have not been measured directly, so we made a global search of parameter space, in contrast to previous clock models. This reduces the possibility that problems with the model are due to a particular set of parameter values, allowing us to focus on the network structure. The fit of the model to experimental data is dramatically improved by the addition of two hypothetical components, <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic>, to the model. Their properties are predicted; <italic>X</italic> remains to be identified, whereas experimental analysis shows that <italic>GI</italic> has several of the properties predicted for <italic>Y</italic>. The model suggests further experiments: we expect that iterative application of modelling and experiment will facilitate a more quantitative understanding of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> circadian clock.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Limitations of the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> network</title><p>Our previous simulations using the single-loop <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> network (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>) showed that it was possible for this network to correctly reproduce the phases of <italic>TOC1</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic> RNA accumulation in wild type (WT) under light&#x02013;dark cycle (LD) 12:12. (In this and subsequent models, we use a single gene, <italic>LHY</italic>, to represent both <italic>CCA1</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic> functions; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary text</xref>.) However, simulated <italic>TOC1</italic> RNA levels remained high until LHY protein accumulated, rather than falling after dusk as observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>). This was exaggerated by halving the <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA translation rate in the simulation (representing <italic>lhy</italic> or <italic>cca1</italic> loss-of function mutants), which incorrectly predicted a long-period phenotype. Thus, there must be another factor responsible for reducing <italic>TOC1</italic> expression, which is not modelled by this network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>).</p><p>Studies of a fluorescent protein, TOC1 fusion protein, suggest an additional limitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>). The TOC1 fusion was shown to be close to its minimum abundance before dawn under LD12:12, whereas according to the single-loop <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> network, TOC1 should be activating <italic>LHY</italic> transcription maximally at that time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>). This suggests that either the active form of TOC1 is present at a far lower concentration than bulk TOC1 protein, perhaps in a complex, or that an additional, TOC1-dependent component is the direct activator of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic>.</p><p>A third problem is that the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> network did not respond to day length (simulated gene expression profiles were identical in LD cycles with long and short photoperiods, data not shown), whereas it is clear experimentally that the clock has a later phase under longer photoperiods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Millar and Kay, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">Roden et al, 2002</xref>). This limitation occurs because light input to this network is modelled only by the activation of <italic>LHY</italic> expression at dawn, so the model is insensitive to light at the end of the photoperiod. Indeed, <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression fall to a low level before the end of a 12 h photoperiod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Kim et al, 2003</xref>), so another mechanism is required to mediate light input at the end of the day.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Model one&#x02014;the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1&#x02013;X</italic> network</title><p>We extended the single-loop <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> network by adding components that would address these limitations, as directed by the experimental data. After each addition, we tested network parameters until it became clear that the new network could not account for further experimental data. We identified optimal parameters for the most promising of the extended, single-loop models, which we term the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1&#x02013;X</italic> network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). Firstly, light activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription was included to provide light input at the end of the day and, conversely, to reduce <italic>TOC1</italic> activation immediately after lights-off. Secondly, an additional gene <italic>X</italic> was added to the network after <italic>TOC1</italic>, with nuclear X protein as the immediate activator of <italic>LHY</italic> instead of nuclear TOC1. Thirdly, as the F-box protein ZEITLUPE (ZTL) has been shown to degrade TOC1 protein more effectively during the night (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>), we added this factor into our network equations (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary text</xref>).</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref> shows the simulated expression profiles for the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1&#x02013;X</italic> network using the optimal parameter set (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). <italic>TOC1</italic> RNA levels peak at dusk in WT under LD12:12, and <italic>LHY</italic> RNA levels at dawn. The model allows <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA levels to drop before <italic>LHY</italic> levels rise, as observed in experiment. Including gene <italic>X</italic> within the model permits simulated TOC1 protein levels to fit well with the published data (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). <italic>ztl</italic> mutants were modelled by reducing the degradation rates of TOC1 protein in the cytoplasm and the nucleus by 50&#x00025;. This results in a long-period phenotype, with a period of 32 h, similar to or longer than the period of <italic>ztl</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>). A prediction of <italic>X</italic> mRNA and protein levels is also possible (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>): <italic>X</italic> mRNA peaks in the middle of the night under LD12:12 and nuclear X protein levels peak at dawn. Strong <italic>x</italic> mutants have the same predicted phenotype as the strongest phenotype of <italic>toc1</italic> loss-of-function mutants, causing arrhythmia due to the lack of <italic>LHY</italic> activation (data not shown). The pattern of <italic>X</italic> mRNA accumulation and its mutant phenotype are similar to those of characterised genes such as <italic>ELF4</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Doyle et al, 2002</xref>). However, this model still incorrectly predicts a long period in the simulated <italic>cca1</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>) and the strong, LL activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription causes several problems, for example the model becomes arrhythmic under LD cycles with long photoperiods (data not shown).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Experimental characterisation of the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant</title><p>The response of circadian phase to day length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Millar and Kay, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">Roden et al, 2002</xref>) strongly suggested that the circadian system receives at least one light input in addition to the activation of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression, yet simulations with the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1&#x02013;X</italic> network indicated that this was unlikely to be a simple light activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription. We sought more direct evidence for this light input by characterising circadian rhythms in the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double loss-of-function mutant. RNA data for <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> mutants in constant conditions show a damping, short-period oscillation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Alabadi et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>), which has been described as arrhythmia. We repeated these experiments using luciferase imaging (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). In the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> mutant, promoter activity of <italic>CCA1</italic> and of the clock output genes <italic>CCR2</italic> and <italic>CAB2</italic> showed an 18 h rhythm for at least three cycles in constant light (LL), which subsequently lost amplitude. The rhythm is more robust in LL but is also apparent in constant dark (DD) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). The double mutant retains a regulatory network capable of supporting rhythmic gene expression.</p><p>Reproducible entrainment of the double mutant by LD cycles was implicit in previous reports, suggesting that entrainment by light is still possible in the residual network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Alabadi et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). To test this more stringently, we generated a phase transition curve (PTC) for the WT and double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>). The PTC shows the response of an oscillator to a resetting stimulus and is plotted as the phase to which the oscillator is set (&#x02018;new phase'), for each phase at which the resetting stimulus is applied (&#x02018;old phase'). In WT, light pulses induced phase delays during the early subjective night and phase advances during the late subjective night, whereas relatively small phase shifts were elicited during the subjective day. The WT showed a type 1 (weak) resetting pattern with less than 6 h maximal phase shifts, in contrast to the type 0 (strong) resetting observed in a previous report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Covington et al, 2001</xref>), probably due to the lower fluence of our light stimulus. In contrast, the double mutant showed type 0 resetting: irrespective of the phase of the light stimulus, the clock was reset to a narrow phase range (circadian time (CT) 20&#x02013;23). Light input to a residual, rhythmic network remained without <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> function, leading us to add a second, light-responsive feedback loop to produce our final model.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Model two&#x02014;the interlocked feedback loop network</title><p>Removing <italic>LHY</italic> function from the single-loop models prevents any oscillation (data not shown), so none of these models can reproduce the entrainable, damped rhythms observed in <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> plants. We therefore developed an interlocked feedback loop network that is capable of oscillation in simulated <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>). A hypothetical gene <italic>Y</italic> activates <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription and TOC1 protein represses <italic>Y</italic> transcription, forming a feedback loop. The proposal that TOC1 has a negative function as well as a positive one is novel. Light input into this loop occurs via transcriptional activation of <italic>Y</italic> rather than of <italic>TOC1</italic>; there is as yet no evidence of direct light activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Makino et al, 2001</xref>). Light input to <italic>Y</italic> can both be through an acute response at dawn similar to that for <italic>LHY</italic> and as a constant activation term throughout the day. <italic>Y</italic> is also repressed by LHY, as this allowed the network to fit the WT as well as the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> experimental data. <italic>LHY</italic> therefore acts as a powerful delaying factor in the early day, when it inhibits expression of both <italic>TOC1</italic> and <italic>Y</italic>.</p><p>Optimal parameters for the interlocked feedback loop network (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>) were identified (see Computational methods). The optimised model achieved a good fit to experimental results that were specifically required by the optimisation process, showing that the proposed network is sufficient to explain these data. Simulations of the WT and <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> mutant using the optimal model fit well to RNA expression profiles in DD and LD12:12 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figures 5A and B</xref>). For the WT simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>), <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA peaks at dawn, <italic>TOC1</italic> at dusk, and the oscillations follow a stable limit cycle with a period of 26 h in DD. <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA levels under LD cycles are shown to increase at dawn. This is due to the induction of <italic>Y</italic> by light activating <italic>TOC1</italic> expression, overcoming the repression by LHY protein. The simulation of <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> gives a low-amplitude oscillation in DD with a 17 h period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>), as observed experimentally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). Under LD12:12, <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA oscillates with an early peak phase in the double mutant, &#x0223c;5 h after dawn, as specified in the optimisation. The rhythm of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression in the double mutant also shows a higher amplitude than WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>), which is observed experimentally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>) but was not specified during optimisation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figures 5C and D</xref> show similar expression profiles for simulated and observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>) <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA in the WT and <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> mutant under LD16:8 (note that normalisation of data and simulated values obscures the change in amplitude in this figure). <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA anticipates dawn in the simulation of the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant, which has not been so clearly observed in published experimental data and points to an area for future experimentation.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Analysis and validation of the interlocked feedback loop network</title><p>The interlocked feedback loop model with the optimal parameters not only fits the above data but its behaviour is also robust to parameter changes. This is widely thought to be a realistic requirement for models of biological regulation, because effective parameter values may be poorly buffered in biology. Changes in the period and amplitude of <italic>TOC1</italic> RNA oscillation under LL were examined after a 5&#x00025; increase or decrease of each parameter value in turn (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>). The resulting change in period varied from 0 to 4&#x00025;. As for previous clock models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">Smolen et al, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>), some parameters are more sensitive to change than others. The most sensitive parameters are those involved in <italic>TOC1</italic> degradation, X translation and X nuclear transport. The period and amplitude of this model are much less sensitive to parameter changes than the single-loop <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> model (data not shown), suggesting that some of the weaknesses of the single-loop model have been overcome.</p><p>Simulations using the optimal parameter set also fit well to several experimental results that were not specified in the optimisation, giving additional support for the proposed network structure. This is the first model that fits well to LL data for <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA levels. The WT period in LL is correctly shorter (25 h) than the period in DD (26 h; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>) although this effect is less than that observed experimentally. The rhythms in LL generally have a higher amplitude than in DD, as observed. The model correctly predicts the short-period phenotype of <italic>cca1</italic> and <italic>lhy</italic> single mutants in LL and DD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>), and the early phase of <italic>TOC1</italic> RNA expression in the single mutant under LD12:12 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5E</xref>). The single mutants were simulated by halving the <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA translation rate. Simulated overexpression of <italic>LHY</italic> produced arrhythmia with low levels of <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA (data not shown), as observed in plants that overexpress <italic>LHY</italic> or <italic>CCA1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">Schaffer et al, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">Wang and Tobin, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Alabadi et al, 2001</xref>). Protein levels are also well fitted: simulated LHY protein levels (data not shown) peak 1&#x02013;2 h after <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA levels, as observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Kim et al, 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5F</xref> compares simulated and measured (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>) TOC1 protein levels in WT, showing low levels at dawn in both cases. The optimal parameter set has minimised the light regulation of TOC1 degradation (&#x0003c;1&#x00025; of total TOC1 degradation), indicating that light-regulated degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>) is not required to fit these data. Simulation of <italic>ztl</italic> mutants by halving the total TOC1 degradation rate results in a 28 h period phenotype, again similar to that observed in <italic>ztl</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>). A simulated <italic>toc1</italic> mutant results in lower levels of <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA as expected from experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Alabadi et al, 2001</xref>), and simulated <italic>TOC1</italic> overexpression is predicted to increase <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA levels. The observed decrease in <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA where TOC1 is overexpressed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Makino et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Mas et al, 2003a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">Somers et al, 2004</xref>) remains paradoxical, since one would expect overexpressing an activator of LHY to cause its levels to rise.</p><p>Simulations of the WT and <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant PTCs were performed, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>. Both simulations are similar to our experimental data, with a type 1 PTC in the WT and a type 0 PTC in the double mutant. Increasing the light level in the WT simulation results in a type 0 PTC (data not shown), as previously observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Covington et al, 2001</xref>). As expected, the entrained phase of the interlocked feedback model is photoperiod responsive (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>), with simulated mRNA levels peaking later under longer photoperiods, as observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">Roden et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">Yanovsky and Kay, 2002</xref>). Light input to <italic>Y</italic> allows the network to respond to light throughout the day. This network will therefore be a good starting point for models of the photoperiod sensor involved in flowering time. The photoperiod range of entrainment is approximately from 3:16 h light for a 24 h period, and the simulations remain entrained for an approximate period range of 22&#x02013;30 h, where half the period is in light and half in dark. At the end of the ranges, entrainment produces a beat in the amplitude, although with little effect on phase. The balance of light input to <italic>LHY</italic>, <italic>Y</italic> and ZTL should now be examined in greater detail to determine how their contributions affect circadian entrainment.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>
<italic>GIGANTEA</italic> is a candidate for <italic>Y</italic>
</title><p>The interlocked feedback model predicts a distinctive pattern of <italic>Y</italic> mRNA accumulation in the WT and double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>). <italic>Y</italic> mRNA levels peak at the end of the day, but also increase transiently at dawn due to the acute light response of <italic>Y</italic> transcription. This early expression is quickly repressed by rising LHY protein levels, delaying the peak in <italic>Y</italic> mRNA level until after LHY protein is degraded at the end of the day. <italic>Y</italic> transcription is then repressed as TOC1 protein levels begin to rise during the night (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>). In the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant, however, the light activation of <italic>Y</italic> at dawn is de-repressed, resulting in a much stronger activation than in WT, and causing <italic>Y</italic> mRNA levels to peak soon after dawn. No gene with this expression pattern had been observed experimentally.</p><p>In order to identify <italic>Y</italic>, we analysed the transcript abundance of clock-affecting genes with peak RNA levels in the evening in WT and <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant seedlings. Tissue samples were harvested across the light&#x02013;dark transitions in one LD cycle, followed by one cycle in LL. <italic>GI</italic> mRNA levels fitted very well to our predicted mRNA profiles for <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>). <italic>GI</italic> was shown to be significantly but transiently light activated in the WT and had a very strong light response in the double mutant. The subsequent circadian peak also fitted closely to the prediction for <italic>Y</italic> mRNA, including the 12 h phase advance in the mutant relative to WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>). The tentative identification of <italic>Y</italic> as <italic>GI</italic> allowed us to test whether <italic>Y</italic> in our model fitted additional, published results for <italic>GI</italic>; indeed, further data do support this proposed function of <italic>GI</italic>. <italic>GI</italic> mRNA is at a low, arrhythmic level in plants that overexpress <italic>LHY</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Fowler et al, 1999</xref>) or <italic>TOC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Makino et al, 2002</xref>): this agrees with model predictions (data not shown) and occurs because both <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>TOC1</italic> repress <italic>Y</italic> transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>). The sequence of the <italic>GI</italic> promoter includes several Evening Elements, the putative binding sites for LHY (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Harmer et al, 2000</xref>). <italic>gi</italic> loss-of-function mutations result in low-amplitude circadian rhythms, with low levels of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> RNA and either shorter or longer circadian periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Fowler et al, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">Park et al, 1999</xref>) or, in some conditions, in arrhythmia (A Hall, personal communication). A simulated null mutation of <italic>Y</italic> indeed results in still lower <italic>LHY</italic> transcription and therefore in arrhythmia. If another gene in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> can substitute for a fraction of <italic>Y</italic> function, then null mutants will avoid arrhythmia. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 6</xref> shows the oscillation of <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA levels in a simulated partial loss-of-function <italic>y</italic> mutant, where <italic>Y</italic> translation rate has been halved compared to the WT rate. As observed in <italic>gi</italic> mutants, the oscillations have reduced <italic>LHY</italic> expression and a low amplitude both in LD cycles and in LL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We use a joint, experimental and mathematical approach to understand the plant circadian clock as an example of a regulatory subnetwork that is not completely identified. We start from the first proposed feedback loop of the circadian clock mechanism in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1</italic> network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Alabadi et al, 2001</xref>). Comparing model predictions with experimental results, we have progressively incorporated additional components and interactions identified by molecular genetics or inferred from physiological analysis. The final, interlocking loop model accounts for a greater range of data than the single-loop models, including the entrainable, short-period oscillations in the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant. In developing this model, we included two putative genes <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic>, and used experiments designed from the model predictions to identify <italic>GI</italic> as a candidate gene for <italic>Y</italic>. Additional components of the plant circadian clock mechanism almost certainly remain to be identified, but we believe that this model is a significant step forward in understanding of the timing mechanism.</p><p>The prediction of new components is a particularly beneficial outcome from formal modelling of a system that has not been completely identified by experiment. Mathematical models, in contrast to intuitive reasoning, can produce quantitative predictions of dynamic processes that allow detailed experimental design. This was important: the acute light activation of <italic>Y</italic> in WT was predicted to be very transient (peak 25 min after lights-on; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>), allowing us to target our tissue sampling to the appropriate interval, whereas conventional sampling had obscured this induction of <italic>GI</italic> RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>). The interlocked feedback model now highlights the importance of <italic>GI</italic> as a component of light input to the clock, a role that had not previously been emphasised and should now be tested in greater detail. The activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> by <italic>GI</italic> in an interlocked feedback loop is also a new proposal, which is consistent with the timing of peak <italic>GI</italic> expression before <italic>TOC1</italic>. Mutants that remove both the loops, such as the <italic>lhy;cca1;gi</italic> triple mutant, should now be tested to determine whether further oscillating subnetworks remain in their absence. A recent study has suggested the existence of a feedback loop between <italic>APRR9/APRR7</italic> and <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">Farre et al, 2005</xref>). Including this loop would not affect our conclusions on the residual network in the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant, which would lack this additional loop. As more data become available, it will be possible to determine how the <italic>PRR</italic> genes should be included into the network model. The component(s) that activate <italic>CCA1</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic> at the end of the night remain to be identified: the model predicts the likely accumulation pattern of such a component, <italic>X</italic>. The level of detail in such predictions is obviously limited by the data upon which the model is based, so including statistical measures of uncertainty with the predictions will be increasingly important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Brown and Sethna, 2003</xref>).</p><p>Each model makes further, qualitative predictions that appear robust and readily testable. The constant activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> by light reproducibly caused arrhythmia of the <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1&#x02013;X</italic> model under long photoperiods or LL, for example, which is not observed in WT plants. This highlights the importance of rhythmic inhibition of the light input (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">Roenneberg and Merrow, 2002</xref>), which is a wide spread feature of clocks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">Fleissner and Fleissner, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">Jewett et al, 1999</xref>). It is reminiscent of the <italic>ELF3</italic>-dependent zeitnehmer function observed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">McWatters et al, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Covington et al, 2001</xref>). In the interlocked loop model, repression of <italic>Y</italic> by LHY and by TOC1 are sufficient to gate the light activation of <italic>Y</italic>, so we had no justification for further additions to this model. Clearly, such models should be interpreted with caution, because undiscovered components cannot be included explicitly. A model that accurately recapitulates the regulation of known components is very likely to have captured the relevant effects of the &#x02018;hidden' components. The model can advance understanding and make useful predictions but might not capture the real number or mechanism of the hidden components. For example, we model the direct activator of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> as the product of a TOC1-activated gene, <italic>X</italic>, which could be a minor population of modified TOC1 protein or TOC1-dependent protein complex. We assume that <italic>Y</italic> mediates both the second light input and the additional feedback loop for parsimony, which is now supported by data on <italic>GI</italic>, although these functions could in principle be split among several components.</p><p>The importance of the light input pathways in our models was to be expected, because the plant circadian system is known to interact with multiple photoreceptor pathways in a complex fashion (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Fankhauser and Staiger, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Millar, 2003</xref>). The tracking of multiple phases during entrainment is thought to require at least two light inputs to two feedback loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Rand et al, 2004</xref>), for example, which are present in our final model. The entrainment patterns of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> clock under different photoperiods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Millar and Kay, 1996</xref>) indicate that the phase of the clock does not simply track dawn. Therefore, the clock must receive light input(s) at times other than the dark&#x02013;light transition. In our model, <italic>LHY</italic> allows light input at dawn, while input to <italic>Y</italic> and <italic>ZTL</italic> is potentially effective throughout the day. The known input photoreceptors could in future be explicitly included, providing quantitative estimates of their function for comparison to data from plant photobiology. Similarly, the models will help to reveal how the circadian output pathways allow the few genes of the clock to control over a thousand rhythmically regulated genes in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Harmer et al, 2000</xref>). However, the complexity of such biological networks is likely to limit the quantitative accuracy of early models, so the potential value of simplified experimental model systems that facilitate the link to mathematical analysis is clear. These will include synthetic gene networks in microbial hosts but also &#x02018;reduced' systems: we have recently characterised circadian rhythms in seedlings without light exposure, in which both the complexity of the circadian system and the number of clock-controlled target genes are greatly reduced (A Hall <italic>et al</italic>, unpublished results).</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title><p>Wassilewskija (Ws) WT and <italic>cca1-11</italic>;<italic>lhy-21</italic> (termed <italic>cca1;lhy</italic>) double mutants in the Ws background (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Hall et al, 2003</xref>) were used in all experiments. Luciferase reporter gene fusions containing the promoter region of <italic>CCA1</italic> (<italic>CCA1:LUC</italic>&#x0002b;), <italic>CHOLOROPHYLL</italic> A/B<italic>-BINDING PROTEIN2</italic> (<italic>LHCB1.1</italic>)(<italic>CAB2:LUC</italic>&#x0002b;) and <italic>COLD AND CIRCADIAN REGULATED 2</italic> (<italic>CCR2:LUC</italic>&#x0002b;) were introduced into Ws and mutant plants by Agrobacterium-mediated transformation, essentially as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Hall et al, 2003</xref>). For each genotype and reporter, three independent transgenic lines were tested in each experiment; all gave very similar results. Light sources were as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Hall et al, 2003</xref>). Seedlings for luminescence analysis were grown under 12 h light:12 h dark cycles (LD12:12), as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Hall et al, 2003</xref>). Seedlings for RNA analysis were grown under LD12:12 comprising 13&#x02013;20 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> red light for 6 days, followed by constant 13&#x02013;20 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> red light for 3 days. Samples of &#x0223c;150 &#x003bc;l packed volume of seedlings were harvested into RNA<italic>later</italic> buffer (Ambion, Huntingdon, UK) to stabilise RNAs, starting in the last cycle of entrainment.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Luminescence and rhythm analysis</title><p>Luminescence of individual seedlings was measured with an automated luminometer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Doyle et al, 2002</xref>). Rhythmic data were analysed using the fast Fourier transform nonlinear least squares procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">Plautz et al, 1997</xref>) through the Biological Rhythms Analysis Software System, available online (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Brown, 2004a</xref>). Variance-weighted mean periods and standard errors are presented. To create PTCs, seedlings expressing the <italic>CCR2:LUC</italic>&#x0002b; reporter were grown and entrained as above, and then transferred to DD at the predicted time of lights-off. Luminescence signals were monitored for 5 days in DD. After 24 h in DD, separate populations of seedlings were treated with 15 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> red light for 1 h and returned to DD at 3 h intervals. The free running period and phase of the control (nontreated WT and mutant) plants was used to calculate the circadian time of the light treatments (&#x02018;old phase'). The time of the next peak of <italic>CCR2:LUC</italic>&#x0002b; expression was determined in the treated plants and circadian time of the &#x02018;new phase' set at the light pulse was estimated using the cognate period value.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>RNA analysis</title><p>Seedlings were homogenised in RLT buffer (Qiagen, Crawley, UK) using a MixerMill MM300 at a frequency of 30 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for 3 min with a 5 mm stainless steel cone ball (Retsch, Leeds, UK). Total RNA was isolated using a Plant RNeasy kit and RNase-free DNase (Qiagen, Crawley, UK) according to the manufacturer's instructions. A 1 &#x003bc;g portion of total RNA was reverse-transcribed using the RevertAid cDNA kit (Fermentas, Helena Biosciences, Sunderland, UK) with random hexamer primers, according to the manufacturer's instructions. <italic>GI</italic> sequence abundance in each cDNA sample was assayed by quantitative PCR in an ABI PRISM 7700 using ABI SYBRgreen PCR Mix (Applied Biosystems, Warrington, UK) in a final volume of 15 &#x003bc;l. <italic>GI</italic> sequence abundance was normalised relative to <italic>ACTIN2</italic> (<italic>ACT2</italic>), using a cDNA dilution series for each primer set in each experiment. The following primers were used:&#x02003;&#x02003;<italic>GI</italic> forward primer AATTCAGCACGCGCCTATTG,&#x02003;&#x02003;<italic>GI</italic> reverse primer GTTGCTTCTGCTGCAGGAACTT;&#x02003;&#x02003;<italic>ACT2</italic> forward primer CAGTGTCTGGATCGGAGGAT,&#x02003;&#x02003;<italic>ACT2</italic> reverse primer TGAACAATCGATGGACCTGA, each at 300 nM.</p><p>Each RNA sample was assayed in triplicate. Data shown are a representative trace from two independent biological replicates that gave very similar results.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Computational methods</title><p>As there is too little data to discriminate <italic>LHY</italic> from <italic>CCA1</italic> regulation and function, we combine them in the single model component &#x02018;<italic>LHY/CCA1</italic>' in order to simplify our models (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary text</xref>); for brevity, we refer to this joint component as <italic>LHY</italic>, as in our previous work. Our method of parameter estimation uses a cost function, which is based on reproducible, qualitative features of experimental data, to score the performance of a model with a test parameter set. The cost function is minimised by the optimisation procedure described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>). A low cost (indicating a good fit) is obtained for parameter sets that allow the model of WT plants to be entrained in LD12:12 cycles, with <italic>LHY</italic> RNA levels that peak at dawn, <italic>TOC1</italic> RNA levels that peak at dusk and oscillations with a period greater than 24 h in DD. As there is only limited, noisy experimental data for the mRNA oscillation of <italic>TOC1</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic> in DD, it is difficult to verify that the <italic>TOC1</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA levels converge to a stable limit cycle. The cost function only requires that <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA levels oscillate with slow damping in DD, giving a reasonable score if the size of oscillation has dropped by 25&#x00025; over 300 h (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">Strayer et al, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Kim et al, 2003</xref>). Developing the model based on LD and DD data allowed subsequent testing of the model by comparison to the larger amount of experimental data available from LL conditions.</p><p>The interlocked feedback loop network proposed here was scored both as a model of WT and of the <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> mutant. The double mutant was simulated by reducing the translation rate of <italic>LHY</italic> to 1/1000th of its WT value. This simulated mutation led to arrhythmia in all the single-loop models (data not shown). Additional terms were introduced to the cost function to score models of the double mutant, specifying entrainment under LD12:12 with peak <italic>TOC1</italic> expression 5 h after dawn and oscillations with a period of 18 h or less in DD. To enable <italic>TOC1</italic> activation sufficiently early in the day in the double mutant, we required that <italic>Y</italic> transcription peaked sharply at dawn in the double mutant.</p><p>The 20 parameter sets with the lowest costs (which allowed the model to best fit the specified criteria) all simulated similar gene expression profiles in WT and <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> backgrounds (data not shown). An optimal parameter set was chosen from these 20 by comparing the simulated rhythms to experimental data that were not included in the cost function (see Results).</p><p>The equations were solved using MATLAB (Mathworks, Cambridge, UK). Parameter optimisation was carried out (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Locke et al, 2005</xref>) by compiling MATLAB code into C and running the code on a task farm computer consisting of 62 &#x000d7; 2.6 GHz Xeon CPUs. We have developed a user-friendly interface, Circadian Modelling, to allow simulations using this and other circadian models, without MATLAB. This software and files for our final model are available online (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Brown, 2004b</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d32e25" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>Supplementary Figures</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-s1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e29" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>Legend to Supplementary Figures and Tables</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-s2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e33" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>Supplementary Tables</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-s3.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e37" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>Supplementary Text</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-s4.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e41" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>Structured data 1</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-sd1.xml" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="xml"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to OE Biringen-Akman, D Salazar, JA Langdale, CD Westbrook and DA Rand for useful discussions, and to N Shariff for technical assistance. JCWL was supported by a postgraduate studentship from the Gatsby Charitable Foundation; MMS was supported by a postgraduate studentship from BBSRC; LKB was supported by an EMBO postdoctoral fellowship; experimental work was funded by grants G15231 and G19886 from BBSRC to AJM. Computer facilities were provided by the Centre for Scientific Computing at the University of Warwick.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Alabadi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Reciprocal regulation between TOC1 and LHY/CCA1 within the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>293</volume>: <fpage>880</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>883</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11486091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Alabadi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Critical role for CCA1 and LHY in maintaining circadian rhythmicity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>757</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>761</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12007421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sethna</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Statistical mechanical approaches to models with many poorly known parameters</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E Stat Nonlinear Soft Matter Phys</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>021904</fpage>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>2004a</year>) <article-title>Biological Rhythms Analysis Software System</article-title>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.amillar.org/Downloads.html">http://www.amillar.org/Downloads.html</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>2004b</year>) <article-title>Circadian Modelling</article-title>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.amillar.org/Downloads.html">http://www.amillar.org/Downloads.html</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Covington</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strayer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>ELF3 modulates resetting of the circadian clock in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1315</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bastow</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McWatters</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kozma-Bognar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The ELF4 gene controls circadian rhythms and flowering time in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>419</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12214234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Molecular bases for circadian clocks</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>290</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9988221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The circadian clock. A plant's best friend in a spinning world</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>732</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>738</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Staiger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Photoreceptors in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: light perception, signal transduction and entrainment of the endogenous clock</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>216</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12430009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Farre</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Overlapping and distinct roles of PRR7 and PRR9 in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15649364</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fleissner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleissner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Feedback loops in the circadian system</article-title>. <source>Disc Neurosci</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Forger</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peskin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A detailed predictive model of the mammalian circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>14806</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14811</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14657377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Onouchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Putterill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>
<italic>GIGANTEA</italic>: a circadian clock-controlled gene that regulates photoperiodic flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and encodes a protein with several possible membrane-spanning domains</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>4679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4688</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10469647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Glossop</surname><given-names>NRJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hardin</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Interlocked feedback loops within the <italic>Drosophila</italic> circadian oscillator</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>286</volume>: <fpage>766</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>768</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10531060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Loss of the circadian clock-associated protein I in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> results in altered clock-regulated gene expression</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>4176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4179</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10097183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bastow</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McWatters</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The TIME FOR COFFEE gene maintains the amplitude and timing of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> circadian clocks</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2729</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hogenesch</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Straume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kreps</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Orchestrated transcription of key pathways in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by the circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>290</volume>: <fpage>2110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11118138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jewett</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forger</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kronauer</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Revised limit cycle oscillator model of human circadian pacemaker</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>499</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10643746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carre</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Light-regulated translation mediates gated induction of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> clock protein LHY</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>944</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12574129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loros</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Interconnected feedback loops in the <italic>Neurospora</italic> circadian system</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>289</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10884222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Leloup</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldbeter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Toward a detailed computational model for the mammalian circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>7051</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7056</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12775757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Leloup</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonze</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldbeter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Limit cycle models for circadian rhythms based on transcriptional regulation in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and <italic>Neurospora</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10643740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>JCW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Modelling genetic networks with noisy and varied experimental data: the circadian clock in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>
<volume>234</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>393</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15784272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ueguchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Genes encoding pseudo-response regulators: insight into His-to-Asp phosphorelay and circadian rhythm in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>803</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10945350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsushika</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Light response of the circadian waves of the APRR1/TOC1 quintet: when does the quintet start singing rhythmically in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>?</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>339</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11266585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsushika</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The APRR1/TOC1 quintet implicated in circadian rhythms of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: I. Characterization with APRR1-overexpressing plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11828023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Martinez-Garcia</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Direct targeting of light signals to a promoter element-bound transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>288</volume>: <fpage>859</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>863</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10797009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alabadi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2003a</year>) <article-title>Dual role of TOC1 in the control of circadian and photomorphogenic responses in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>236</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12509533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2003b</year>) <article-title>Targeted degradation of TOC1 by ZTL modulates circadian function in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>426</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>570</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McWatters</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bastow</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The <italic>ELF3 zeitnehmer</italic> regulates light signalling to the circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>408</volume>: <fpage>716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>720</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A suite of photoreceptors entrains the plant circadian clock</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12828279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Integration of circadian and phototransduction pathways in the network controlling <italic>CAB</italic> gene transcription in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>15491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15496</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8986839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wheatley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carre</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>LHY and CCA1 are partially redundant genes required to maintain circadian rhythms in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>641</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soh</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Control of circadian rhythms and photoperiodic flowering by the <italic>Arabidopsis GIGANTEA</italic> gene</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>285</volume>: <fpage>1579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1582</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10477524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Plautz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Straume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stanewsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dowse</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Quantitative analysis of <italic>Drosophila period</italic> gene transcription in living animals</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>217</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9181432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shulgin</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Design principles underlying circadian clocks</article-title>. <source>Interface</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>130</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16849158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Roden</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carre</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Floral responses to photoperiod are correlated with the timing of rhythmic expression relative to dawn and dusk in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>13313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13318</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12271123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Roenneberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merrow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Life before the clock: modeling circadian evolution</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>505</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12465882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ruoff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behzadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hauglid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vinsjevik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Havas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>ph homeostasis of the circadian sporulation rhythm in clock mutants of <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>750</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11128290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ruoff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vinsjevik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monnerjahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rensing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The Goodwin model: simulating the effect of light pulses on the circadian sporulation rhythm of <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>
<volume>209</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11237568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Salome</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> clock</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15534322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Putterill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carre</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The late elongated hypocotyl mutation of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> disrupts circadian rhythms and the photoperiodic control of flowering</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1229</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9657154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hardin</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Simulation of <italic>Drosophila</italic> circadian oscillations, mutations, and light responses by a model with VRI, PDP-1, and CLK</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source>
<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>2786</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2802</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15111397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The F-box protein ZEITLUPE confers dosage-dependent control on the circadian clock, photomorphogenesis, and flowering time</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>782</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14973171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stelling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Robustness properties of circadian clock architectures</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>13210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13215</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15340155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Strayer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kreps</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cloning of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> clock cone TOC1, an autoregulatory response regulator homolog</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>289</volume>: <fpage>768</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>771</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10926537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tyson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thron</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A simple model of circadian rhythms based on dimerization and proteolysis of PER and TIM</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source>
<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>2411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2417</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10545344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Robust oscillations within the interlocked feedback model of <italic>Drosophila</italic> circadian rhythm</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>
<volume>210</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>406</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11403560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Constitutive expression of the CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED 1 (CCA1) gene disrupts circadian rhythms and suppresses its own expression</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1217</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9657153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular basis of seasonal time measurement in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>419</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12239570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p>Article Highlights added to synopsis 5 July 2005.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The single-loop <italic>LHY/CCA1&#x02013;TOC1-X</italic> network. Left panel: Network diagram. <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> are modelled as a single gene, <italic>LHY</italic> (genes are boxed). Nuclear and cytoplasmic protein levels are grouped for clarity (shown encircled) and degradation is not shown. Light acutely activates <italic>LHY</italic> transcription at dawn and activates <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription throughout the day. TOC1 activates a putative gene <italic>X</italic>, which in turn activates <italic>LHY</italic>. Nuclear LHY protein represses <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription. Right panel: Simulation of mRNA levels for the optimal parameter set. In all figures, filled box above the panel represent dark interval and open or no box represent light interval. <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA (dotted line) peaks at dawn in LD12:12 and <italic>TOC1</italic> (solid line) falls after dusk, due to the loss of light activation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>CCR2:LUC</italic>&#x0002b; in WT (filled diamonds) and <italic>cca1-11;lhy-21</italic> double mutant (open diamonds) plants in LL (top) and DD (bottom). Luminescence of each seedling was normalised to its mean value over the entire time course. Data are averages of normalised luminescence from WT seedlings in LL <italic>n</italic>=16, in DD <italic>n</italic>=18, <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> seedlings in LL <italic>n</italic>=13, in DD <italic>n</italic>=15. Error bars represent one s.e.m., often within symbols.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>PTC for WT (left panel) and <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant (right panel). Red light pulses (15 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for 1 h) were administered at 3 h intervals to <italic>CCR2:LUC</italic>&#x0002b; plants in DD. The new phase of the rhythm induced by the light pulses was converted to circadian time (CT, 24ths of the free-running period) and plotted against the circadian time of light treatment (solid lines). Simulated phase responses are represented by dashed lines, and show simulated response of the interlocked feedback loop model to a 1 h light pulse. Phase marker for simulation was <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA peak, compared to <italic>CCR2:LUC</italic>&#x0002b; peak in data.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The interlocked feedback loop network. Left panel: Network diagram. Compared to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>, <italic>TOC1</italic> is activated by light indirectly via hypothetical gene <italic>Y</italic>. Y activates <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription and both LHY and TOC1 repress <italic>Y</italic> transcription, forming a second feedback loop. Right panel: Simulation of <italic>LHY</italic> (dashed line) and <italic>TOC1</italic> (solid line) mRNA levels for the optimal parameter set, representing WT (top) and <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> double mutant (bottom) in DD. Translation rate of <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA in simulated mutant is 1/1000 WT value. Period of WT in DD is 26 h and period of mutant is 17 h.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of interlocked feedback loop simulations (dashed line) under LD to data (solid line). (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA levels in WT plants entrained to LD12:12, left axis; TOC1 mRNA levels relative to UBIQUITIN (UBQ) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">Makino et al, 2000</xref>), right axis. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA levels in WT plants entrained to LD12:12, left axis; data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Kim et al (2003)</xref>, right axis. (<bold>C&#x02013;E</bold>) <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA levels in WT (C), <italic>cca1;lhy</italic> mutant (D) and <italic>cca1</italic> mutant (E) entrained to LD16:8; data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Mizoguchi et al (2002)</xref>. Translation rate of <italic>LHY</italic> in simulated <italic>cca1</italic> is set to 1/2 WT value. Highest value of data and simulation is set to 1, for each panel. (<bold>F</bold>) TOC1 protein levels for WT simulation entrained to LD12:12; TOC1 fusion protein data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Mas et al (2003b)</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-f5"/></fig><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>
<italic>GI</italic> is a candidate gene for <italic>Y</italic>. Simulated <italic>Y</italic> mRNA levels under LD12:12 and LL (dashed line). Data for <italic>GI</italic> mRNA levels (crosses), assayed by quantitative RT&#x02013;PCR relative to the <italic>ACT2</italic> control, from samples harvested at the times indicated. Left panel, WT; right panel, <italic>cca1;lhy</italic>. Highest value of data and simulation is set to 1, for each panel.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb4100018-f6"/></fig></floats-group></article>