<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Syst Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Systems Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1744-4292</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20865009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2964123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">msb201069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2010.69</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Data assimilation constrains new connections and components in a complex, eukaryotic circadian clock model</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pokhilko</surname><given-names>Alexandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>Sarah K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stratford</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>Kirsten</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>Kieron D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>Adrian W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n2">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>Andrew J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>School of Biological Sciences, University of Edinburgh</institution>, Mayfield Road, Edinburgh, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Edinburgh Parallel Computing Center (EPCC), JCMB, University of Edinburgh</institution>, Mayfield Road, Edinburgh, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Laboratory of Molecular Microbiology, School of Agriculture, Nagoya University</institution>, Chikusa-ku, Nagoya, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>Centre for Systems Biology at Edinburgh</institution>, CH Waddington Building, Kings Buildings, Mayfield Road, Edinburgh, <country>UK</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label>Centre for Systems Biology at Edinburgh, University of Edinburgh, CH Waddington Building, Kings Buildings, Mayfield Road, Edinburgh EH9 3JD, UK. Tel.: +44 131 651 3325; Fax: +44 131 651 9068; <email>andrew.millar@ed.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="n1"><label>*</label><p>Present address: Advanced Technologies (Cambridge) Ltd., Cambridge, UK</p></fn><fn id="n2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Present address: School of Clinical Sciences and Community Health, 49 Little France Crescent, Edinburgh, UK</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>09</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>09</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>01</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2010, EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><copyright-holder>EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial Share Alike 3.0 Unported License, which allows readers to alter, transform, or build upon the article and then distribute the resulting work under the same or similar license to this one. The work must be attributed back to the original author and commercial use is not permitted without specific permission.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="hidden-highlights"><p><list id="l1" list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Integrating molecular time-series data resulted in a more robust model of the plant clock, which predicts that a wave of inhibitory PRR proteins controls the morning genes <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>PRR5 is experimentally validated as a late-acting component of this wave.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The family of sequentially expressed PRR proteins allows flexible entrainment of the clock, whereas a single protein could not, suggesting that the duplication of clock genes might confer this generic, functional advantage.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The observed post-translational regulation of the evening protein TOC1 by interaction with ZTL and GI remains consistent with an indirect activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA expression by GI, which was previously postulated from modelling.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="hidden-synopsis"><p>Circadian rhythms are present in most eukaryotic organisms including plants. The core genes of the circadian clock are very important for plant physiology as they drive the rhythmic expression of around 30&#x00025; of Arabidopsis genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Edwards et al, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Michael et al, 2008</xref>). The clock is normally entrained by daily environmental changes in light and temperature. Oscillations also persist under constant environmental conditions in a laboratory. The clock gene circuit in Arabidopsis is based on multiple interlocked feedback loops, which are typical of circadian genetic networks in other organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">Dunlap and Loros, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">Bell-Pedersen et al, 2005</xref>). Mechanistic, mathematical models are increasingly useful in analysing and understanding how the observed molecular components give rise to the rhythmic behaviour of this dynamic, non-linear system.</p><p>Our previous model of Arabidopsis circadian clock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>) presented the core, three-loop structure of the clock, which comprised morning and evening oscillators and coupling between them (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). The morning loop included the dawn-expressed <italic>LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL (LHY)</italic> and <italic>CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED 1 (CCA1)</italic> genes, which negatively regulate their expression through activation of the inhibitor proteins, PSEUDO-RESPONSE REGULATOR 9 (PRR9) and PRR7. These were described by a single, combined model component, PRR9/7. The evening loop included the dusk-expressed gene <italic>TIMING OF CAB EXPRESSION 1</italic> (<italic>TOC1</italic>), which negatively regulates itself through inhibition of a hypothetical activator, gene <italic>Y</italic>. The evening-expressed gene <italic>GIGANTEA</italic> (<italic>GI</italic>) contributes to <italic>Y</italic> function. The morning and evening loops were connected through inhibition of the evening genes by LHY/CCA1 and activation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression by a hypothetical evening gene <italic>X</italic>. Here, we extend the previous model of circadian gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>) based on recently published data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). The new model retains the good match of our previous model to the large volume of molecular time-series data, and improves the behaviour of the model clock system under a range of light conditions and in a wider range of mutants.</p><p>The morning loop was extended by adding a hypothetical clock component, the night inhibitor (NI), which acts together with PRR9 and PRR7 to keep the expression of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> at low levels over a broad interval spanning dusk. This regulation is important to set the phase of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression at dawn. Data from the literature suggested that the <italic>PRR5</italic> gene was a candidate for <italic>NI</italic>, leading us to predict that the sequentially expressed PRR9, PRR7 and PRR5 proteins together formed a wave of inhibitors of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic>. This hypothesis was tested under discriminating light conditions, in which the light interval is replaced with the dawn and dusk pulses of light to form a &#x02018;skeleton photoperiod'. Combining this protocol with mutation of the <italic>PRR7</italic> and/or <italic>PRR5</italic> genes, our new experimental results validated the model predictions and confirmed that PRR5 contributes to the function that we modelled as NI. During revision of this paper, that result received further experimental support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Nakamichi et al, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Model simulations revealed the functional importance of the inhibitor wave in entraining the clock to the light/dark cycle. Separating <italic>PRR9</italic> from the other inhibitors in the model showed how the strong light activation observed for this gene contributes to more rapid entrainment. The observed, post-translation regulation of all three inhibitor proteins by light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Farre and Kay, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Ito et al, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Kiba et al, 2007</xref>) was also included in the model. Light-regulated degradation provides a molecular mechanism to explain the later phase of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression under long photoperiods compared with short photoperiods, in line with experimental observations.</p><p>The connection between evening and morning loops was revised by including the inhibition of the morning gene <italic>PRR9</italic> by the evening component TOC1, based on the data on <italic>TOC1</italic>-overexpressing plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">Makino et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Ito et al, 2005</xref>). This inhibition causes a delay of <italic>PRR9</italic> expression relative to <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic>, which allows <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> to reach a higher expression level at dawn. Our simulations showed that a partial mutant that lacks this inhibition of <italic>PRR9</italic> by TOC1 is sufficient to cause the higher level of <italic>PRR9</italic> and the short circadian period observed in <italic>toc1</italic> mutant plants.</p><p>The evening loop was extended by introducing the observed, post-translational regulation of the TOC1 protein by the F-box protein ZEITLUPE (ZTL) and stabilization of ZTL by its interaction with GI in the presence of light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Kim et al, 2007</xref>). GI's function in the clock model has thus been revised according to the data: GI promotes an inhibition of TOC1 protein function through positive regulation of ZTL. This results, together with negative regulation of <italic>Y</italic> by TOC1, in indirect activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA expression by GI, which agrees with our earlier experimental data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>). Simulations showed that the post-translational regulation of TOC1 by ZTL and GI results in the observed long period of the <italic>ztl</italic> mutant and fast dampening of rhythms in the <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> triple mutant.</p><p>This is the first mathematical model that incorporates the observed post-translational regulation into the genetic network of the Arabidopsis clock. In addition to specific, mechanistic insights, the model shows a generic advantage from the duplication of clock genes and their expression at different phases. Such clock gene duplications are observed in eukaryotes with larger genomes, such as the mouse. Analogous, functional duplication can be achieved by differential regulation of a single clock gene in distinct cells, as in Drosophila.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Circadian clocks generate 24-h rhythms that are entrained by the day/night cycle. Clock circuits include several light inputs and interlocked feedback loops, with complex dynamics. Multiple biological components can contribute to each part of the circuit in higher organisms. Mechanistic models with morning, evening and central feedback loops have provided a heuristic framework for the clock in plants, but were based on transcriptional control. Here, we model observed, post-transcriptional and post-translational regulation and constrain many parameter values based on experimental data. The model's feedback circuit is revised and now includes <italic>PSEUDO-RESPONSE REGULATOR 7</italic> (<italic>PRR7</italic>) and <italic>ZEITLUPE</italic>. The revised model matches data in varying environments and mutants, and gains robustness to parameter variation. Our results suggest that the activation of important morning-expressed genes follows their release from a night inhibitor (NI). Experiments inspired by the new model support the predicted NI function and show that the <italic>PRR5</italic> gene contributes to the NI. The multiple <italic>PRR</italic> genes of Arabidopsis uncouple events in the late night from light-driven responses in the day, increasing the flexibility of rhythmic regulation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></kwd><kwd>biological clocks</kwd><kwd>circadian rhythms</kwd><kwd>mathematical model</kwd><kwd>systems biology</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Circadian rhythms are widespread in the biology of almost all eukaryotic organisms, including plants. The self-sustained 24 h oscillations of the core clock genes drive rhythmic expression of &#x0003e;30&#x00025; of the Arabidopsis genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Michael and McClung, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Edwards et al, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Covington et al, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Michael et al, 2008</xref>) and thus provide plants with an adaptive advantage to anticipate the daily changes in environmental conditions, such as light/dark cycles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Dodd et al, 2005</xref>). The current concept of the Arabidopsis circadian clock is of a genetic network consisting of morning and evening feedback loops interconnected by a central loop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">McClung, 2006</xref>). The complexity of the mechanism, consisting of two coupled oscillators, makes mathematical modelling a useful tool for the analysis of functional properties of the system.</p><p>Our previous model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>), hereafter referred to as L2006, was based on the three-loop circuit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). The dawn-expressed genes <italic>LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL (LHY)</italic> and <italic>CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED 1 (CCA1)</italic> form a morning negative feedback loop through activation of their inhibitors, <italic>PSEUDO-RESPONSE REGULATOR 9</italic> (<italic>PRR9</italic>) and <italic>PRR7</italic>. <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> also control the phase of evening genes by inhibiting their expression in the morning. The important evening gene <italic>TIMING OF CAB EXPRESSION 1</italic> (<italic>TOC1</italic>), which is expressed at dusk, regulates itself in the evening loop of the clock through inhibition of its hypothetical activator, gene <italic>Y</italic>. The evening-expressed gene <italic>GIGANTEA</italic> (<italic>GI</italic>) was previously suggested to be a component of <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>). The evening loop feeds back to the morning loop through the hypothetical gene <italic>X</italic>, which activates <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression in the late night. Light stimulates the expression of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic>, <italic>PRR9</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> and thus provides daily resetting or entrainment of the clock.</p><p>Although it remains a foundation for understanding the Arabidopsis circadian clock, the L2006 model did not include recent experimental findings, particularly on post-translational regulation. GI protein regulates the clock at the post-translational level by stabilization of the F-box protein ZEITLUPE (ZTL) in the presence of light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Kim et al, 2007</xref>). ZTL, in turn, is necessary for the targeting of TOC1 protein to degradation by the proteasome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Kim et al, 2007</xref>). The results from <italic>gi</italic> mutants have questioned the implication that GI directly regulates <italic>TOC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Martin-Tryon et al, 2007</xref>), which was proposed for Y in the L2006 model. The evening-expressed gene <italic>PRR5</italic> was not explicitly included in the model, though together with the morning genes <italic>PRR9</italic> and <italic>PRR7</italic>, <italic>PRR5</italic> is important for the regulation of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Farre et al, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Nakamichi et al, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">2010</xref>). Several results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Farre and Kay, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Ito et al, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Kiba et al, 2007</xref>) also suggest that PRRs are regulated by light at the protein level. Finally, the model could not describe the low level of <italic>PRR9</italic> mRNA in transgenic plants that overexpress <italic>TOC1</italic> (<italic>TOC1-ox</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">Makino et al, 2002</xref>).</p><p>Here, we have integrated the new data into the formal description of the clock gene network. First, we explicitly modelled GI and ZTL function, separating GI from Y and including the stabilization of ZTL by GI. The updated ZTL regulation retained a good match to previous data on the control of <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription by GI, but by an unexpected mechanism. Second, we introduced a new element, the night inhibitor (NI) of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression and suggested <italic>PRR5</italic> as a candidate component of the NI, with an important function in controlling the phase of morning gene expression. After showing that the model could match multiple sets of molecular time-series data, we analysed the clock responses to perturbations of the light conditions combined with mutations of the clock genes. New data on <italic>prr5/prr7</italic> double mutant plants showed a good match to the model, supporting the idea that PRR5 is an essential part of the NI. In summary, the model integrates new and existing experimental data and allows us to understand (describe, explain and predict) the complex responses of the clock to environmental and genetic perturbations.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Modification of the circadian clock circuit</title><p>An extended three-loop circuit for the circadian clock in Arabidopsis is proposed. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref> shows the principal scheme of the model. A more detailed description of the full reaction scheme, model assumptions and network equations are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>. The proposed scheme incorporates several new features compared with the L2006 model, based on experimental data as detailed below. The <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> genes are represented by a single <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> component, as before. In contrast to the previous models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Locke et al, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">2006</xref>), we identified data that constrained 35 of the 90 parameters in the model (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>). The remaining parameters were fitted to two types of data: the quantitative profiles of molecular components of the clock and the values of free-running periods of circadian rhythms, in wild-type (wt) plants and <italic>lhy/cca1</italic>, <italic>toc1</italic>, <italic>ztl</italic> and <italic>prr7/prr9</italic> mutants, under varying environmental conditions (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>). The parameter values used for all calculations are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. We then applied the model to analyse the mechanisms of circadian regulation under additional genetic and environmental perturbations.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Revised evening loop</title><p>We started the modification of the clock scheme from the evening loop, in which we included the post-translational regulation of TOC1 protein by GI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Kim et al, 2007</xref>). The model described the stabilization of the ZTL protein in complex with GI protein and the acceleration of TOC1 protein degradation by ZTL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Kim et al, 2007</xref>). Thus, GI inhibits <italic>TOC1</italic> function in the model at the level of TOC1 protein, through positive regulation of ZTL. Together with the inhibition of <italic>Y</italic> expression by TOC1 protein, this results in indirect activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA expression by GI in the model, as described in a later section. Previously, GI was also considered as the main candidate for <italic>Y</italic>, the direct activator of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression, accounting for 70&#x00025; of <italic>Y</italic> activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>). The high <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA levels in <italic>gi</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Martin-Tryon et al, 2007</xref>) suggested that this aspect of <italic>Y</italic> function was not related to <italic>GI</italic>. We, therefore, removed the direct activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression by GI in the model, and discovered that the revised structure of the evening loop retained the main features of the L2006 model.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Regulation of Y and TOC1 expression under different photoperiods</title><p>The structure of the evening loop of the clock, with activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription by Y, was originally based on the data on autonomous oscillations of the evening genes in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> double mutant plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Locke et al, 2005</xref>). The entrainment of rhythmic <italic>TOC1</italic> expression by light in the <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Mizoguchi et al, 2002</xref>), together with the absence of direct activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression by light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Matsushika et al, 2000</xref>), implied that <italic>Y</italic> was the light-responsive component of the evening loop. In addition, the evening expression of <italic>TOC1</italic> in wt plants suggested that the expression of <italic>Y</italic> was delayed through inhibition by LHY/CCA1 protein, analogous to <italic>GI</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Locke et al, 2005</xref>).</p><p>We used the revised model to predict the properties of Y and its regulation of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression. As the structure of the evening loop is inherited from our L2006 model, its components showed qualitatively similar behaviour. The predicted profiles of <italic>Y</italic> and <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA expression in wt plants under light&#x02013;dark cycles with various photoperiods are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2A</xref>. The first peak of <italic>Y</italic> after dawn is caused by the acute light activation of <italic>Y</italic> expression, whereas a second, major peak 10 h after dawn is related to the release of <italic>Y</italic> expression from its inhibition by LHY/CCA1 protein. The broad expression of Y during the light period allows a measure of &#x02018;dusk sensing' by the evening loop of the clock. Interestingly, the model predicts a later phase of peak <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA in short photoperiods compared with 9L:15D cycles, which corresponds to our experimental data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2C</xref>). The model explains this effect by the lower activation of <italic>Y</italic> expression in darkness, which slows down <italic>TOC1</italic> accumulation in cycles with &#x0003c;9 h of light.</p><p>The simulated double-peaked shape of <italic>Y</italic> mRNA profiles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2A</xref>) and the delayed phase of <italic>TOC1</italic> in short days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2C</xref>) were also observed in the simulations of wt plants using the L2006 model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figures 5 and 6</xref>). However, the current model predicted a stronger response to photoperiod in the <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7</xref> of <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2B</xref> shows the simulated profiles of <italic>Y</italic> and <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> plants under various photoperiods. <italic>Y</italic> mRNA is abundant in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> during the light period, which results in a broader profile of <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA in long days compared with short days. Our results on <italic>TOC1:LUC</italic> expression in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> mutant plants under 6L:18D and 18L:6D photoperiods confirm this prediction (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 19</xref>). The characteristic profiles predicted for <italic>Y</italic> expression in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> suggest that candidate genes for <italic>Y</italic> could be identified by testing genome-wide expression profiles in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> mutant plants under various photoperiods.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Feed-forward regulation of LHY/CCA1 amplitude by TOC1 and PRR9</title><p>In addition to the revision of the structure of the evening loop, we modified the connection between morning and evening oscillators. First, the unknown activator of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression (gene <italic>X</italic>) was replaced by a post-translational modification or complex dependent on TOC1 protein (TOC1<sub>mod</sub>), based on the data on TOC1 binding to protein complexes at the <italic>CCA1</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Pruneda-Paz et al, 2009</xref>). Second, an inhibition of <italic>PRR9</italic> expression by TOC1 was introduced, because overexpression of <italic>TOC1</italic> was shown to reduce <italic>PRR9</italic> mRNA to a negligible level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">Makino et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Ito et al, 2005</xref>).</p><p>Next, the model was used to analyse the regulation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> by TOC1 in more detail. The scheme of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref> suggests that there are three steps in <italic>TOC1</italic> action in the clock: (1) auto-regulation of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression through the inhibition of <italic>Y</italic>, (2) activation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression and (3) inhibition of <italic>PRR9</italic> expression. Model simulations showed that the third mechanism enhances the second, because the inhibition of <italic>PRR9</italic> by TOC1 delays <italic>PRR9</italic> expression relative to <italic>LHY/CCA1. LHY/CCA1</italic> expression can, therefore, rise further under the influence of TOC1<sub>mod</sub> before the onset of inhibition by PRR9 protein. The effect of TOC1's inhibition of <italic>PRR9</italic> on the expression profile of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> is especially pronounced in constant light (LL) conditions. The expression level of <italic>PRR9</italic> is low in LL, because the acute induction of <italic>PRR9</italic> at lights-on does not occur in these conditions. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref> shows the simulated profiles of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA and PRR9 protein for wt plants and a hypothetical <italic>toc1</italic> mutant that is unable to inhibit <italic>PRR9</italic> expression. The release of <italic>PRR9</italic> from inhibition by TOC1 results in a higher level of PRR9 protein, which in turn reduces the amplitude of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression and shortens the period in this partial <italic>toc1</italic> mutant.</p><p>The model predicts that the phenotype of <italic>toc1</italic> null mutants is similar to the partial <italic>toc1</italic> mutant described above (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 9</xref>). Thus, the experimentally observed 4 h shortening of the period and decrease of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> amplitude in the <italic>toc1</italic> mutant compared with wt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">Mas et al, 2003a</xref>) can be mostly ascribed to the above effect of the absence of <italic>PRR9</italic> inhibition by TOC1, rather than direct activation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic>. The proposed mechanism of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> regulation by TOC1 is known in the biology of transcriptional networks as a coherent feed-forward motif, when one transcription factor affects another and both of them jointly regulate a target gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">Mangan and Alon, 2003</xref>). In this case, TOC1 regulates <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> through a double negative connection through <italic>PRR9</italic>, in parallel with activation through TOC1<sub>mod</sub>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Updating of ZTL effects on the clock</title><p>The L2006 model included ZTL-dependent degradation of TOC1 protein, but it did not include the regulation of ZTL by the clock and light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>). Updating the mechanism of ZTL regulation by including its stabilization by GI in the presence of light allowed us to explore ZTL action in the clock. We found that in the absence of ZTL, the level of TOC1 protein is higher and its rhythm has lower amplitude in <italic>ztl</italic> mutants compared with wt plants, which corresponds to experimental observations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref> shows TOC1 protein (panel A) and TOC1<sub>mod</sub> protein (panel B) profiles in wt and <italic>ztl</italic> mutant plants in LL conditions. The change of TOC1 profile, in turn, results in the delay of the <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA peak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4B</xref>) and is in agreement with the experimentally observed, long period of the <italic>ztl</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>).</p><p>To understand the influence of ZTL on the evening loop, we revisited our previous data on the kinetics of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression in the <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> double and <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> triple mutant plants in LL conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>). Our simulations showed that the ZTL level would be low in <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5A</xref>), because of the rapid degradation of ZTL in the absence of GI protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Kim et al, 2007</xref>). The lower ZTL increased TOC1 protein levels in <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> compared with <italic>lhy/cca1</italic>. Next, the negative feedback from TOC1 to <italic>Y</italic> resulted in decreased <italic>Y</italic> mRNA in <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic>. As Y activates <italic>TOC1</italic> expression, this resulted in a lower level of <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA and reduction of oscillation amplitude in the <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> mutant plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5A and B</xref>). This prediction of the model suggested that GI stabilization of ZTL causes an unexpected, indirect activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression, consistent with the 2.5-fold increase of mean <italic>TOC1:LUC</italic> expression observed in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> compared with <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>). In summary, the above simulations of the wt, <italic>ztl</italic> and <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> mutants showed good agreement of the updated ZTL mechanism with existing experimental data.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Regulation of LHY/CCA1 expression by a wave of inhibitors allows dawn and dusk sensitivity</title><p>The morning loop was extended by introducing a new element, the NI of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> (NI). Introducing NI was originally motivated by the levels of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> mRNA, 100- to 1000-fold lower than their dawn peak, that were observed in the middle of the night (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). The identity of NI is discussed in the next section. Its effect, together with the day-phased inhibitors PRR9 and PRR7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Farre et al, 2005</xref>), guarantees that <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA quickly falls after dawn and stays at a very low level until the middle of the night. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref> shows the simulated profile of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA together with experimental data and the wave of inhibitor proteins. The high level of activator TOC1<sub>mod</sub> at night (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 8</xref>) ensures a steep rise of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA before dawn, when the inhibitor proteins degrade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>).</p><p>The model provides sequential expression of <italic>PRR9</italic>, <italic>PRR7</italic> and <italic>NI</italic> using a simple, effective formulation, because the molecular details underlying the striking &#x02018;PRR wave' of mRNA profiles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Matsushika et al, 2000</xref>) are unclear. <italic>PRR9</italic> expression in the model is activated by light at dawn and by LHY/CCA1 protein, consistent with data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Ito et al, 2005</xref>). PRR9 protein activates <italic>PRR7</italic>, and PRR7 activates <italic>NI</italic>. A modified form of LHY/CCA1 protein, LHY<sub>mod</sub>, is introduced to activate <italic>PRR7</italic> and <italic>NI</italic>. The PRR9/PRR7/NI activation cascade and LHY<sub>mod</sub> have no other function in the model. Phosphorylation of CCA1 protein, which is known to affect timing <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Daniel et al, 2004</xref>), provides one example of the type of post-translational modification envisaged for LHY<sub>mod</sub>. Alternative formulations are discussed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>.</p><p>Modelling the PRR/NI wave allowed us to explore the functional impact of multiple genes with divergent timing and light regulation in the morning loop. In addition to light-activated <italic>PRR9</italic> transcription, the model includes the light-dependent stabilization observed for PRR9 and PRR7 proteins and assumed for NI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Farre and Kay, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Ito et al, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Kiba et al, 2007</xref>). The PRR/NI wave has the potential to respond both to dawn, when <italic>PRR9</italic> is activated, and to dusk, when the PRR/NI proteins are degraded, and thus to alter circadian timing in response to changing photoperiods. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7A</xref> shows simulated <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA profiles under short 6L:18D photoperiods, standard 12L:12D photoperiods and long 18L:6D photoperiods. PRR9 was activated strongly after dawn in all photoperiods, matching published data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Matsushika et al, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>). The model predicts that the PRR7 and NI proteins will fall to low levels during the long dark interval in 6L:18D, owing to their higher degradation rate in darkness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>). Consequently, <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression is expected to be de-repressed earlier in short photoperiods compared with long photoperiods. This corresponds closely to our experimental data, in which <italic>CCA1</italic> mRNA levels rise 3 h earlier in short photoperiods compared with long photoperiods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7B</xref>).</p><p>Thus, the inclusion of the PRR/NI wave improved the entrainment of the model to various photoperiods compared with L2006 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>). In addition, the PRR/NI wave allowed the model to entrain in a broad range of T cycles (light/dark cycles of total duration T), again in contrast with L2006 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Validation of the inhibitor wave and the identity of NI</title><p>We used a classical protocol of circadian biology, the skeleton photoperiod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">Pittendrigh and Daan, 1976</xref>), to test the predicted regulation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> by the inhibitor wave. The skeleton photoperiod uses two short light treatments per daily cycle to entrain the clock, separating the contributions of light at dawn and dusk. Previous work had shown that the Arabidopsis clock could be entrained by skeleton photoperiods as expected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">Millar, 2003</xref>), but that &#x0003e;3 h light per cycle was required to maintain normal plant development (Millar, unpublished results). Simulations were, therefore, conducted to match the experiments: initial entrainment in 12L:12D was followed by simulated skeleton photoperiods with 3 h light treatments starting at dawn and ending at dusk (3L:6D:3L:12D). The <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA profile showed correct entrainment, with a strong peak at the first (&#x02018;dawn') pulse and only a small shoulder of expression at the second pulse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8A</xref>). The L2006 model failed to match this entrained pattern (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>). <italic>PRR9</italic>, in contrast, was predicted to show strong expression in response to both light pulses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8C</xref>).</p><p>The responses of wt plants to skeleton photoperiods were tested experimentally by measuring the bioluminescence of the <italic>CCA1:LUC</italic> and <italic>PRR9:LUC</italic> reporter genes. Our data confirmed the prevalence of the &#x02018;dawn' response in <italic>CCA1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8B</xref>), contrasting with major light induction of <italic>PRR9:LUC</italic> expression after both light pulses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8D</xref>). The slower decrease and delay in the peak of <italic>CCA1:LUC</italic> and <italic>PRR9:LUC</italic> activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8B and D</xref>) compared with the simulated mRNA in the model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8A and C</xref>) may result from a slower degradation rate of LUC mRNA and protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">Finkenstadt et al, 2008</xref>) compared with rapid degradation of <italic>CCA1</italic> and <italic>PRR9</italic> mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Ito et al, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">Yakir et al, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 17</xref> shows the faster decrease of <italic>CCA1</italic> and <italic>PRR9</italic> mRNA in qPCR measurements compared with <italic>CCA1:LUC</italic> and <italic>PRR9:LUC</italic>, supporting this interpretation. We conclude that light input pathways are functional during both light pulses in the skeleton photoperiod, yet <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> was only weakly induced at dusk.</p><p>The model explains the mechanism of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression at &#x02018;dawn', because the inhibitory PRR7 and NI proteins are degraded during the longer period of darkness that represents the night phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8A</xref>). In contrast, the PRR/NI inhibitors are strongly expressed during the day phase, which results in a low <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> response to the &#x02018;dusk' pulse of light.</p><p>The model predicted that the absence of both PRR7 and NI would result in the loss of the &#x02018;dawn preference' of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression in the skeleton protocol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8E</xref>). The existing data suggested that PRR5 is a good candidate for NI, because PRR5 together with PRR7 inhibits <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> RNA accumulation in darkness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Nakamichi et al, 2005</xref>) and data published during revision of this manuscript revealed physical association of PRR5 to <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Nakamichi et al, 2010</xref>). <italic>CCA1:LUC</italic> expression in the <italic>prr7/prr5</italic> double mutant responded at nearly equal levels to both light pulses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8F</xref>). This result indicates that PRR5 is a good candidate for NI, because it participates in the inhibition of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression at night together with PRR7.</p><p>To test the relative importance of PRR7 and PRR5 <italic>in vivo</italic>, we analysed the behaviour of the <italic>prr7</italic> and <italic>prr5</italic> single mutant plants under skeleton conditions. Our experiments showed some impairment of <italic>CCA1</italic> inhibition in the &#x02018;dusk' light pulse in both single mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8G and H</xref>) compared with wt plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8B</xref>). The difference between the <italic>prr7/prr5</italic> double mutant and the single mutants showed that both PRR7 and PRR5 normally contribute to repress <italic>CCA1</italic> expression in the late day.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>The main aim of this study was to understand better the structure of the circadian clock circuit based on existing and new experimental data. To achieve this, we improved our previous modelling approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>) by including more kinetic data to build and constrain the model. Quantitative time-series data from dynamic perturbation experiments are common in circadian biology and are essential to this approach. Experiments to measure specific parameter values are also helpful, because the sensitive parameters in complex biological models cannot generally be located <italic>a priori</italic>. Each measured parameter value, even with associated experimental uncertainty, progressively constrains the high-dimensional search space of biologically realistic values. The final model's behaviour may be robust (insensitive) to variation in many parameter values, but this does not justify a <italic>post hoc</italic> deprecation of laborious parameter measurements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">Gutenkunst et al, 2007</xref>). Measuring the degradation rates of the <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> and <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA, for example, was a relatively tractable experiment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 18</xref>), and these were unexpectedly among the most sensitive parameters in our model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figures 15 and 16</xref>).</p><p>We were able to introduce several new components and interactions into the clock circuit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>) using these constraints, starting from the revision of the evening loop. The effects of the <italic>GI</italic> gene on the clock are not completely understood. The L2006 model suggested that <italic>GI</italic> was part of the hypothetical component <italic>Y&#x02014;</italic>an activator of <italic>TOC1</italic> transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Locke et al, 2005</xref>). However, recent data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Kim et al, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Martin-Tryon et al, 2007</xref>) show that <italic>GI</italic> influences <italic>TOC1</italic> not on the transcriptional, but on the protein level. We, therefore, modified the structure of the evening loop by separating GI and Y functions in the model. Y increases <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA level, whereas GI decreases TOC1 protein level through stabilization of ZTL protein. The decreased TOC1 protein tends to relieve repression of <italic>Y</italic> by TOC1, acting in the evening negative feedback loop. Increased <italic>Y</italic> expression in turn activates <italic>TOC1</italic> expression. Both Y (directly) and GI (indirectly) activate <italic>TOC1</italic> expression in the model. This allows us to give a new explanation of the previous experimental data from the <italic>gi/lhy/cca1</italic> triple mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>), which show that the <italic>gi</italic> mutation reduces <italic>TOC1</italic> expression.</p><p>However, we included only one function of GI in the model. In addition to the interaction with ZTL, GI can function as a scaffold cofactor in the formation of multi-protein activator complexes at gene promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">Sawa et al, 2007</xref>). This raises the possibility that GI can also accelerate the expression of some clock genes, similarly to the hypothetical activation of <italic>TOC1</italic> by Y. Experimental data show a variation of the periods of <italic>gi</italic> mutant alleles from short to long compared with wt plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">Park et al, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Gould et al, 2006</xref>). The shortening of the period of some <italic>gi</italic> mutants was less pronounced in blue light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Martin-Tryon et al, 2007</xref>), which is necessary for GI&#x02013;ZTL interaction, suggesting that a perturbation of the GI&#x02013;ZTL interaction could be responsible for the longer period of <italic>gi</italic> alleles that cause amino-acid substitutions, such as <italic>gi-596</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Gould et al, 2006</xref>). This observation is consistent with the 2 h period lengthening of the simulated <italic>gi</italic> mutant relative to wt in our model (data not shown), which incorporated only the effect of the GI&#x02013;ZTL interaction upon the degradation of TOC1 protein. The short periods observed in other <italic>gi</italic> mutant alleles are possibly related with the loss of other functions of GI as a scaffold, which might affect protein targets other than TOC1. We do not yet have data to include this function of GI explicitly in the model, so only Y retained the function in transcriptional activation, and simulated <italic>y</italic> mutants had short periods in our model (data not shown), as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Locke et al (2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">2006</xref>).</p><p>We also used the model to study the ZTL effects on the clock. We showed that the long period of <italic>ztl</italic> mutant is related to changes in TOC1 protein levels. This is consistent with experimental data, which show that the main effect of ZTL is related with <italic>TOC1</italic>: the <italic>ztl/toc1</italic> double mutant has a short period close to the <italic>toc1</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Mas et al, 2003b</xref>). In addition to its effect on TOC1, ZTL is known to participate in the degradation of PRR5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Kiba et al, 2007</xref>), which is probably responsible for some part of NI activity. The potential for ZTL-like control of NI protein degradation was taken into consideration by increasing the rate of NI protein degradation in darkness, analogous to PRR9 and PRR7.</p><p>Our current understanding of the Arabidopsis clock leaves some open questions about the structure of the evening loop and its connection to the morning loop. Mostly, they are related with Y, the unknown <italic>TOC1</italic> transcriptional activator. The model predicts that the characteristic property of <italic>Y</italic> is its broad expression in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> double mutants in the daytime, which may allow identification of this gene in future. This profile is most obvious in long days, in which <italic>Y</italic> mRNA is predicted to rise to a second peak before dusk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2B</xref>). Another question is related with the multiple functions ascribed to TOC1. The data on <italic>TOC1</italic> co-expression with the transcription factor <italic>LUX</italic> in constant light, and short- and long-photoperiod conditions, as well as in multiple mutant backgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Hazen et al, 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">2005</xref>), suggest that some TOC1 functions in the model might be realized through LUX <italic>in vivo</italic>. New experimental data on <italic>LUX</italic> expression and LUX functions will be required to understand how LUX contributes to the evening loop and its connection to the morning loop of the clock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Hazen et al, 2005</xref>).</p><p>An important aspect of this study is related to regulation of the important morning components <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic>, which in turn control the expression of multiple genes with evening and morning elements in their promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">Harmer and Kay, 2005</xref>). The central function of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> in the clock may explain the precise regulation of their expression by multiple inhibitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">McClung, 2006</xref>). When the <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> profiles are altered, the phase of all other clock components is changed. Here, we introduced NI, an inhibitor of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression in the model, based on existing data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Nakamichi et al, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Pruneda-Paz et al, 2009</xref>).</p><p>Our model predicts that regulation of the wave of inhibitor proteins PRR9, PRR7 and NI by light is important for correct phasing of the clock. The simulated profiles of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression match our experimental data under multiple light conditions including various photoperiods, constant light conditions and in skeleton photoperiods, in which the clock is reset by &#x02018;dawn' and &#x02018;dusk' pulses of light. The model shows that the wave of inhibitors may contribute to the observed response of morning genes to the time of dusk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7B</xref>), whereas dusk sensitivity was previously ascribed only to the evening loop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>). The combined, <italic>PRR9/7</italic> gene of the L2006 model did not match either this dusk-responsive behaviour or the strong induction of <italic>PRR9</italic> observed at dawn, because the regulation of that single component represented a difficult compromise between the two patterns. Consequently, the morning loop in L2006 showed no response to changing photoperiods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Edwards et al, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>), and parameters of the <italic>PRR7/9</italic> component were the most sensitive in the model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>; Treenut Saithong and Millar, unpublished results). The L2006 model was also relatively slow to reach stable entrainment, because it lacked strong light activation of <italic>PRR9</italic> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>). The introduction of three inhibitor components (<italic>PRR9</italic>, <italic>PRR7</italic> and <italic>NI</italic>) instead of one (combined <italic>PRR7/9</italic>) greatly increased the flexibility of entrainment and the robustness of the present model to parameter changes, compared with the L2006 model. These advantages arise generically from the duplication and divergent regulation of clock components. Organisms with large genomes show this effect in clock gene families, such as the plant <italic>PRR</italic> genes and the mammalian <italic>Period</italic> genes, but other biochemical mechanisms could evolve to provide the same properties. The differential regulation of a single clock gene in distinct, though coupled, cells offers one alternative, as in Drosophila.</p><p>The model predicted that the initial phase of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> transcription in the late night depends on PRR7 and NI proteins, which are present at night. Such regulation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> would not result simply from the PRR9 protein profile, which falls at the start of the night (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Nakamichi et al, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>). Considering PRR5 as a candidate for NI based on previous data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Nakamichi et al, 2005</xref>), we investigated in more detail the effects of PRR7 and PRR5 on <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression. Our experimental data on the <italic>prr7</italic> and <italic>prr5</italic> single and <italic>prr7/prr5</italic> double mutant plants showed that both PRR7 and PRR5 are important for the higher induction of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> at dawn compared with dusk under skeleton photoperiods, in agreement with the model prediction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8</xref>). The higher level of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression at dusk in the <italic>prr7</italic> and <italic>prr7/prr5</italic> mutants was expected from published data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Farre et al, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Nakamichi et al, 2005</xref>). The increase of <italic>CCA1</italic> mRNA levels at dusk in <italic>prr5</italic> was not expected from previous data under normal photoperiods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Eriksson et al, 2003</xref>), emphasizing the usefulness of the skeleton photoperiod protocol in understanding the clock mechanisms. Thus, our data on <italic>prr7/prr5</italic> and <italic>prr5</italic> mutants confirm that PRR5 is a good candidate for NI. During revision of this manuscript, experimental results showing that PRR5 associates with and inhibits expression of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> further supported this hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Nakamichi et al, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Previous data showed that the <italic>prr7/prr5</italic> double mutant alters the entrained phase in normal photoperiods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Yamashino et al, 2008</xref>). Our model also shows a phase shift (data not shown), but the extent of the shift is dependent on the quantitative contributions and mutual regulation of the PRR genes, which cannot yet be defined from data. In addition, recent experimental data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Pruneda-Paz et al, 2009</xref>) show the inhibition of <italic>CCA1</italic> by another dusk-expressed gene, <italic>CHE</italic> (<italic>TCP21</italic>), the product of which interacts with TOC1 at the <italic>CCA1</italic> promoter. On the basis of these data we expect that PRR7 and PRR5 may work together with CHE protein at night in the inhibition specifically of <italic>CCA1</italic>. Thus, the NI component of our model may represent a protein complex with elements additional to PRR5.</p><p>The model simulations showed that, in addition to inhibitors, the activator TOC1<sub>mod</sub> has an impact on <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression by determining the amplitude of the <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA rhythm. The model predicts that TOC1 has two, coherent effects on <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression. As well as direct activation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic>, TOC1 inhibits activation of <italic>PRR9</italic> expression by LHY/CCA1, which further increases the amplitude of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>). Thus, inhibition of <italic>PRR9</italic> by TOC1 at night increases robustness of oscillations. In the morning, however, <italic>PRR9</italic> is quickly induced by light. The molecular mechanism of the switch from inhibition to activation at the <italic>PRR9</italic> promoter is unknown. In our model, we assumed that the acute induction of <italic>PRR9</italic> expression by light through protein P does not depend on TOC1, allowing a robust acute induction of <italic>PRR9</italic> by both pulses of light in the skeleton photoperiods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8C</xref>). However, the observed <italic>PRR9</italic> response to the &#x02018;dusk' pulse of light is smaller than the response to the &#x02018;dawn' pulse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8D</xref>). This would be consistent with some minor inhibition of <italic>PRR9</italic> light induction by TOC1. Future studies of the protein complexes at the <italic>PRR9</italic> promoter will allow a more detailed description of <italic>PRR9</italic> inhibition by TOC1 and the competition between TOC1 and light activation for the <italic>PRR9</italic> promoter.</p><p>The model emphasises that <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> regulation must switch from inhibition by PRR9, PRR7 and PRR5 in the early night to activation by TOC1<sub>mod</sub> in the late night, but the molecular mechanism of this switch is unknown. One possible scenario is that the function of CHE, and perhaps other similar DNA-binding proteins, is modulated through binding of different effectors, such as PRR proteins other than TOC1 (PRR1). In that case, competition between PRR proteins that inhibit or activate <italic>CCA1</italic> might also be important in the modulation of the morning loop by evening components. Thus, our approach both highlights general principles of circadian circuits and also focuses experimental work, from introducing an inhibitory function for PRR5 to considering how this function must end in the night.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Computational and experimental methods are described in detail in Supplementary information.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d31e26" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Supplementary information, Supplementary figures S2&#x02013;19</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-s1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d31e32" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-s2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d31e35" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-s3.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d31e38" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>SBML model</title><p><italic>The version of this supplementary SBML file originally posted online on 21 September 2010 contained minor errors due to the use of the name "time" in the light function and the parameter "default". These errors have  been corrected by substitution of "time" with "t" and "default" with "def" and the file replaced on 22 November 2010.</italic>
</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-s4.xml" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="xml"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by BBSRC awards E015263 and F005466. The Centre for Systems Biology at Edinburgh is a Centre for Integrative and Systems Biology supported by BBSRC and EPSRC award D019621. This work has made use of the resources provided by the Edinburgh Compute and Data Facility (ECDF). The ECDF is partially supported by the eDIKT initiative. We are grateful to the Edinburgh Parallel Computing Centre (EPCC; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epcc.ed.ac.uk/">http://www.epcc.ed.ac.uk/</ext-link>) for computing time on their BlueGene/L service.</p><p><italic>Author contributions</italic>: AP, SKH, KK, KDE and AJM designed experiments; SKH, KK, KDE and AWT performed experiments; TM supplied biological materials; AP, KS and AJM designed computational analysis; AP and KS performed computational analysis; AP and AJM wrote the paper with comments from all authors.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Covington</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maloof</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Straume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Global transcriptome analysis reveals circadian regulation of key pathways in plant growth and development</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>R130</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18710561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sugano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>CK2 phosphorylation of CCA1 is necessary for its circadian oscillator function in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>3292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14978263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salathia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kevei</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Plant circadian clocks increase photosynthesis, growth, survival, and competitive advantage</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akman</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lumsden</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pokhilko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kozma-Bognar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Quantiatiave analysis of regulatory flexibility under changing environmental conditions</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> (in press)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salathia</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Straume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>FLOWERING LOCUS C mediates natural variation in the high-temperature response of the Arabidopsis circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Response regulator homologues have complementary, light-dependent functions in the Arabidopsis circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>218</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12955513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Farre</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Overlapping and distinct roles of PRR7 and PRR9 in the Arabidopsis circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15649364</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Farre</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PRR7 protein levels are regulated by light and the circadian clock in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>548</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17877705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Finkenstadt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Komorowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Reconstruction of transcriptional dynamics from gene reporter data using differential equations</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>2901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2907</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larue</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moyle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Putterill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The molecular basis of temperature compensation in the Arabidopsis circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16617099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gutenkunst</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waterfall</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sethna</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Universally sloppy parameter sensitivities in systems biology models</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1871</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17922568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Positive and negative factors confer phase-specific circadian regulation of transcription in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1926</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15923346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Hazen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borevitz</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mapping LUX ARRHYTHMO, a novel myb transcription factor essential for circadian rhythms, and other circadian clock mutants by oligonucleotide array genotyping</article-title>. In <italic>15th International Conference on Arabidopsis Research</italic>. Berlin, Germany</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hazen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borevitz</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>LUX ARRHYTHMO encodes a Myb domain protein essential for circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>10387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16006522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamichi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Rhythmic and light-inducible appearance of clock-associated pseudo-response regulator protein PRR9 through programmed degradation in the dark in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17890242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamichi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsushika</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujimori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Molecular dissection of the promoter of the light-induced and circadian-controlled APRR9 gene encoding a clock-associated component of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15725665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Targeted degradation of PSEUDO-RESPONSE REGULATOR5 by an SCFZTL complex regulates clock function and photomorphogenesis in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2516</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17693530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>David</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Putterill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>ZEITLUPE is a circadian photoreceptor stabilized by GIGANTEA in blue light</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>449</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17704763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Le Novere</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broicher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Courtot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donizelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dharuri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sauro</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schilstra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snoep</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hucka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>BioModels database: a free, centralized database of curated, published, quantitative kinetic models of biochemical and cellular systems</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>D689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kozma-Bognar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kevei</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Experimental validation of a predicted feedback loop in the multi-oscillator clock of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17102804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kozma-Bognar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Extension of a genetic network model by iterative experimentation and mathematical analysis</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>2005</fpage> 0013<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16729048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsushika</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The APRR1/TOC1 quintet implicated in circadian rhythms of Arabidopsis thaliana: I. Characterization with APRR1-overexpressing plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11828023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mangan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alon</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Structure and function of the feed-forward loop network motif</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>11980</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11985</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martin-Tryon</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kreps</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>GIGANTEA acts in blue light signaling and has biochemically separable roles in circadian clock and flowering time regulation</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alabadi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2003a</year>) <article-title>Dual role of TOC1 in the control of circadian and photomorphogenic responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12509533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2003b</year>) <article-title>Targeted degradation of TOC1 by ZTL modulates circadian function in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>426</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsushika</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Circadian waves of expression of the APRR1/TOC1 family of pseudo-response regulators in Arabidopsis thaliana: insight into the plant circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1002</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11100772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Plant circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16595397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Enhancer trapping reveals widespread circadian clock transcriptional control in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mockler</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McEntee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trout</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hazen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Givan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Network discovery pipeline elucidates conserved time-of-day-specific cis-regulatory modules</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18248097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A suite of photoreceptors entrains the plant circadian clock</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12828279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wheatley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carre</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>LHY and CCA1 are partially redundant genes required to maintain circadian rhythms in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamichi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>PSEUDO-RESPONSE REGULATORS 9, 7, and 5 are transcriptional repressors in the Arabidopsis circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>594</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20233950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamichi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis pseudo-response regulators, PRR5 and PRR7, coordinately play essential roles for circadian clock function</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>619</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15695441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soh</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Control of circadian rhythms and photoperiodic flowering by the Arabidopsis GIGANTEA gene</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>1579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10477524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pittendrigh</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>A functional analysis of circadian pacemakers in nocturnal rodents</article-title>. <source>J Comp Physiol</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Para</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A functional genomics approach reveals CHE as a component of the Arabidopsis circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>323</volume>: <fpage>1481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19286557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nusinow</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>FKF1 and GIGANTEA complex formation is required for day-length measurement in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>318</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17872410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yakir</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hilman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hassidim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED1 transcript stability and the entrainment of the circadian clock in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17873091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yakir</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hilman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hassidim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melamed-Book</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Posttranslational regulation of CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED1 in the circadian oscillator of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>844</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19339503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kunihiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamichi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Involvement of Arabidopsis clock-associated pseudo-response regulators in diurnal oscillations of gene expression in the presence of environmental time cues</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><ref-list><title>Synopsis only</title><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bell-Pedersen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cassone</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Earnest</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hardin</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zoran</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Circadian rhythms from multiple oscillators: lessons from diverse organisms</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15951747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loros</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The neurospora circadian system</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>414</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15534321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The main elements of the extended Arabidopsis circadian clock model. The previous circuit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>) is shown, upper right. Elements of the morning and evening oscillators are shown in yellow and grey, respectively. For clarity, proteins are shown only for ZTL, LHY modified (LHY<sub>mod</sub>) and TOC1 modified (TOC1<sub>mod</sub>). Genetic interactions, solid arrows; post-translational regulation, dashed arrows. Light inputs to gene transcription are marked by flashes. The full scheme of the model is presented in SBGN format in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Regulation of the evening components <italic>Y</italic> and <italic>TOC1</italic> by photoperiods. Simulated expression profiles of <italic>Y</italic> (blue lines) and <italic>TOC1</italic> (black lines) mRNA in wt (<bold>A</bold>) and <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> mutant (<bold>B</bold>) plants are shown for 6L:18D (dotted lines); 12L:12D (solid lines) and 18L:6D (dashed lines). (<bold>C</bold>) Dependence of peak <italic>TOC1</italic> phase on the day length in wt plants. Simulations are shown by a line and the experimental data points for the peak phase of <italic>TOC1:LUC</italic> reporter expression are taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Edwards et al (2010)</xref>. The level of each clock component in the model is normalized to its maximum level in 12L:12D (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Importance of <italic>PRR9</italic> inhibition by TOC1 for high-amplitude oscillations of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> in constant light. Simulated profiles of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA (black lines) and PRR9 protein (magenta lines) are shown for wild-type plants (solid lines) and for a simulated partial <italic>toc1</italic> mutant that specifically lacks <italic>PRR9</italic> inhibition by TOC1 (dashed lines).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Mechanism of ZTL function under LL conditions. Simulated profiles for wild-type and <italic>ztl</italic> mutant plants are shown by solid and dashed lines, respectively. (<bold>A</bold>) TOC1 protein; (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA (black) and TOC1<sub>mod</sub> protein (green).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Mechanism of <italic>TOC1</italic> regulation by GI. The predicted (<bold>A</bold>) and experimental (<bold>B</bold>) profiles of <italic>TOC1</italic> expression in <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> double and <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> triple mutants. Green lines correspond to <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> and red lines to <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic>. (A) <italic>TOC1</italic> mRNA expression is shown by solid lines and the total content of ZTL protein is shown by dashed lines. (B) Bioluminescence of transgenic mutant plants carrying the <italic>TOC1:LUC</italic> reporter, in the <italic>lhy/cca1</italic> double and <italic>lhy/cca1/gi</italic> triple mutant backgrounds (taken from our previous data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Locke et al, 2006</xref>)).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-f5"/></fig><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Regulation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression by the wave of inhibitors and the activator TOC1<sub>mod</sub>. Simulations are shown during 12L:12D entrainment of wild-type plants. <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA is shown by the black line. Inhibitor proteins PRR9, PRR7 and NI are shown by dashed magenta, green and blue lines, respectively. TOC1<sub>mod</sub> is shown by the brown line. Experimental data on <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> expression are shown by filled squares (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Edwards et al, 2010</xref>) and open squares (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Farre et al, 2005</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-f6"/></fig><fig id="f7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Regulation of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> phase. Simulations are shown under entrainment of wild-type plants to various photoperiods. (<bold>A</bold>) Simulated profiles of <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA (black) and NI protein (blue) are shown for 6L:18D (solid lines), 12L:12D (dotted lines) and 18L:6D (dashed lines). (<bold>B</bold>) Experimental data on <italic>CCA1</italic> mRNA for 6L:18D, 12L:12D and 18L:6D entrainment were taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Edwards et al (2010)</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-f7"/></fig><fig id="f8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Theoretical and experimental profiles of clock components during skeleton entrainment. Plants were transferred from 12L:12D to skeleton entrainment with &#x02018;dawn' and &#x02018;dusk' pulses of light, each of 3 h duration (3L:6D:3L:12D), at time 0 h in simulations (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>C</bold>, <bold>E</bold>) and experiments (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>, <bold>F&#x02013;H</bold>). Black lines correspond to simulated <italic>LHY/CCA1</italic> mRNA in wild-type (A) or <italic>prr7/ni</italic> double mutants (E), or normalized luminescence from transgenic <italic>CCA1:LUC</italic> plants in wild-type (B) or <italic>prr7/prr5</italic> (F), <italic>prr7</italic> (H) or <italic>prr5</italic> (G) mutant backgrounds. (A) Simulated levels of inhibitor proteins PRR7 and NI in wild type are shown by green and blue lines. (C) Simulated levels of <italic>PRR9</italic> mRNA are shown by the magenta line. Normalized luminescence from wild-type <italic>PRR9:LUC</italic> plants is shown in panel D. Luminescence data represent the mean of data from 9 to 18 individual plants, in which each plant's trace was normalized to the mean luminescence level for the plant. Data shown are representative of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201069-f8"/></fig></floats-group></article>