<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Syst Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Syst Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Systems Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1752-0509</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23705851</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3668293</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1752-0509-7-41</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-7-41</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Computational modelling of the regulation of Insulin signalling by oxidative stress</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Graham R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>graham.smith3@newcastle.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A2"><name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>Daryl P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>daryl.shanley@newcastle.ac.uk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Centre for Integrated Systems Biology of Ageing &#x00026; Nutrition (CISBAN), Institute for Ageing and Health, Newcastle University, Campus for Ageing and Vitality, Newcastle upon Tyne NE4 5PL, UK</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013 Smith and Shanley; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Smith and Shanley; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1752-0509/7/41"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Existing models of insulin signalling focus on short term dynamics, rather than the longer term dynamics necessary to understand many physiologically relevant behaviours. We have developed a model of insulin signalling in rodent adipocytes that includes both transcriptional feedback through the Forkhead box type O (FOXO) transcription factor, and interaction with oxidative stress, in addition to the core pathway. In the model Reactive Oxygen Species are both generated endogenously and can be applied externally. They regulate signalling though inhibition of phosphatases and induction of the activity of Stress Activated Protein Kinases, which themselves modulate feedbacks to insulin signalling and FOXO.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Insulin and oxidative stress combined produce a lower degree of activation of insulin signalling than insulin alone. Fasting (nutrient withdrawal) and weak oxidative stress upregulate antioxidant defences while stronger oxidative stress leads to a short term activation of insulin signalling but if prolonged can have other effects including degradation of the insulin receptor substrate (IRS1) and FOXO. At high insulin the protective effect of moderate oxidative stress may disappear.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our model is consistent with a wide range of experimental data, some of which is difficult to explain. Oxidative stress can have effects that are both up- and down-regulatory on insulin signalling. Our model therefore shows the complexity of the interaction between the two pathways and highlights the need for such integrated computational models to give insight into the dysregulation of insulin signalling along with more data at the individual level.</p><p>A complete SBML model file can be downloaded from BIOMODELS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels-main">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels-main</ext-link>) with unique identifier MODEL1212210000.</p><p>Other files and scripts are available as additional files with this journal article and can be downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/graham1034/Smith2012_insulin_signalling">https://github.com/graham1034/Smith2012_insulin_signalling</ext-link>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Insulin signalling</kwd><kwd>FOXO</kwd><kwd>Oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>Kinetic computational modelling</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Nutrient response signalling pathways are activated in response to feeding and control such aspects of an organism&#x02019;s response to feeding as satiety and the generation, consumption and storage of energy. They also control the allocation of energy and biological substrates to somatic growth, maintenance and repair, and so implicitly underlie theories of ageing such as the Disposable Soma Theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] which are based on the idea of trade-offs between these processes. In the animal kingdom the insulin-signalling (IS) pathway is of particular importance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Dietary sugars trigger the production of insulin or insulin-like peptides which are sensed by Insulin receptors at the cell surface and initiate a kinase cascade, leading to the activation of the downstream kinase Akt (PKB), the translocation of GLUT4 glucose transporters to the cell surface, and ultimately glucose uptake. Longer-term adaptive effects are controlled through transcription factors such as FOXO, which is deactivated (via cytoplasmic translocation) by Akt-mediated phosphorylation when IS is active [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. When active, FOXO transcribes genes regulating cell cycle arrest, apoptosis, metabolism and maintenance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Animal lifespan may be increased by nutrient restriction in many animals including nematodes, flies and mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], at least in part through the decrease in activity of IS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In addition to its role in ageing, dysregulation of IS is central in metabolic diseases such as Type II Diabetes (T2D).</p><p>Oxidative stress is an inescapable concomitant of the life of aerobic organisms, given that reactive oxygen species (ROS) are produced by energy generation by oxidative phosphorylation in mitochondria. ROS can damage all main categories of biomolecule including DNA, protein and lipids. Accordingly, organisms protect themselves by the production of many classes of antioxidant enzymes, including superoxide dismutase and catalase (that catalyse reactions that lead ultimately to the conversion of ROS to water), and thioredoxins and peroxiredoxins (that use reversible oxidation of sulphydryl groups to remove ROS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The extent of cellular resistance to oxidative stress varies between organisms and closely correlates with lifespan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], and in the free radical theory of ageing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] the damage caused by ROS is hypothesised to be the primary cause of age-related degeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Notwithstanding this, recent studies have tended to emphasise that the levels of antioxidant enzymes do not correlate with lifespan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], and the effects of overexpression or knockout of antioxidants, or of dietary supplementation, are not always as might be expected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. In addition ROS activate several stress-activated protein kinases (SAPKs) such as JNK, IKK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] and p38 MAPK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The response of IS to oxidative stress is complicated by the fact that ROS has been co-opted into the active regulation of the pathway, ROS produced by NOX enzymes affecting IS immediately through the reversible oxidation and inhibition of the catalytic cysteine residues of the protein tyrosine phosphatases and lipid phosphatases that deactivate IS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. The effect of ROS on IS has also been strongly implicated in the development of metabolic disease such as T2D [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] and neurodegenerative disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p><p>Given the complicated nature of these two important processes and their interaction, especially the multiple countervailing effects of ROS, a quantitative model is essential to understand the biological consequences. In particular, the ability of a computational model to quantify multiple effects and study the effects of variation of experimentally-inaccessible parameters may be expected to lead to some insight. Motivated by this, we here present a kinetic computational model of IS in rodent adipocytes including FOXO and some FOXO-mediated outputs, and including interactions with ROS and some oxidative stress activated kinases. Previous modelling work on IS has focused on receptor binding, the activation of Akt and Glucose uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. In recent years it has expanded to include a more detailed description of Insulin-InR binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], integration with connected signalling pathways such as mTOR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>], EGF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], MAPK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] and whole-body insulin/glucose dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], though these aspects are not included in the model presented here. We have used work by Sedaghat et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] as the basis of our modelling of IS and integrated it with a model we previously developed of the regulation of the FOXO transcription factor by multiple post-translational modifications (PTMS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The role of stress-activated kinases JNK and IKK in regulating FOXO was already included in this model; here we have extended this to include their regulation of IS through phosphorylation of IRS. ROS is included in the model and leads to activation of SAPKs while also having a direct effect on IS through the phosphatase-dependent mechanism described above. In the model, insulin stimulation leads to signalling-induced ROS through NOX but not additional mitochondrially generated ROS resulting from glucose uptake (this would be an oversimplification in other tissues such as muscle, where mitochondrially generated ROS makes up a larger fraction of the total). Aspects of a recent model of the antioxidant system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] describing the transport of oxidants between the extracellular and cytoplasmic compartment were included; this enables connection with experiments in which oxidants (hydrogen peroxide) are externally applied. We develop a model integrating multiple experimental findings on the IS and oxidative stress systems and study its behaviour in scenarios of nutrient withdrawal, the simultaneous applications of Insulin and ROS, and the effects of low and high oxidative stress on insulin response.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The modules making up the model are shown diagrammatically in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, with outputs shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Molecule numbers are given in Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and kinetic parameters in Tables&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>. Differential equations are given in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>. Mass action kinetics are used for the majority of equations, except activation of Akt and PKC and JNK/IKK mediated feedbacks on IRS. The modules in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A-C make up the core insulin signalling pathway and Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A-C show its behaviour in response to insulin. ROS production and SAPK activation modules are described in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>D-E and their behaviour is shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>D-G. The FOXO module is shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>F and its behaviour in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>H.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Block diagrams of the model.</bold> (<bold>A</bold>): Insulin &#x02013; Insulin Receptor binding and InR activation; (<bold>B</bold>): IRS regulation by active InR, PKC, JNK and IKK and IRS &#x02013; PI3K binding; (<bold>C</bold>) downstream activation of Akt though the IRS&#x02013; PI3K complex and PIP3, and GLUT4 transport to the plasma membrane; (<bold>D</bold>) ROS production basally (by Mt) and insulin-stimulated (by NOX); ROS transport across the plasma membrane; ROS degradation by SOD2; inhibition of PTP and PTEN by ROS and reactivation by GSH; (<bold>E</bold>) activation of JNK and IKK by ROS; (<bold>F</bold>) FOXO regulation by Akt, JNK and IKK; FOXO synthesis and degradation; FOXO transport between compartments; transcriptional regulation of InR and SOD2 by FOXO. The presence of the PTMs applied to FOXO by the kinases affects the transport and degradation rates, as detailed in Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Short-term effects of insulin signalling and Oxidative stress.</bold> (<bold>A</bold>) Insulin (100 nM; dosing bar) activates Akt leading to Glut4 translocation and Glucose uptake (timecourses). Akt timecourse reproduces Sedaghat et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]; (<bold>B</bold>) Dose response curves for bound insulin, PI3K activation and Glucose uptake; data adapted from experiments by Stagstad et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] in rat adipocytes; (<bold>C</bold>) Insulin activates IRS through Tyrosine phosphorylation (IRS_Yp) and PKC inhibits through serine phosphorylation. (data adapted from experiments by Cedersund et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] in human adipocytes); (<bold>D</bold>) Endogenous ROS inhibits PTP1B (data adapted from experiments by Mahadev et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] in mouse 3T3-L1 adiopocytes); (<bold>E</bold>) Inhibition of NOX prevents oxidation-mediated inactivation of PTP1B and moves D-R curves of IS components to higher insulin concentrations; (<bold>F</bold>) Antioxidants control internal ROS until external ROS passes a threshold (calculations based on a model developed by Adimora et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] in human Jurkat T cells); (<bold>G</bold>) ROS activates JNK/IKK; (<bold>H</bold>) Insulin (through Akt) and ROS (through JNK) modulate FOXO subcellular localization.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Particle numbers in initial conditions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Module</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Species</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Initial value (number of molecules)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Comments &#x00026; References</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Receptor binding<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Ins<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>, boundary<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<sup>-7</sup>&#x000a0;M<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">InR<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">9&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">BioNumbers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cytoplasm_InR<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x0003c;&#x0003c; cell surface<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PTP1B<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assigned (PaxDb suggests PTPN1 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> in human, 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> in mouse) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pax-db.org">http://pax-db.org</ext-link> &#x00026;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] Appdx B<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI3K<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] Appdx B<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PP2A<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Phosphatases<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PTEN<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PaxDb, human<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">GSH<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">100<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assigned<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">NOX_inact<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">100<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assigned<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cytoplasm_SOD2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4.17&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">scale 10<sup>-3</sup> * PaxDb<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mt<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">50<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assigned<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">extracellular_ROS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup>, boundary<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">scale 10<sup>-3</sup> * 10 &#x003bc;M<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AS160<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assigned<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PKC<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assigned same as Akt<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PIP2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">scale 10<sup>-3</sup> *[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PIP3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">scale 10<sup>-3</sup> * [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">cytoplasm_GLUT4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">9.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Total 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>, assigned ((PaxDb suggests Slc2a4 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> in mouse)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">cellsurface_GLUT4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">JNK<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">JNK<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">16000<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PaxDB (Mapk9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IKK<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2000<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PaxDb (Ikbkb)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">DUSP<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assigned<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">FOXO<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">E2F1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">300<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assigned, to keep FOXO&#x02009;~&#x02009;1000<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">cytoplasm_Foxo1_Pa0 Pd0_Pe0_pUb0 (Foxo with no PTMs)</td><td align="left">1000</td><td align="left">see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>All other species are initially zero.</p><p>Initial particle numbers in the model (all other species are initially zero).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Parameter values of the model (except for FOXO part)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Module</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Reaction</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Name</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Parameter</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Value</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Order</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Comments &#x00026; Ref</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">All<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Volume<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">extracellular<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">8.3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-12</sup>&#x000a0;l<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;cytoplasm<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Volume<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">cell surface<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-14</sup>&#x000a0;l<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">assumes thickness of 20 nm<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Volume<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">cytoplasm<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.65&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-11</sup>&#x000a0;l<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">typical of many cells<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Volume<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">nucleus<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-13</sup>&#x000a0;l<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Volume<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">DNA-bound<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-13</sup>&#x000a0;l<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Receptor binding<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R1f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">m8b2_recep.6mod<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R1r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">12072<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2500<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R3f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R3r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">9&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x0003e;&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;kminus1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R5f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0333<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">forward/reverse ratio 10, much faster than [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R5r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">see R5f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R6f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k4&#x02019;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0021<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">unchanged from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R6r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus4&#x02019;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R7f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k4&#x02019;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0021<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R7r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus4&#x02019;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R10<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4.61&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] corrected for mol number of PTP1B<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R11<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4.61&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">see R10<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R12f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k7<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5.8<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">fitted to IRSYp<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">m8b2_irs.6.mod<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R12r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus7a<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">8.75&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R12f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R12_a_f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS-SerP by PKC_P<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kpsp2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">changed to simple MA; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] used for fitting<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R12_a_r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus7b<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.28&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R12_a_f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R12_b_(f,r)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R12_a_(f,r)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R13f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k8<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R13r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus8<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.55<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R13f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R50f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS basal synth<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k_irs1_basal_syn<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">260<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">increased to keep IRS1 const<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R50r1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS degrade<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k_irs_basal_degr<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<sup>-3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Lifetime of ~2&#x000a0;days<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R50r2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS-Yp degr<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k_irs_basal_degr<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<sup>-3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R50r2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R50r3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS1-Sp degr<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k_irs_polyserp_degr<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<sup>-2</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;faster than r50r2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R51<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS-SerP by IKK_P<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kcat51<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.87<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">consistent with [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] and IKK/JNK activation<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS-SerP by IKK_P<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Km51<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">100<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as above<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R52<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS-SerP by JNK_P<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kcat52<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6.95<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R51<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IRS-SerP by JNK_P<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Km52<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">100<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as above<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Phosphatases<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R30f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">oxidation of PTP1B<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k30f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.08<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">m8b2_phosph.6.mod<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R30r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">reduction of PTP1B by GSH<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k30r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R31f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">oxidation of PTEN<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k31f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.7&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">slower than R30f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R31r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">reduction of PTEN by GSH<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k31r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">similar to R30r<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R34f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Activation of NOX<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k34f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">consistent with R35<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R34r1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">NOX deactivation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k34r1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<sup>-3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">consistent with R35<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R34r2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">NOX inactivation(1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k34r2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.25<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">consistent with R35<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R34r3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">NOX deact-&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;inact<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k34r3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<sup>-3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">consistent with R35<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R35f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ROS production by NOX<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k35f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">450<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">fitted to get desired ROS level (30/5) and PTP1B inhibition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R35r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ROS elimination by SOD2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k35r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.12<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">lifetime&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;s<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R36f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ROS production by Mitoch<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k36f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">180<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R37f, R37r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ROS transport across plasma membrane<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ros_perm<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7.8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>8</sup> (thousands cm<sup>-2</sup>min<sup>-1</sup>)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">membrane_area<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-9</sup>&#x000a0;cm<sup>2</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">from volume<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k_ros_perm<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4.8 thousands min<sup>-1</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">product of above<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R38f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Glutathione oxidation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k38f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.05<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">see R38f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R38r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Glutathione reduction<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k38r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">(auto-reduction)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R14f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI(3,4,5)P3 generation, basal<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k9_basal<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.13145<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">m8b2_akt.6.mod<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">By PI3K complex<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k9<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.055<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">derived from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R14r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PIP3 breakdown, basal<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus9_basal<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.7<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">by PTEN<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus9<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0014<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R16f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt activation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k11<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">modified mass action, effect similar to express in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pip3_basal<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">200<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">offset<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R16r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt deactivation by PP2A<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus11<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.188&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R17f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PKC activation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k12<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R16f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R17r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PKC deactivation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus12<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.25&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R16r<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R16a<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AS160 activation by AKT<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kr16a<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3.33&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">see methods; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R16r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AS160 deactivation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminusr16a<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">see R16a<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R20f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">GLUT4 translocation to cell surface; basal<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k13_basal<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.015<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">see R16a<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">and by AS160<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">see R16a<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R20r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">GLUT4 translocation to cytoplasm<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">kminus13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.167<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">see R16a<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">JNK<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R32f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">DUSP oxidation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k32f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">consistent with [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">m8b2_jnk.6.mod<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R32r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">DUSP reduction by GSH<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k32r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R32f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R42f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">JNK activation by ROS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k42f<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R32f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R42r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">JNK deactivation by DUSP<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k42r<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R32f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R43f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IKK activation by ROS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">k43f<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (cat)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">as R32f<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">R43r</td><td align="left">IKK deactivation</td><td align="left">k43r</td><td align="left">0.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup></td><td align="left">2 (cat)</td><td align="left">as R32f</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup> k42f expressed as &#x003b1;&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;k42f&#x02019; where &#x003b1;&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 and k42f&#x02019;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup>.</p><p>(phosphatases, Akt, JNK, FOXO).</p><p>Kinetic parameters of the model, except for the FOXO components. Units of rate constants are min-1 for first order or (number)-1 min-1 for second order.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>FOXO parameters for synthesis, degradation, transport and PTMs</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Process</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>2</bold><sup><bold>o </bold></sup><bold>rate constant (#min</bold><sup><bold>-1</bold></sup><bold>)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Enzyme</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Enz #</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>1</bold><sup><bold>o </bold></sup><bold>rate const (min</bold><sup><bold>-1</bold></sup><bold>)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>PTM modifying rate</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Rate MF</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Reference</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Synthesis (NULL&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;FOXO)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0055<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">E2F1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">300<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cytoplasm&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;nuclear transport<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1/0.55&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.182<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt-Phos Pa<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IKK-Phos Pd<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">JNK-Phos Pe<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Nuclear&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;cytoplasm transport<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.55&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.055<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt-Phos Pa<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IKK-phos Pd<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">JNK-Phos Pe<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Nuclear&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;DNAbound transport<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.25<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt-Phos Pa<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] Figure 6B<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">DNAbound&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;Nuclear transport<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.25&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.5&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.125<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">basal phosphorylation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">basal dephosphorylation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">akt_phos_<break/>factor<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">ikk phos_factor<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">jnk phos_factor<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">FOXO&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;FOXO_Pa<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">akt phos_factor&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;basal phosphorylation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">(10<sup>4</sup>)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>C<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">FOXO_Pa&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;FOXO<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">basal dephosphorylation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PP2A<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">FOXO&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;FOXO_Pd<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ikk phos_factor&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;basal phosphorylation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IKK<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">(10<sup>4</sup>)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">FOXO_Pd&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;FOXO<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">basal dephosphorylation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PP2A<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">FOXO&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;FOXO_Pe<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">jnk phos_factor&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;basal phosphorylation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">JNK<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">(10<sup>4</sup>)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">FOXO_Pe&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;FOXO<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">basal dephosphorylation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PP2A<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">FOXO&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;FOXO_pUb<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-6</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">SCF/MDM2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<sup>3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<sup>-3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>; also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Akt (Pa)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IKK (Pd)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">22<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] Figure 5F<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Degradation (FOXO_pUb&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;NULL)</td><td align="left">1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup></td><td align="left">Proteasome</td><td align="left">10<sup>3</sup></td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Kinetic parameters of the FOXO module of the model. Where a second-order rate constant is given and the Enzyme is time-varying, the Enz # and first order rate constant columns show typical values when the process is activated. The PTM modifying rate refers to the way modifiable species are implemented in this system: if the PTM is present, then the basal rate for the process (in the 1o rate column) is multiplied by the entry in the Rate MF (Multiplicative Factor) column.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Parameters for FOXO mediated transcription</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Protein</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>FOXO- simulated transcription k</bold><sub><bold>transl</bold></sub></th><th align="left"><bold>Basal transcription k</bold><sub><bold>basalt</bold></sub></th><th align="left"><bold>RNA export k</bold><sub><bold>exp</bold></sub></th><th align="left"><bold>RNA degradation k</bold><sub><bold>mdeg</bold></sub></th><th align="left"><bold>RNA translation k</bold><sub><bold>transl</bold></sub></th><th align="left"><bold>Protein degradation k</bold><sub><bold>pdeg</bold></sub></th><th align="left"><bold>Ref</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">InR<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.24<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5.0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.22<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5.622<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.46<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4.4&#x000d7; 10<sup>-3</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">SOD2</td><td align="left">0.95</td><td align="left">15.0</td><td align="left">0.22</td><td align="left">5.622</td><td align="left">1.23</td><td align="left">1.9&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-3</sup></td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Parameters for transcription, transport, translation and degradation of the FOXO-regulated InR and SOD2 genes and proteins.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>Model development and parameter estimation</title><sec><title>Insulin signalling</title><p>The parameters in the insulin signalling pathway itself were arrived at as follows. Model development was started with the model in Sedaghat et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] as a basis, but was substantially refitted in the light of the timecourse of PTP1B inhibition and extra data. Various sources were used to obtain particle numbers, particularly PaxDb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. In the receptor binding module, insulin binding and unbinding (k1 and kminus1) were fitted using data on bound insulin in rat adipocytes from Stagsted et al. Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1 </xref>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. In the IRS module k7 and kminus7 were fitted to IRS_tyrosine phosphorylation data in human adipocytes from Cedersund et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] to get the rapid rise. k8 and k-8, the rate constants for Reaction 13, the formation of the IRS-PI3K complex, were fitted to PI3K activation kinetics from Stagsted et al. Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3 </xref>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], with the additional information that max PI3K&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05 of total [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Parameters of PIP3 production and degradation were fitted to give PIP3 activation on a timescale of 30s, rising from 0.003 (basal) to 0.03 (maximum stimulated) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Parameters of Akt and PKC activation (reactions R16 and R17) were chosen to give maximum insulin-stimulated Akt and PKC phosphorylation&#x02009;=&#x02009;10% of total after 2 minutes. The exact time is uncertain given the data used here but must be rapid to enable parameters of IRS &#x02013; serine phosphorylation (in R12af) to produce the observed feedback inhibition of IRS1. In the rate law, an offset to the mass-action dependence on PIP3 was used to give zero Akt/PKC activation below the basal PIP3 level (parameter pip3_basal; see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). Glucose uptake is proxied by cell surface GLUT4, and so GLUT4 parameters were chosen so that a fraction 0.1 of GLUT4 is located at the cell surface basally, and 0.6 at maximum. The fact that GLUT4 is not entirely surface located at its maximum, but this maximum must occur at a lower Insulin concentration than the peak activation of PI3K (and Akt) activation, necessitates the addition of AS160 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>] between Akt and GLUT4 (otherwise, the further activation of PI3K produces more GLUT4 translocation). AS160 is fully activated by partial activation of Akt, at an Insulin concentration of around 1 nM, but even when fully activated leads to only a partial translocation of GLUT4.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Long term effects and effects of inter-subsystem interactions (A) Fasting; Insulin receptors are upregulated during a fast (left panel).</bold> Insulin is applied for 15 minutes at the beginning and end of the two-day period (dosing bars at t&#x02009;=&#x02009;0 and t&#x02009;=&#x02009;2785 in left panel) producing the effect on the Insulin dose&#x02013;response curve at the end of the fasting period shown in the right panel; (<bold>B</bold>) Interaction of Insulin Stimulation and Oxidative stress; Insulin activates glucose uptake strongly; oxidative stress activates it weakly, but reduces the effect of insulin. Data adapted from experiments by Archuleta et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] in rat skeletal muscle; (<bold>C</bold>) Low oxidative stress increase antioxidant defence, high oxidative stress decreases it. Data adapted from experiments by Essers et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] in human DLD1 human colon carcinoma cells. Both simulation and experiment at t&#x02009;=&#x02009;960&#x000a0;min (16 h) after exposure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>ROS production and signalling</title><p>Insulin stimulation is associated with the production of ROS (hydrogen peroxide) intracellularly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] and it has been shown in experiments on mouse 3T3-L1 adipocytes that this involves the activation of NOX in a way independent of downstream components of IS that are downstream of IRS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] Accordingly we include NOX activated directly by Insulin, the NOX passing spontaneously into a deactivated state from which it only slowly returns to the inactive state (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1A). The NOX-generated ROS is about fivefold above the background level of Mitochondrially-generated ROS (qualitative data from Mahadev et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1A)) and decays in about 10 min.</p><p>It is difficult to quantify the difference between the background and Ins-stimulated ROS production in Mahadev et al.; it has been taken that the NOX generated ROS is about 5&#x000d7; the background level of Mt-generated ROS, and that even the NOX-generated ROS is low enough that JNK activation by insulin is very low, enough to maintain Akt-control of FOXO localization under insulin stimulation. The parameters k30f, k30r and k35f were varied to fit the timecourse of Insulin-stimulated PTP deactivation in 3T3-L1 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] and reactivation in human A431 carcinoma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. K35f is essential for a good fit.</p><p>Inhibition of PTEN by ROS is much weaker but occurs at high cytoplasmic ROS levels in 3T3 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] and human neuroblastoma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>].</p><p>ROS transport into and out of the cell was based on the work reported in Adimora et al. in Jurkat T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. The differences in the effect of membrane permeability, SOD2 concentration and basal ROS production are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1C-E. We remark that the molecule numbers of the ROS species in the model are scaled such that each represents 1000 real molecules (the same is true of the cytoplasmic SOD2 and PIP2/3 species).</p><p>JNK and IKK are activated by ROS directly, and by ROS deactivating the DUSP that reverses the SAPK activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>], and deactivating the GSH that reactivates the DUSP (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>E). The timescale of this activation is about one hour in response to external ROS in Fao cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The effects of ROS on activation of JNK and IKK were arranged to reproduce the data from DLD1 cells (human colon carcinoma) in Essers et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]; with the attribution of the inhibition at high oxidative stress to IKK- mediated degradation of FOXO (measured in 293T and MCF-7 cells by Hu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]). IKK and JNK also lead to degradation of IRS1 through serine phosphorylation (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1B). Michaelis-Menten rate laws were used for these phosphorylation reactions.</p></sec><sec><title>FOXO</title><p>The FOXO model was extended based on previous work, using the same approach of scripting to generate the species and reactions required to describe the multiple FOXO species with all allowed combinations of PTMs. Compared to the previous paper, acetylation and modifications by AMPK were omitted, but modifications by Akt observed in CCL39 fibroblasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], by JNK in DL23 cells (related to DLD-1 human colon carcinoma) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>] and by IKK in 293T human kidney and MCF-7 human breast cancer cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] were included, with Akt modification altering translocation (measured in CV1 African green monkey kidney fibroblasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]), opposed by JNK (measured in human endothelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>] and DLD1 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]), and with the modifications by Akt and IKK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] modulating degradation (for Akt, measured in HepG2 human liver carcinoma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]). The model of transcription and translation was based originally on one of the effect of osmotic stress on yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>], but some parameters are substantially different. With the mass-action laws, the fold-change on upregulation is dependent only on the number of DNA-bound FOXO molecules and the FOXO-stimulated and basal transcription rates, with the other parameters affecting the final absolute protein and mRNA levels and the timescales. The timescale of protein regulation is several hours while the timescale of mRNA up- or down-regulation is taken as being much more rapid than this (tens of minutes); given this, it has little effect on the timescale of protein regulation. Transcriptional parameters were tuned so that SOD2 and InR showed stable cycles under physiological insulin variation (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>: Figure S2).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Model simulations</title><p>The model reproduces previously calculated time courses of downstream activation in response to high insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A) and the corresponding observed dose&#x02013;response curves to insulin, which were taken from experiments on rat adipocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>](Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B). We use GLUT4 cell surface localization as a proxy for glucose uptake throughout. It will be noted that it is found experimentally that insulin-stimulated glucose uptake reaches saturation before either the Insulin receptors are fully occupied or the downstream kinases are fully active [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], though (at least in muscle) at this maximum only about 60% of GLUT4 receptors are at the cell surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. It was found difficult to reproduce these observations with the original model architecture, where Akt activation and GLUT4 translocation are described by algebraic expressions depending on PIP3 levels; moreover, it was felt preferable to use differential equations to describe all reactions. By the introduction of an additional species, AS160, which mediates between Akt and GLUT4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>], it was possible to obtain the dose&#x02013;response curve in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B while still maintaining the fractional activations both in the unstimulated and fully stimulated states.</p><sec><title>Signalling and feedback through IRS1</title><p>The insulin receptor substrate IRS1 is phosphorylated on multiple serine as well as tyrosine residues, and the serine phosphorylations tend to have the effect of reducing downstream signalling, by reducing the rate of tyrosine phosphorylation and reducing the extent to which a jointly Ser and Tyr phosphorylated IRS can signal to PI3K [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>] or interact with the insulin receptor InR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>], though the details are complex and not fully elucidated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. We have included a single &#x0201c;composite&#x0201d; modification, IRS_PolySerP which may be present with or without Tyr phosphorylation (so there are four IRS species in the model, IRS1, IRS1_PolySerP, IRS1_TyrP and IRS1_TyrP_PolySerP, the latter representing IRS phosphorylated on both Ser and Tyr; this latter was not included in the Sedaghat model, although the others werer); IRS_PolySerP may be produced by SAPKs and the activated form of PKC (representing the PKC-&#x003b6; isoform, activated by IS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>]). The rates of PKC modification were set by fitting data of the timecourse of IRS tyrosine phosphorylation from human adipocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The Serine phosphorylation by PKC is a simple representation in the model of the negative feedback loop that stabilizes the basal response of insulin signalling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>]. The result is the model IRS tyrosine phosphorylation timecourse of Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C: initially it rises, within the first minute of insulin stimulation; then as PKC becomes active (after about 5 minutes) and produces serine phosphorylated forms of IRS, which do not signal downstream, IRS_TypP declines again.</p><p>Serine phosphorylation is also thought under many circumstances to lead to accelerated degradation of IRS1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>], though this may depend on the kinases involved and on which and how many IRS1 sites are modified. Therefore we have extended the Sedaghat model by introducing synthesis and degradation reactions for the various IRS species, and have taken the Ser-p to result in accelerated degradation of IRS1 by a factor of 10, which is consistent with data for long-term insulin stimulation in rat hepatoma (H4IIE) cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>].</p><p>IRS is also serine phosphorylated by the SAPKs, JNK and IKK in CHO and HEK 293 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>], 3T3-L1 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>] and Fao rat hepatoma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]; reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. We have selected the rates of phosphorylation by these kinases so that IRS can be degraded on a timescale of about 4&#x02013;6&#x000a0;hours; the outcome is shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1B.</p></sec><sec><title>ROS interactions</title><p>ROS production, detoxification and signalling in the cell is an extremely complex process and the model used here (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>D and E) is much simplified. Only a &#x0201c;generic&#x0201d; ROS species representing superoxide or hydrogen peroxide is represented. Correspondingly, a single detoxifying enzyme, called SOD2, is included, which removes this in one step.</p><p>The direct interactions of oxidative stress with IS occur via the phosphatases PTEN and PTP1B. The insulin signal is transduced by tyrosine phosphorylation (in the Insulin receptor and IRS) and lipid phosphorylation (of PIP2 to PIP3), processes which are reversed by phosphatases (PTP1B and PTEN) that contain vital cysteine residues. These catalytic cysteines can be reversibly oxidised by ROS, inactivating the enzyme. Indeed, they are more susceptible to oxidation than the majority of protein cysteines precisely because they are in a protein environment that lowers their pKa in order to give them their catalytic property. Accordingly, ROS is produced by NOX enzymes in response to Insulin, facilitating the activation of IS (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>D). Detailed studies in 3T3-L1 adipocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] have revealed the extent of ROS production by NOX, and also that it deactivates after a few minutes despite continuous Insulin stimulation. The resultant ROS-mediated phosphatase inactivation is shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>D; it is apparent that more than half the PTP is deactivated. PTEN behaves similarly but more weakly; it is not appreciably deactivated by insulin-stimulated ROS. Kinetics of NOX are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1A. The phosphatases are reactivated on a timescale of 2&#x02013;5&#x000a0;minutes in A431 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] (the rate depends on glutathione (GSH), which can itself be oxidised by high ROS, although insulin signalling alone does not appreciably reduce the availability of glutathione). The effect of the PTP inhibition is to increase the sensitivity of insulin signalling, moving the GLUT4 dose&#x02013;response curve to lower Insulin concentrations. This can be seen by setting NOX&#x02009;=&#x02009;0 (equivalent to inhibiting it, e.g. with DPI, or introducing a large excess of antioxidants), which produces a decrease in sensitivity (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>E).</p><p>ROS in the model is removed by cytoplasmic SOD2, the activity of which ensures ROS decays on a timescale of about 0.01&#x000a0;second. The ROS species can be exchanged across the plasma membrane at a rate 7.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>8</sup> m<sup>-2</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>-1</sup>, (derived from measurements on Jurkat T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]), giving a rate of 4.8/min with the chosen membrane area. The existence of internal detoxification enzymes means that ROS is removed as it diffuses into the cell. The background level of cytoplasmic ROS is taken to be 1 nM, and with the above diffusion rate and SOD concentration, an external concentration of 1000 times this can be tolerated before the internal concentration begins to increase appreciably (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>F). The figure also shows that this threshold depends on the SOD2 concentration.</p><p>The activation of the SAPK enzymes (JNK, IKK) in the model depends directly on the concentration of cytoplasmic ROS, and by ROS deactivating the DUSP that reverses the SAPK activation, and deactivating the GSH that reactivates the DUSP (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>E &#x00026; D). The result is a fairly abrupt activation of JNK and IKK, shown as a function of external ROS concentration in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>G. The activation of IKK is chosen to begin at a higher level of oxidative stress than JNK based on requirements of FOXO response, as described below.</p><p>JNK activation modulates the activity of the FOXO transcription factor, sending it to the nucleus and initiating transcription (for FOXO4 this occurs by direct phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]; similar JNK-dependent effects seem to occur through other mechanisms for the other FOXO factors, even though the phosphorylation sites are not conserved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>]). Conversely, Akt, activated by Insulin signalling, phosphorylates FOXO on different sites and sends it to the cytoplasm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>], terminating transcription. The cytoplasmic FOXO is also vulnerable to degradation. Moreover, IKK can phosphorylate FOXO, also deactivating it and accelerating its degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. In previous work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] we produced a model of FOXO including these (and other) effects, which is here linked to the signalling pathways described above. The result is an interplay between Insulin-driven deactivation and oxidative stress driven activation, as shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>H. The fraction of DNA bound (transcriptionally active) FOXO decreases at higher insulin, but it also increases once external ROS passes the threshold at which internal ROS begins to rise and JNK becomes active, only to fall again once IKK is also activated, as IKK-phosphorylated FOXO is expelled from the nucleus and degraded.</p></sec><sec><title>Pathway interactions and long-term processes</title><p>The above examples are all reasonably rapid processes. We now turn to those on a rather longer timescale, allowing for the interactions between the subsystems and for processes of protein synthesis/degradation to become more important. FOXO controls many genes, including InR and SOD2. The activation of stress response kinases regulating FOXO allows the system to respond to events that alter ROS through levels of SOD2. Transcriptionally regulated species in the model showed stable cycles during the physiological diurnal variation of human insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>], as shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>: Figure S2.</p><p>In Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A we show the effect of long-term starvation (Insulin withdrawal) on the InR level: over the course of 48 hours it is upregulated roughly twofold. The result of this is to increase the sensitivity to insulin; as shown in the right-hand panel, the insulin dose&#x02013;response curve then moves appreciably to lower concentrations. The upregulation of the insulin receptor has been shown qualitatively in C2C12 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>] and the twofold upregulation is in agreement with experiments in which FOXO is overexpressed in rat cardiomyocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. For SOD2, regulated similarly, there is qualitative data from MEFs and DL23 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>].</p><p>Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B shows that the model is able to qualitatively reproduce the experimentally-observed interaction between Insulin signalling and Oxidative stress in rat skeletal muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]. Relative to basal activity, hydrogen peroxide alone produces a weak activation of Glucose uptake, Insulin produces a strong uptake, but the two together, surprisingly, lead to an intermediate uptake. Examination of the intermediate components of the model show a possible explanation for this: with hydrogen peroxide alone, signalling remains inactive in the model as far as PI3K, but there is an increase in PIP3 above its basal level because of partial oxidation of PTEN (~20%) reducing its activity. This is sufficient to weakly activate Akt and its downstream targets, producing some glucose uptake. Conversely, with both Insulin and hydrogen peroxide present, activation of the SAPKs causes serine phosphorylation of IRS1, sequestering it from Tyrosine phosphorylation and hence reducing the amount available to form the IRS1-PI3K complex. The PTEN inactivation does not compensate for this, hence the effect of Insulin and hydrogen peroxide is less than insulin alone. After 240 min, there is appreciable IRS1 loss due to degradation of the serine-phosphorylated form, which affects both the Insulin-stimulated experiment and (to a greater extent) the experiments where hydrogen peroxide is present. The concentrations of hydrogen peroxide and Insulin used in the simulation were Ins&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 nM and extracellular ROS&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 &#x003bc;M. The concentrations used in the experiment are not known exactly, except that Insulin is saturating and the oxidative stress (generated by glucose oxidase) was high.</p><p>Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>C shows dose&#x02013;response bars indicating that antioxidant defence (SOD2) can be upregulated by FOXO at a low degree of oxidative stress, but at a high level it is downregulated. There is reasonable agreement between simulation and experiment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], though the SOD2 fold-change is rather too small and the upregulation of FOXO at low oxidative stress (caused by its nuclear location, hence escaping some degradation) is not seen in this experiment, though it was (under different experimental conditions) in the data used to parameterize the earlier FOXO model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. The simulation time at which these results were observed was 960 min (16 h), and the Insulin concentration was taken to be 2 nM.</p><p>We next investigated the longer term effects of oxidative stress (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Various initial oxidative stresses were applied for one day (1440&#x000a0;minutes) followed by a longer, higher basal oxidative stress lasting until 20 k minutes (approximately 14 days). With no insulin present (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A), preconditioning with various oxidative stress (including zero, corresponding to the fasting situation) upregulates antioxidants, leading to a bifurcation in the response: those that had low oxidative stress can support a higher subsequent oxidative stress than those that had a high initial stress, which downregulated antioxidants. With higher 0.2 nM insulin (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>B), this bifurcation disappears; even though SOD2 may be initially downregulated to various extents, the subsequent oxidative stress leads all the systems to converge to a low SOD2 state. This contrasts somewhat with the result on FOXO localisation in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>H, which was measured at t&#x02009;=&#x02009;60 min after application of the oxidative stress. The high DNA-bound FOXO fraction at that time slightly disguises a loss of FOXO due to IKK mediated degradation.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of external oxidative stress &#x0201c;preconditioning&#x0201d; on later effect of higher oxidative stress.</bold> (<bold>A</bold>): Insulin&#x02009;=&#x02009;0; effect of various initial external ROS for 1440 min, followed by moderate external ROS of 20 &#x003bc;M for 20000 min, on Total FOXO, DNA bound FOXO, SOD2, cytoplasmic ROS and total IRS; (<bold>B</bold>): as before, but with Insulin&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.2 nM (#&#x02009;=&#x02009;1000).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-4"/></fig><p>Sensitivity analysis of the model has been carried out; the results can be found as Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>By integrating and extending previous work, we have produced an integrated model of insulin signalling and oxidative stress and shown that it can reproduce multiple experimental observations of the response to these stimuli in isolation and together.</p><p>With regard to the modelling approach adopted here, the treatment of the multiple PTMs in the system, especially of FOXO and IRS1, would be better treated in the rule-based modelling/kappa calculus framework currently being intensively developed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>] than by SBML. This would also enable treatment of the many FOXO-interacting partners. Nevertheless, we reproduced some of the flexibility of rule-based modelling by using a scripting approach to generate reactions in SBML (see Methods). In addition, FOXO mediated transcription would be better modelled within a stochastic framework, which would allow the appreciable degree of variability observed in the system on a cell-to-cell basis to become apparent. However, our emphasis was on using an integrative framework for all processes and therefore the established ODE approach was the best option.</p><p>Only a few key aspects of ROS production and detoxification have been treated in the current work. There are several chemical species of importance, particularly superoxide, produced by complexes I and III of the electron transport chain; it is a highly reactive species that is converted by superoxide dismutase (SOD) in mitochondria and cytoplasm to hydrogen peroxide, which is itself converted to water by catalases in mitochondria, cytoplasm and peroxisomes. In addition, superoxide and hydrogen peroxide can be detoxified by reacting with SH groups in GSH and Prx. Hydroxyl radicals can be produced by reaction of superoxide with Iron (II); they are extremely reactive and will react with a nearby molecule before they can be detoxified. Accordingly they are handled by keeping Iron II and superoxide levels under control and keeping iron sequestered in complexes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>]. A detailed model of the antioxidant system featuring more of these components awaits future work. In our current model, only a &#x0201c;generic&#x0201d; ROS species representing superoxide or hydrogen peroxide is represented. Correspondingly, a single detoxifying enzyme, SOD2, is included, which removes this in one step, rather than the pair of an SOD and catalase (not to mention the numerous enzymes that use dithiol-disulphide conversions to remove ROS). Recent modelling work has described interesting effects of over/underexpression of particular enzymes in this detoxification pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. However the approach adopted here can be justified at least in part by the fact that both SOD2 and catalase seem to be regulated in parallel by FOXO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>].</p><p>ROS can react with proteins, lipids and nucleic acids to form a variety of adducts which are deleterious to a greater or lesser extent. The process may or may not be reversible. This general molecular damage is not explicitly represented in this work: more detailed models of the effects of molecular damage and its resolution by protein turnover [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>] or the DNA damage response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>] have been developed; in future work it would be desirable to combine these and explicitly represent the different damage inducing species superoxide, peroxide and hydroxyl radical.</p><p>Although the production of ROS may appear to be a process that is simply deleterious for an organism, the situation is complicated by the intricacy of the antioxidant system and the co-opting of ROS into signalling pathways such as IS. This underlies the complicated countervailing effects of ROS in the regulation of nutrient uptake and related pathologies, such as diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>]; the present model is a first step to provide a computational framework to address this. Moreover, ROS signalling is important in the regulation of cell growth and division in general: it is becoming clear that changes in intracellular redox state coupled to ROS production are important in the regulation of almost all phases of the cell cycle, including maintenance of a quiescent state and the G1/S transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>]. FOXO, JNK and PTP1B/PTEN all have important roles here, along with many other proteins not treated in the current work such as NRF2, p53, the CKIs, PP2A. SHP-2, LAR and Cdc25. In yeast at least, the redox potential normally cycles roughly in synchrony with the cell cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>]. Moreover, cellular senescence, apparently an anticancer adaptation, proceeds through a feedback loop of ROS generation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>]. Other essential processes in which ROS have a functional role include inflammation and the killing of pathogens by the macrophage oxidative burst.</p><p>The activation of SAPKs occurs by similar mechanisms to those outlined above for phosphatases: reversible cysteine oxidation leads to release of upstream activating enzymes from sequestering complexes and activates the kinases after a phosphorylation cascade; cysteine oxidation also leads to the blocking of their inactivating phosphatases (DUSPs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. A more detailed model of the JNK activation cascade was made by Ferrell and co-workers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>], and it was found that in most cell types activation led to an ultrasensitive activation kinetics. Activation of IKK through TNF&#x003b1; was included in several models of NF&#x003ba;B activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">93</xref>].</p><p>Although lack of correlation of antioxidant levels in different organisms with lifespan, and the unexpected effects of knockouts and dietary antioxidant supplementations have led some authors to suggest that the free radical theory needs to be revised or rejected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>], it remains plausible that the complexity and multifaceted nature of the system could account for the observed behaviour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">95</xref>]. Exploration of this will require much further development, but it has been begun in the recent work on catalase/SOD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>], dithiol antioxidants and transport of ROS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] and antioxidant response through KEAP/NRF2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96">96</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>], as well as that reported here, with the introduction of the phosphatase inhibition, the interaction with SAPKs and the feedback regulation of FOXO.</p><p>The dose&#x02013;response curve of FOXO-mediated antioxidant regulation is at first puzzling. Upregulation of antioxidant defences in the face of weak external oxidative stress (through a JNK-mediated mechanism) is as expected; however, high oxidative stress then leads to a downregulation again (through an IKK mediated mechanism). Here we have concentrated only on describing this effect; however evolutionarily it is hard to see what its cause could be. It may simply be that the hydrogen peroxide concentrations required to observe it (an extracellular concentration of about 20 &#x003bc;M) are higher than would ever be experienced by a cell in vivo, or it may be that the mechanism is cell type specific. The IKK-mediated mechanism could be activated in vivo by other, more specific, activators of NF&#x003ba;B signalling such as certain cytokines.</p><p>The work carried out here has been largely literature based. Better constraints could be put on the model with more detailed and more fully quantified timecourses carried out in a single (or a few) cell types. Rather than adhering to the minimal modelling approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>], we have not considered multiple model architectures, and the architecture used is fairly complex, so we accept that some parameters will not be uniquely determined. Nevertheless, we have tried to avoid overfitting by extensive human intervention in the fitting, to prevent sparse data driving parameters to particularly large or small values. The sensitivity analysis indicates that all parameters have an effect on at least some species of the model and so are likely to be at least in principle identifiable, although due to the model architecture there may be some unidentifiable parameter combinations; for example the rate of FOXO synthesis is chosen to be, not a zero-order process, but the product of an E2F1 transcription factor species, whose number is assigned and does not otherwise vary, and a per-molecule rate.</p><p>We have also found it necessary to use data sources from multiple organisms and multiple tissues. Most of them are adipocyte or adipocytes like (eg 3T3-L1 cells) or skeletal muscle, the two most strongly insulin-responsive tissues, from rodent (rat/mouse) or human sources. Particularly in the FOXO part of the model, however, other cell types have been used, such as human colon and liver carcinoma (see text and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). Many mechanisms, particularly of core insulin signalling, are strongly conserved among mammals and indeed between mammals other vertebrates and even invertebrates, but this feature of the model certainly emphasises the need for independent experimental validation.</p><p>In this model we have begun to address transcriptional feedbacks, but the simple nature of the treatment here belies the extreme difficulty of handling this: antioxidants are under the control of multiple transcription factors, but the measurements of total protein or transcript level can give no indication of which TF produced it. Hence we expect our long-time (FOXO-transcription-mediated) results will be qualitative only. The situation is further complicated by the regulation of protein synthesis at the translational level, the physical interaction of TFs with cofactors or each other, and the transcription of one TF by another [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">99</xref>]. For example FOXO exerts positive feedback on its own synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">100</xref>], and there are additional mutual regulations of FOXO, Akt and PP2A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B101">101</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B102">102</xref>]. Achieving biological realism here is a formidable task, but could lead to a better understanding of the homeostatic and adaptive behaviours of the pathway.</p><p>What, aside from chemical detail of the ROS, is missing in the model? Clearly the system as it stands is much simplified. Other signalling pathways (p38 MAPK etc.) and TFs (NFkB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B103">103</xref>], NRF2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96">96</xref>]) may also be activated by ROS, and there are other effects, for example secretion of inflammatory cytokines. This may lead to reinforcement of inflammation by positive feedback generation of ROS, a process which the current model could be extended to describe. Moreover, a long exposure to anything more than mild oxidative stress may induce apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B104">104</xref>]. With regard to the nutrient sensing and response pathways, a full description would require the inclusion of the mTOR (amino acid sensing) pathway along with AMPK (total energy) and possibly sensing of other nutrients, such as fatty acids, which give rise to inflammatory responses and activate PKC. Modelling of fatty acid metabolism was included in a model of glycolysis by Dash et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B105">105</xref>]. Other work has already been done, which could be combined with that reported here, including for example insulin signalling combined with mTOR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B106">106</xref>], AMPK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107">107</xref>], and the ERK pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Significantly, other recent models of insulin signalling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], as well as including mTOR signalling, have combined the cell signalling model with a whole body model of insulin/glucose dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B108">108</xref>].</p><p>Uptake of glucose and its transfer to mitochondria will lead to an increase in the energy production of the cell, but also the ROS output of the mitochondria. This has been neglected in the current model for which mitochondrially generated ROS is a constant. This approximation is likely to be acceptable for a cell type such as adipocytes, where the majority of ROS is signalling-associated, but would certainly need to be revised in order to extend the model to other cell types such as muscle for which mitochondrially produced ROS constitutes a larger fraction of the total. The energy demand and the ratio of glucose to other fuel sources, (particularly fatty acids, which may compete with carbohydrates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B109">109</xref>]), will also have an influence on mitochondrially-generated ROS; see Fridlyand and Philipson for a review in the context of diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110">110</xref>]. This may be expected to occur on a rather slower timescale than the signalling-related ROS production included in the current model, but, (even in adipocytes), will complicate the long-time effects which lead to the activation of SAPKs and the induction of insulin resistance. Hence, detailed modelling of mitochondria may be required to fully understand the role of chronic oxidative stress in the system. Mechanistic models of glycolysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B111">111</xref>], oxidative phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B112">112</xref>] and ROS production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B113">113</xref>] in mitochondria have been produced and will be combined with the current model in future extensions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>We have adapted an existing model of insulin signalling, integrated it with a model of FOXO regulation, and expanded it by introducing regulations through oxidative stress, to produce a model able to reproduce several quite complex observed effects: oxidative stress is able to activate insulin signalling, endogenous ROS increase the sensitivity of insulin signalling, and weak oxidative stress or fasting upregulates antioxidants through a homeostatic feedback mechanism, that increases the level of oxidative shock that can be withstood for a short time. Nevertheless long term high oxidative stress leads to a collapse of the oxidative stress resistance mechanism.</p><p>As outlined in the discussion, the current work addresses only a part of this very complex system and much more development, and extra experimental data, will be required to make a truly biologically realistic model of IS, FOXO and oxidative stress. Nevertheless the current work makes it apparent how valuable such an integrated model will be. A model including signalling pathways from all three food groups, as outlined above, combined with a whole body model of nutrient flux, and the interactions with oxidative stress outlined here, would be a powerful tool to address the progress of insulin resistance to metabolic syndrome and T2D [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B114">114</xref>], and how fuel use depends on overall nutrient availability and energy expenditure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B115">115</xref>]. FOXO is known to contribute to the regulation of this [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], for example by controlling the switching between gluconeogenesis and glycolysis through transcription of PDK4, G6Pase and PEPCK; the model could be extended to include these genes downstream. It is apparent that the modelling of nutrient signalling and oxidative stress, to which the current work contributes, is coming to a level of detail that enables it to address interesting questions of life history, metabolic regulation and disease.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Simulations were carried out with Copasi version 4.6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B116">116</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B117">117</xref>], using the particle number representation in deterministic mode, and analysis was done with R version 2.9.2 which was also used to produce the figures. Particle numbers were converted to concentrations for presentation. Fitting was done using Copasi&#x02019;s Parameter Estimation task, and parameter sensitivities calculated with the Sensitivities tasks, using time series not steady states. The model was developed using SBML shorthand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B118">118</xref>] in separate files corresponding to the modules of Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, which were converted into SBML prior to importing into Copasi. Python scripts were used to combine the individual module files and, in the case of the FOXO module, to generate all species and reactions corresponding to the different possible combinations of PTMs and localization, as previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. In essence, this results in a simulation and analysis pipeline Python -&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;SBML-shorthand -&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;SBML -&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Copasi -&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;R. These scripts are available in supplementary material as Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S9">9</xref>, and on GitHub (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/graham1034/Smith2012_insulin_signalling">https://github.com/graham1034/Smith2012_insulin_signalling</ext-link>), together with the model files (SBML) of each module (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S10">10</xref>), and the complete model in two forms: initially (with particle numbers as in Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), which was used to produce the majority of the results (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S11">11</xref>); and after equilibration (taken from the end of the simulation in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S2, then further equilibrated at constant low insulin of 0.2 nM for two more days), which was used to produce the results in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S12">12</xref>). The first of these models. with particle numbers at their initial levels, has been uploaded to BIOMODELS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels-main">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels-main</ext-link>; identifier MODEL1212210000). The differential equations of the model are also available as Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>FOXO: Forkhead box, type O; IRS1: Insulin Receptor Substrate 1; IS: Insulin signalling; T2D: Type 2 Diabetes; ROS: Reactive oxygen species; SAPK: Stress-activated protein kinase; JNK: c-Jun N-terminal Kinase; IKK: I-kappa-B kinase; InR: Insulin receptor; PTM: Post translational modification; PI3K: Phosphoinositide 3-Kinase; PIP2: Phosphatidylinositol 3,5-bisphosphate; PIP3: Phosphatidylinositol 3,4,5-trisphosphate; Akt (PKB): RAC-alpha serine/threonine kinase; Akt Kinase; Protein Kinase B; PKC: Protein Kinase C; GSH: Glutathione; PTEN: Phosphatase and Tensin homolog; PTP1B: Protein Tyrosine Phosphatase 1B (PTPN1); AS160: Akt substrate of 160&#x000a0;kDa; TBC1: domain family member 4; GLUT4: Solute carrier family 2, facilitated Glucose transporter member 4 (SLC2A4).</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>GS carried out the simulations, analysed the results and drafted the manuscript. DS conceived the study and helped to draft the manuscript. Both authors participated in the design of the study. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p>Differential equations of the model, exported from Copasi and formatted with LaTeX.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Description of Data: (</bold><bold>A</bold><bold>) Model kinetics of NOX activation in response to 15 min insulin, and resulting ROS production; (</bold><bold>B</bold><bold>) Degradation of IRS1 by prolonged high insulin signalling (black) or high extracellular ROS (red); (</bold><bold>C</bold><bold>) Effect of variation of basal intracellular ROS production (particle # Mt) on the dependence of intracellular ROS on extracellular ROS; (</bold><bold>D</bold><bold>) Effect of variation of intracellular antioxidants (particle # of SOD2) on the dependence of intracellular ROS on extracellular ROS; (</bold><bold>E</bold><bold>) Effect of variation of membrane permeability on the dependence of intracellular ROS on extracellular ROS.</bold></p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S2.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>Description of Data: Behaviour of key model species through 5 days (7200 minutes) of human physiological insulin variation.</bold> Insulin data taken from Frayn et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>].</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S3.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p>Description of Data: Sensitivity of model species to parameter variation at 0.2 nM Insulin and zero external ROS.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S4.csv"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional file 5</title><p>Description of Data: Sensitivity of model species to parameter variation at 0.2 nM Insulin and 1 micromolar external ROS.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S5.csv"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6"><caption><title>Additional file 6</title><p>Sensitivity Analysis.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S6.docx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7"><caption><title>Additional file 7: Table S5</title><p>Summary of experimental data sets used in fitting the model; see text for additional references.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S7.docx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S8"><caption><title>Additional file 8</title><p><bold>Catshorthand python script.</bold> Description of Data: Python script to concatenate sbml-shorthand model files, putting together each section and removing species declarations that are repeated in multiple models (the one in the first file on the command line will be kept).</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S8.py"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S9"><caption><title>Additional file 9</title><p><bold>Make-foxo-shorthand python script.</bold> Description of Data: Python script to make a SBML-shorthand (.mod) file for the FOXO module by a rule-based approach, generating the species names and equations interconverting them for all combinations of the PTMs of FOXO.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S9.py"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S10"><caption><title>Additional file 10</title><p><bold>Zip archive of model sbml-shorthand files.</bold> Description of Data: zip archive containing SBML-shorthand files (.mod) for receptor binding, akt, phosphatase, IRS, JNK and FOXO modules and for events to set five days of physiological insulin variation as in Frayn et al. m8b2_rapijf.mod is the result of assembling the files with $ catshorthand.py m8b2_recep.6.mod m8b2_akt.6.mod m8b2_phosph.6.mod m8b2_irs.6.mod m8b2_jnk.6.mod m8b2_foxo.6.mod.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S10.zip"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S11"><caption><title>Additional file 11</title><p><bold>SBML file of the complete model (initial state).</bold> SBML file of the complete model with particle numbers as in Table 1.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S11.xml"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S12"><caption><title>Additional file 12</title><p><bold>SBML file of the complete model (equilibrated).</bold> SBML file of the complete model with equilibrated particle numbers after physiol insulin cycles for 5 days then 2 more days equilibration at constant Ins=1000 (0.2 nM).</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-7-41-S12.xml"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Glyn Nelson and Piero Dalle Pezze for critical reading of the manuscript and the reviewers for helpful comments. This work was funded by the EU Network of Excellence LifeSpan (FP6 036894) and by the BBSRC/EPSRC grant to CISBAN (BBC0082001).</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><article-title>Evolution of ageing</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1977</year><volume>270</volume><issue>5635</issue><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/270301a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">593350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Selman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Separating cause from effect: how does insulin/IGF signalling control lifespan in worms, flies and mice?</article-title><source>J Intern Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>263</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2796.2007.01906.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18226095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zigmond</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Juo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Blenis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><article-title>Akt promotes cell survival by phosphorylating and inhibiting a Forkhead transcription factor</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>857</fpage><lpage>868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80595-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10102273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calnan</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>The FoxO code</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>2276</fpage><lpage>2288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2008.21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18391970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Heuvel</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><article-title>The role of FoxO in the regulation of metabolism</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>2320</fpage><lpage>2336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2008.25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18391974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Masoro</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><article-title>Dietary restriction-induced life extension: a broadly based biological phenomenon</article-title><source>Biogerontology</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10522-006-9015-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16732403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bartke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>New findings in gene knockout, mutant and transgenic mice</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2008</year><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2007.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18053667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tatar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The plate half-full: status of research on the mechanisms of dietary restriction in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2011</year><volume>46</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2010.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21187139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Veal</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogen peroxide sensing and signaling</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2007.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17434122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kapahi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulton</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><article-title>Positive correlation between mammalian life span and cellular resistance to stress</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>26</volume><issue>5&#x02013;6</issue><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10218637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Aging: a theory based on free radical and radiation chemistry</article-title><source>J Gerontol</source><year>1956</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/geronj/11.3.298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13332224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>The biologic clock: the mitochondria?</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>1972</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5016631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiens</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiedtke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Burness</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><article-title>Antioxidant enzyme activities are not broadly correlated with longevity in 14 vertebrate endotherm species</article-title><source>Age (Dordr)</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11357-010-9131-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20431992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Remmen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Is the oxidative stress theory of aging dead?</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2009</year><volume>1790</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2009.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19524016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baynes</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Mice deficient in both Mn superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase-1 have increased oxidative damage and a greater incidence of pathology but no reduction in longevity</article-title><source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>64</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1212</fpage><lpage>1220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19776219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bloch-Damti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Potashnik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gual</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Marchand-Brustel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanti</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Differential effects of IRS1 phosphorylated on Ser307 or Ser632 in the induction of insulin resistance by oxidative stress</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>2006</year><volume>49</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2463</fpage><lpage>2473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-006-0349-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16896943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Archuleta</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemieux</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saengsirisuwan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Teachey</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindborg</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><article-title>Oxidant stress-induced loss of IRS-1 and IRS-2 proteins in rat skeletal muscle: role of p38 MAPK</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1486</fpage><lpage>1493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.08.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19703555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mahadev</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilbering</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogen peroxide generated during cellular insulin stimulation is integral to activation of the distal insulin signaling cascade in 3T3-L1 adipocytes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><issue>52</issue><fpage>48662</fpage><lpage>48669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M105061200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11598110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mahadev</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilbering</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><article-title>Insulin-stimulated hydrogen peroxide reversibly inhibits protein-tyrosine phosphatase 1b in vivo and enhances the early insulin action cascade</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>21938</fpage><lpage>21942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C100109200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11297536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>Reversible inactivation of the tumor suppressor PTEN by H2O2</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>20336</fpage><lpage>20342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111899200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11916965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeol Yeo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung Hur</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>The major target of the endogenously generated reactive oxygen species in response to insulin stimulation is phosphatase and tensin homolog and not phosphoinositide-3 kinase (PI-3 kinase) in the PI-3 kinase/Akt pathway</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15537704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldfine</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddux</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grodsky</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><article-title>Oxidative stress and stress-activated signaling pathways: a unifying hypothesis of type 2 diabetes</article-title><source>Endocr Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/er.2001-0039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12372842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bashan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovsan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kachko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ovadia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Positive and negative regulation of insulin signaling by reactive oxygen and nitrogen species</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>2009</year><volume>89</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00014.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><article-title>Targeting Forkhead box O1 from the concept to metabolic diseases: lessons from mouse models</article-title><source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ars.2010.3370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20615072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Manolopoulos</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Klotz</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Korsten</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Linking Alzheimer's disease to insulin resistance: the FoxO response to oxidative stress</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1046</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2010.17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20966918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sedaghat</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><article-title>A mathematical model of metabolic insulin signaling pathways</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2002</year><volume>283</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>E1084</fpage><lpage>E1101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cedersund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulfhielm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Danielsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tidefelt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Stralfors</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Model-based hypothesis testing of key mechanisms in initial phase of insulin signaling</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e1000096</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18551197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kiselyov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Versteyhe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauguin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Harmonic oscillator model of the insulin and IGF1 receptors' allosteric binding and activation</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>243</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19225456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dalle Pezze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonntag</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Thien</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prentzell</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Godel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann-Haefelin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><article-title>A dynamic network model of mTOR signaling reveals TSC-independent mTORC2 regulation</article-title><source>Sci Signal</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><issue>217</issue><fpage>ra25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2002469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22457331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vinod</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><article-title>Quantification of the effect of amino acids on an integrated mTOR and insulin signaling pathway</article-title><source>Mol Biosyst</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1163</fpage><lpage>1173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b816965a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19756306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borisov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Aksamitiene</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyatkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Legewie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maiwald</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaimachnikov</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoek</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kholodenko</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><article-title>Systems-level interactions between insulin-EGF networks amplify mitogenic signaling</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>256</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19357636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faratian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Goltsov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebedeva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorokin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moodie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Um</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Langdon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goryanin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Systems biology reveals new strategies for personalizing cancer medicine and confirms the role of PTEN in resistance to trastuzumab</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>69</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>6713</fpage><lpage>6720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-0777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19638581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nyman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brannmark</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nystrom</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Stralfors</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cedersund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>A hierarchical whole-body modeling approach elucidates the link between in Vitro insulin signaling and in Vivo glucose homeostasis</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><issue>29</issue><fpage>26028</fpage><lpage>26041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.188987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><article-title>Modelling the response of FOXO transcription factors to multiple post-translational modifications made by ageing-related signalling pathways</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e11092</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0011092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20567500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adimora</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><article-title>A model of redox kinetics implicates the thiol proteome in cellular hydrogen peroxide responses</article-title><source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ars.2009.2968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20121341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stagsted</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Correlation between insulin receptor occupancy and tyrosine kinase activity at low insulin concentrations and effect of major histocompatibility complex class I-derived peptide</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>1993</year><volume>267</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8246175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>BioNumbers--the database of key numbers in molecular and cell biology</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D750</fpage><lpage>D753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haertinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrimpf</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hengartner</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>von Mering</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>PaxDb, a database of protein abundance averages across all three domains of life</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.O111.014704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22535208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrimpf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hengartner</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lercher</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>von Mering</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Shotgun proteomics data from multiple organisms reveals remarkable quantitative conservation of the eukaryotic core proteome</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>1306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200900414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20077411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Virshup</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>Protein serine/threonine phosphatases: life, death, and sleeping</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2005.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15780597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Naka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yumoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirouzu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>A computational model on the modulation of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) and Akt pathways in heregulin-induced ErbB signalling</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2003</year><volume>373</volume><issue>Pt 2</issue><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12691603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Augert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackmore</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Exton</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><article-title>Changes in the concentration and fatty acid composition of phosphoinositides induced by hormones in hepatocytes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1989</year><volume>264</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2574</fpage><lpage>2580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2536716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alessi</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><article-title>Modulation of insulin-stimulated degradation of human insulin receptor substrate-1 by Serine 312 phosphorylation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>8199</fpage><lpage>8211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M209153200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12510059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Essers</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijzen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries-Smits</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saarloos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ruiter</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgering</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><article-title>FOXO transcription factor activation by oxidative stress mediated by the small GTPase Ral and JNK</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>4802</fpage><lpage>4812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15538382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsuzaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Daitoku</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukamizu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Insulin-induced phosphorylation of FKHR (Foxo1) targets to proteasomal degradation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>11285</fpage><lpage>11290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1934283100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13679577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Biggs</surname><given-names>WH</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Meisenhelder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavenee</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><article-title>Protein kinase B/Akt-mediated phosphorylation promotes nuclear exclusion of the winged helix transcription factor FKHR1</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>7421</fpage><lpage>7426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.13.7421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Golfman</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ou-Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Saso</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>IkappaB kinase promotes tumorigenesis through inhibition of forkhead FOXO3a</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>117</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(04)00302-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frescas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Accili</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Nuclear trapping of the forkhead transcription factor FoxO1 via Sirt-dependent deacetylation promotes expression of glucogenetic genes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>20589</fpage><lpage>20595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M412357200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15788402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesecar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Unterman</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><article-title>Phosphorylation of serine 256 suppresses transactivation by FKHR (FOXO1) by multiple mechanisms. Direct and indirect effects on nuclear/cytoplasmic shuttling and DNA binding</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><issue>47</issue><fpage>45276</fpage><lpage>45284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M208063200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kops</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ruiter</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vries-Smits</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgering</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><article-title>Direct control of the Forkhead transcription factor AFX by protein kinase B</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>398</volume><issue>6728</issue><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/19328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10217147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramamoorthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimojima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>MDM2 acts downstream of p53 as an E3 ligase to promote FOXO ubiquitination and degradation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>13987</fpage><lpage>14000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M901758200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19321440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Klipp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordlander</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gennemark</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Integrative model of the response of yeast to osmotic shock</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>975</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16025103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><article-title>Bidirectional regulation of upstream IGF-I/insulin receptor signaling and downstream FOXO1 in cardiomyocytes</article-title><source>J Endocrinol</source><year>2007</year><volume>192</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1677/joe.1.07020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17210752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ambrogini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-Millan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Depinho</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goellner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jilka</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><article-title>FoxO-mediated defense against oxidative stress in osteoblasts is indispensable for skeletal homeostasis in mice</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2009.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20142101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Galic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Skiba</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooms</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><article-title>Reactive oxygen species enhance insulin sensitivity</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2009.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19808019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Larance</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stockli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dam</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Winata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasinger</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Junutula</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Guilhaus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Characterization of the role of the Rab GTPase-activating protein AS160 in insulin-regulated GLUT4 trafficking</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><issue>45</issue><fpage>37803</fpage><lpage>37813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M503897200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16154996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Miinea</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Asara</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lienhard</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><article-title>Insulin-stimulated phosphorylation of a Rab GTPase-activating protein regulates GLUT4 translocation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>14599</fpage><lpage>14602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C300063200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12637568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>Reversible inactivation of protein-tyrosine phosphatase 1B in A431 cells stimulated with epidermal growth factor</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>15366</fpage><lpage>15372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.25.15366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9624118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kamata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Reactive oxygen species promote TNFalpha-induced death and sustained JNK activation by inhibiting MAP kinase phosphatases</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>120</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2004.12.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15766528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kops</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dansen</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Polderman</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Saarloos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Medema</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgering</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><article-title>Forkhead transcription factor FOXO3a protects quiescent cells from oxidative stress</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>419</volume><issue>6904</issue><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12239572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Pivotal role of JNK-dependent FOXO1 activation in downregulation of kallistatin expression by oxidative stress</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>298</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>H1048</fpage><lpage>H1054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.00826.2009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20081110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chibalin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Koistinen</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koumanov</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallberg-Henriksson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zierath</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><article-title>Kinetics of GLUT4 trafficking in rat and human skeletal muscle</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><year>2009</year><volume>58</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db08-1539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yenush</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><article-title>The c-Jun NH(2)-terminal kinase promotes insulin resistance during association with insulin receptor substrate-1 and phosphorylation of Ser(307)</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>9047</fpage><lpage>9054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.12.9047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10722755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoelson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><article-title>Phosphorylation of Ser307 in insulin receptor substrate-1 blocks interactions with the insulin receptor and inhibits insulin action</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1531</fpage><lpage>1537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M101521200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zick</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Ser/Thr phosphorylation of IRS proteins: a molecular basis for insulin resistance</article-title><source>Sci STKE</source><year>2005</year><volume>2005</volume><issue>268</issue><fpage>pe4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15671481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanti</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Cellular mechanisms of insulin resistance: role of stress-regulated serine kinases and insulin receptor substrates (IRS) serine phosphorylation</article-title><source>Curr Opin Pharmacol</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coph.2009.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19683471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Herschkovitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tennenbaum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>LeRoith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zick</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Insulin stimulates PKCzeta -mediated phosphorylation of insulin receptor substrate-1 (IRS-1). A self-attenuated mechanism to negatively regulate the function of IRS proteins</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>14459</fpage><lpage>14465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11278339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ravichandran</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><article-title>Protein kinase C-zeta phosphorylates insulin receptor substrate-1 and impairs its ability to activate phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase in response to insulin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>3543</fpage><lpage>3549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M007231200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11063744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Um</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Frigerio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Joaquin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sticker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fumagalli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allegrini</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozma</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Auwerx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Absence of S6K1 protects against age- and diet-induced obesity while enhancing insulin sensitivity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>431</volume><issue>7005</issue><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15306821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pederson</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rondinone</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><article-title>Serine/threonine phosphorylation of IRS-1 triggers its degradation: possible regulation by tyrosine phosphorylation</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><year>2001</year><volume>50</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diabetes.50.1.24</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11147790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hiratani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Haruta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Usui</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Roles of mTOR and JNK in serine phosphorylation, translocation, and degradation of IRS-1</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2005</year><volume>335</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.07.152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16099428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres-Aleman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Neuronal death by oxidative stress involves activation of FOXO3 through a two-arm pathway that activates stress kinases and attenuates insulin-like growth factor I signaling</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2014</fpage><lpage>2025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E07-08-0811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18287535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frayn</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppack</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><article-title>Net carbon flux across subcutaneous adipose tissue after a standard meal in normal-weight and insulin-resistant obese subjects</article-title><source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source><year>1996</year><volume>20</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>800</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8880344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Transcriptional feedback control of insulin receptor by dFOXO/FOXO1</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>2435</fpage><lpage>2446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1340505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16230533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kozlovsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Potashnik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Reactive oxygen species activate glucose transport in L6 myotubes</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(97)00069-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9378365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Higaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirshman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodyear</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Oxidative stress stimulates skeletal muscle glucose uptake through a phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase-dependent pathway</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2008</year><volume>294</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>E889</fpage><lpage>E897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00150.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18303121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faeder</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blinov</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Hlavacek</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><article-title>Rule-based modeling of biochemical systems with BioNetGen</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>500</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-59745-525-1_5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19399430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hlavacek</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Faeder</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blinov</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hucka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Rules for modeling signal-transduction systems</article-title><source>Sci STKE</source><year>2006</year><volume>2006</volume><issue>344</issue><fpage>re6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16849649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Danos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Krivine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Internal coarse-graining of molecular systems</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>6453</fpage><lpage>6458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0809908106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><article-title>Iron behaving badly: inappropriate iron chelation as a major contributor to the aetiology of vascular and other progressive inflammatory and degenerative diseases</article-title><source>BMC Med Genomics</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1755-8794-2-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19133145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kowald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zintel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klipp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Osiewacz</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><article-title>A systems biological analysis links ROS metabolism to mitochondrial protein quality control</article-title><source>Mech Ageing Dev</source><year>2012</year><volume>133</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mad.2012.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22449407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kowald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehrach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Klipp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Alternative pathways as mechanism for the negative effects associated with overexpression of superoxide dismutase</article-title><source>J Theor Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>238</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2005.06.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16085106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>The daf-2 gene network for longevity regulates oxidative stress resistance and Mn-superoxide dismutase gene expression in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1385</fpage><lpage>1393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10428762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsirigotis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><article-title>An in silico model of the ubiquitin-proteasome system that incorporates normal homeostasis and age-related decline</article-title><source>BMC Syst Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-1-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17408507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woulfe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><article-title>Experimental and computational analysis of polyglutamine-mediated cytotoxicity</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>p100944</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorimer</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><article-title>Modelling the role of the Hsp70/Hsp90 system in the maintenance of protein homeostasis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e22038</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21779370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Passos</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Simillion</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Olijslagers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallinan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wipat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Feedback between p21 and reactive oxygen production is necessary for cell senescence</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>347</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20160708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zupanic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Systems modelling of NHEJ reveals the importance of redox regulation of Ku70/80 in the dynamics of dna damage foci</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e55190</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0055190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23457464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tiganis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Reactive oxygen species and insulin resistance: the good, the bad and the ugly</article-title><source>Trends Pharmacol Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tips.2010.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21159388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Burhans</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heintz</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><article-title>The cell cycle is a redox cycle: linking phase-specific targets to cell fate</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1282</fpage><lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.05.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19486941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudlicki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowicka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><article-title>Logic of the yeast metabolic cycle: temporal compartmentalization of cellular processes</article-title><source>Science (New York, NY</source><year>2005</year><volume>310</volume><issue>5751</issue><fpage>1152</fpage><lpage>1158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1120499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bagowski</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Besser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><article-title>The JNK cascade as a biochemical switch in mammalian cells: ultrasensitive and all-or-none responses</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(03)00083-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12593797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levchenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Understanding NF-kappaB signaling via mathematical modeling</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>192</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18463616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Doonan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthijssens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Houthoofd</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Back</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Matscheski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanfleteren</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gems</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Against the oxidative damage theory of aging: superoxide dismutases protect against oxidative stress but have little or no effect on life span in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>3236</fpage><lpage>3241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.504808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19056880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>The free-radical theory of ageing - older, wiser and still alive: Modelling positional effects of the primary targets of ROS reveals new support</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><year>2012</year><volume>34</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.201200014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22641614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><article-title>Phase I to II cross-induction of xenobiotic metabolizing enzymes: a feedforward control mechanism for potential hormetic responses</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><year>2009</year><volume>237</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2009.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19371757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><article-title>A systems biology perspective on Nrf2-mediated antioxidant response</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><year>2010</year><volume>244</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2009.08.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19716833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brannmark</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Glad</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Cedersund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stralfors</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Mass and information feedbacks through receptor endocytosis govern insulin signaling as revealed using a parameter-free modeling framework</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><issue>26</issue><fpage>20171</fpage><lpage>20179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.106849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20421297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tullet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Doonan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthijssens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reece-Hoyes</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanfleteren</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gems</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>DamID in C. elegans reveals longevity-associated targets of DAF-16/FoxO</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>399</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20706209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Essaghir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dif</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marbehant</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Demoulin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><article-title>The transcription of FOXO genes is stimulated by FOXO3 and repressed by growth factors</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>10334</fpage><lpage>10342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M808848200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19244250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerard</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuro</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothermel</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><article-title>FoxO transcription factors activate Akt and attenuate insulin signaling in heart by inhibiting protein phosphatases</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><issue>51</issue><fpage>20517</fpage><lpage>20522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0610290104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavin</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>PP2A regulates the pro-apoptotic activity of FOXO1</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>7411</fpage><lpage>7420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M708083200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18211894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihekwaba</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibney</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Foreman</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>See</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiller</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><article-title>Oscillations in NF-kappaB signaling control the dynamics of gene expression</article-title><source>Science (New York, NY</source><year>2004</year><volume>306</volume><issue>5696</issue><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1099962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berdichevsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarente</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Acute oxidative stress can reverse insulin resistance by inactivation of cytoplasmic JNK</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><issue>28</issue><fpage>21581</fpage><lpage>21589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.093633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20430894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dash</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dibella</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><article-title>A computational model of skeletal muscle metabolism linking cellular adaptations induced by altered loading states to metabolic responses during exercise</article-title><source>Biomed Eng Online</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-925X-6-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name><article-title>Signaling logic of activity-triggered dendritic protein synthesis: an mTOR gate but not a feedback switch</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e1000287</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19242559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sonntag</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalle Pezze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Thedieck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>A modelling-experimental approach reveals insulin receptor substrate (IRS)-dependent regulation of adenosine monosphosphate-dependent kinase (AMPK) by insulin</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2012</year><volume>279</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3314</fpage><lpage>3328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2012.08582.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22452783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B108"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dalla Man</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizza</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Meal simulation model of the glucose-insulin system</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Biomed Eng</source><year>2007</year><volume>54</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1740</fpage><lpage>1749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17926672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B109"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Randle</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garland</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Newsholme</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><article-title>The glucose fatty-acid cycle. Its role in insulin sensitivity and the metabolic disturbances of diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1963</year><volume>1</volume><issue>7285</issue><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13990765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B110"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fridlyand</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Philipson</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><article-title>Reactive species and early manifestation of insulin resistance in type 2 diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Obes Metab</source><year>2006</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1463-1326.2005.00496.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16448517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B111"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinnakota</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><article-title>Computer modeling of mitochondrial tricarboxylic acid cycle, oxidative phosphorylation, metabolite transport, and electrophysiology</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><issue>34</issue><fpage>24525</fpage><lpage>24537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M701024200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17591785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B112"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><article-title>A biophysical model of the mitochondrial respiratory system and oxidative phosphorylation</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>1</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0010036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16163394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B113"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Demin</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorianin</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name><surname>Kholodenko</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerhoff</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><article-title>[Kinetic modeling of energy metabolism and generation of active forms of oxygen in hepatocyte mitochondria]</article-title><source>Mol Biol (Mosk)</source><year>2001</year><volume>35</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1095</fpage><lpage>1104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11771135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B114"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eckel</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberti</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundy</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmet</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></name><article-title>The metabolic syndrome</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2010</year><volume>375</volume><issue>9710</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61794-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20109902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B115"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saidel</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><article-title>Multi-scale computational model of fuel homeostasis during exercise: effect of hormonal control</article-title><source>Ann Biomed Eng</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17111212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B116"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoops</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pahle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simus</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Singhal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kummer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><article-title>COPASI--a COmplex PAthway SImulator</article-title><source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>3067</fpage><lpage>3074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B117"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoops</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kummer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><article-title>Computational modeling of biochemical networks using COPASI</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>500</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-59745-525-1_2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19399433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B118"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Boys</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><article-title>Tools for the SBML Community</article-title><source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btk042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>