<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Comput. Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24244122</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3820522</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-13-00431</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Computational Model of Liver Iron Metabolism</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A Computational Model of Liver Iron Metabolism</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>Pedro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>School of Computer Science and Manchester Institute of Biotechnology, University of Manchester, Manchester, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Virginia Bioinformatics Institute, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Virginia, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Stelling</surname><given-names>Jorg</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>ETH Zurich, Switzerland</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>pedro.mendes@manchester.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SM PM. Performed the experiments: SM. Analyzed the data: SM. Wrote the paper: SM PM.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e1003299</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 Mitchell, Mendes</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mitchell, Mendes</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Iron is essential for all known life due to its redox properties; however, these same properties can also lead to its toxicity in overload through the production of reactive oxygen species. Robust systemic and cellular control are required to maintain safe levels of iron, and the liver seems to be where this regulation is mainly located. Iron misregulation is implicated in many diseases, and as our understanding of iron metabolism improves, the list of iron-related disorders grows. Recent developments have resulted in greater knowledge of the fate of iron in the body and have led to a detailed map of its metabolism; however, a quantitative understanding at the systems level of how its components interact to produce tight regulation remains elusive. A mechanistic computational model of human liver iron metabolism, which includes the core regulatory components, is presented here. It was constructed based on known mechanisms of regulation and on their kinetic properties, obtained from several publications. The model was then quantitatively validated by comparing its results with previously published physiological data, and it is able to reproduce multiple experimental findings. A time course simulation following an oral dose of iron was compared to a clinical time course study and the simulation was found to recreate the dynamics and time scale of the systems response to iron challenge. A disease state simulation of haemochromatosis was created by altering a single reaction parameter that mimics a human haemochromatosis gene (HFE) mutation. The simulation provides a quantitative understanding of the liver iron overload that arises in this disease. This model supports and supplements understanding of the role of the liver as an iron sensor and provides a framework for further modelling, including simulations to identify valuable drug targets and design of experiments to improve further our knowledge of this system.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>Iron is an essential nutrient required for healthy life but, in excess, is the cause of debilitating and even fatal conditions. The most common genetic disorder in humans caused by a mutation, haemochromatosis, results in an iron overload in the liver. Indeed, the liver plays a central role in the regulation of iron. Recently, an increasing amount of detail has been discovered about molecules related to iron metabolism, but an understanding of how they work together and regulate iron levels (in healthy people) or fail to do it (in disease) is still missing. We present a mathematical model of the regulation of liver iron metabolism that provides explanations of its dynamics and allows further hypotheses to be formulated and later tested in experiments. Importantly, the model reproduces accurately the healthy liver iron homeostasis and simulates haemochromatosis, showing how the causative mutation leads to iron overload. We investigate how best to control iron regulation and identified reactions that can be targets of new medicines to treat iron overload. The model provides a virtual laboratory for investigating iron metabolism and improves understanding of the method by which the liver senses and controls iron levels.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>SM thanks the BBSRC and the University of Manchester for funding through the Manchester Doctoral Training Centre for Integrative Systems Biology. PM thanks the BBSRC (grant BB/J019259/1) and the NIH (grant R01 GM080219) for funding. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Iron is an essential element from archaea to complex eukaryotes and man <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Aisen1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, and is required for many processes including oxygen transport, DNA synthesis and respiration. Iron deficiency is the most common nutritional deficiency affecting a large proportion of all humans <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-TussingHumphreys1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. The redox activity which provides iron's utility also means poorly regulated iron metabolism can lead to highly toxic free radicals <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Kell1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Maintaining the delicate balance of iron requires robust cellular and systemic regulation since both iron deficiency and overload can cause cell death <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Hentze1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Recent research has lead to a much greater understanding of the mechanisms controlling iron metabolism and a global view of the interactions between iron-related components is beginning to emerge <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Dunn1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Hower1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p><p>The liver has been proposed to play a central role in the regulation of iron homeostasis <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Frazer1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> through the action of the recently discovered hormone hepcidin <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Hepcidin is expressed predominantly in the liver <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Pigeon1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> and distributed in the serum to control systemic iron metabolism. Hepcidin acts on ferroportin to induce its degradation. Ferroportin is the sole iron exporting protein in mammalian cells <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-VanZandt1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, therefore hepcidin expression reduces iron export into the serum from enterocytes, and reduces iron export from the liver. Intracellular iron metabolism is controlled by the action of iron response proteins (IRPs) <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Hentze2" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. IRPs post-transcriptionally regulate mRNAs encoding proteins involved in iron metabolism. IRPs combined with ferritin and the transferrin receptors (TfR) make up the center of cellular iron regulation. Ferritin is the iron-storage protein forming a hollow shell which counters the toxic effects of free iron by storing iron atoms in a chemically less reactive ferrihydrite <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Harrison1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Extracellular iron circulates bound to transferrin (Tf), and is imported into the cell through the action of membrane bound proteins transferrin receptors 1 and 2 (TfR1 and TfR2). Human haemochromatosis protein (HFE) competes with transferrin-bound iron for binding to TfR1 and TfR2 <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>.</p><p>Systems Biology provides an excellent methodology for elucidating understanding, through computational modelling, of the complex iron metabolic network. A quantitative model of iron metabolism allows for a careful and principled examination of the effect of the various components of the network. Modelling allows one to do &#x0201c;what-if&#x0201d; experiments leading to new hypotheses that can later be put to test experimentally. However, no comprehensive model of liver iron metabolism exists to date. Models have been published that cover specific molecular events only, such as the loading of iron in ferritin <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. A qualitative map of mammalian iron metabolism provides a detailed overview of the molecular interactions involved in iron metabolism, including in specific cell types <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Hower1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Similarly, a detailed model of iron metabolism and oxidative stress was described but uses a Boolean approach and is specific for yeast <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Achcar1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Quantitative models of the iron network have been recently described <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chifman1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Mobilia1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, yet these include only a few components of the iron network. The model from Chifman <italic>et al.</italic> suggests that the dynamics of this iron network is stable <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chifman1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Large-scale models of the metabolism of the hepatocyte <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Gille1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Krauss1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and a generic human metabolism stoichiometric model <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Thiele1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> have also been published, but these contain only four reactions relating to iron metabolism. While they include iron transport, the receptors are not considered, and regulatory details are absent altogether.</p><p>Existing models are therefore at two extremes of detail: very specific and very generic &#x02014; but to address questions about hepatic iron regulation, what is desirable is a model that balances coverage and detail. This is the aim of the present work. One of the problems of modelling iron metabolism quantitatively and in detail arises from the lack of parameter values for many interactions. Recently, several of those parameters have been described in the literature (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t001">Table 1</xref>), particularly using technologies like surface plasmon resonance. This has enabled us to construct a detailed mechanistic kinetic model of human hepatocyte iron metabolism. The model has been validated by being able to reproduce data from several disease conditions &#x02014; importantly, these physiological data were not used in constructing the model. This validation provides a sense of confidence that the model is indeed appropriate for understanding liver iron regulation and for predicting the response to various environmental perturbations.</p><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003299-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Reactions, rate laws and kinetic constant values.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003299-t001-1" xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate law</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fpn Export</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIP&#x02192;Tf-Fe_intercell; FPN1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e001.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e002.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e003.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Sarkar1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02192; TfR; IRP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e004.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e005.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e006.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e007.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Johnson1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferroportin Expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02192; FPN1; IRP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function -|</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e008.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e009.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e010.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02192; IRP; LIP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function -|</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e011.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e012.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e013.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Pantopoulos1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e014.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Pantopoulos1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fpn degradation Hepc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPN1 &#x02192;; HAMP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e015.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e016.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e017.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e018.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Wang3" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02192; HFE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant flux</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e019.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Wang3" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02192; TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant flux</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e020.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 &#x02192;; Tf-Fe_intercell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function -|</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e021.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e022.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e023.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02192; HAMP; 2HFE-TfR2 2(Tf-Fe)-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e024.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e025.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e026.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e027.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e028.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Zaritsky1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAMP &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e029.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Rivera1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme oxygenation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme&#x02192;LIP; HO-1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Henri-Michaelis-Menten</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e030.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e031.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Kinobe1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE+TfR&#x02192;HFE-TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e032.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR&#x02192;HFE+TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e033.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe_intercell+TfR&#x02192;Tf-Fe-TfR1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e034.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe-TfR1&#x02192;Tf-Fe_intercell+TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e035.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR2 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2*HFE+TfR2&#x02192;2HFE-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e036.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR2 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2HFE-TfR2&#x02192;2 * HFE+TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e037.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe_intercell+TfR2&#x02192;Tf-Fe-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e038.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe-TfR2&#x02192;Tf-Fe_intercell+TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e039.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe-TfR1+Tf-Fe_intercell&#x02192;2(Tf-Fe)-TfR1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e040.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 release 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(Tf-Fe)-TfR1&#x02192;Tf-Fe-TfR1+Tf-Fe_intercell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e041.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR+HFE&#x02192;2HFE-TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e042.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 release 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2HFE-TfR&#x02192;HFE-TfR+HFE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e043.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe-TfR2+Tf-Fe_intercell&#x02192;2(Tf-Fe)-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e044.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 release 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(Tf-Fe)-TfR2&#x02192;Tf-Fe-TfR2+Tf-Fe_intercell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e045.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-West2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 iron internalisation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(Tf-Fe)-TfR1&#x02192;4(LIP)+TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e046.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Byrne1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 iron internalisation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(Tf-Fe)-TfR2&#x02192;4(LIP)-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e047.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Byrne1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">outFlow</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIP &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action (irreversible)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e048.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin Iron binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIP+FT&#x02192;Fe-FT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e049.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin Iron release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe-FT&#x02192;LIP+FT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e050.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin Iron internalisation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe-FT&#x02192;FT1+FT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e051.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin internalised iron release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT1&#x02192;LIP; FT1 FT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kloss Hill</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e052.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ferritin expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02192; FT; IRP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function -|</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e053.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e054.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e055.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Cozzi1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HO1 Degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HO-1 &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e056.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Pimstone1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HO1 Expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02192; HO-1; Heme</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hill Function &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e057.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e058.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Bao1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin Degradation Full</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e059.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme uptake</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme_intercell&#x02192;Heme</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Henri-Michaelis-Menten</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e060.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Shayeghi1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme export</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme&#x02192;Heme_intercell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Henri-Michaelis-Menten</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e061.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Tamura1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin Degradation Full Iron Release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT1&#x02192;LIP; FT1 FT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass Action Ferritin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e062.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2HFE-TfR &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e063.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR2 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2HFE-TfR2 &#x02192;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass action</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e064.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><p>Our model was constructed based on many published data on individual molecular interactions (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> section), and is available in Systems Biology Markup Language (SBML) and COPASI formats in supplementary data, as well as from BioModels (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://identifiers.org/biomodels.db/MODEL1302260000">http://identifiers.org/biomodels.db/MODEL1302260000</ext-link>) <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-LeNovre1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g001">Figure 1</xref> depicts a process diagram of the model, using the Systems Biology Graphical Notation (SBGN) standard <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Novere1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, where all the considered interactions are shown. It is important to highlight that while results described below are largely in agreement with observations, the model was not forced to replicate them. The extent of agreement between model and physiological data provides confidence that the model is accurate enough to carry out &#x0201c;what-if&#x0201d; type of experiments that can provide quantitative explanation of iron regulation in the liver.</p><fig id="pcbi-1003299-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>SBGN process diagram of human liver iron metabolism model.</title><p>The compartment with yellow boundary represents the hepatocyte, while the compartment with pink boundary represents plasma. Species overlayed on the compartment boundaries represent membrane-associated species. Abbreviations: Fe: iron, FPN1: ferroportin, FT: ferritin, HAMP: hepcidin, haeme: intracellular haeme, haeme_intercell: plasma haeme, HFE: human haemochromatosis protein, HO-1: haeme oxygenase 1, IRP: iron response protein, LIP: labile iron pool, Tf-Fe_intercell: plasma transferrin-bound iron, TfR1: transferrin receptor 1, TfR2: transferrin receptor 2. Complexes are represented in boxes with the component species. In the special case of the ferritin-iron complex symbol, the amounts of each species are not in stoichiometric amounts (since there are thousands of iron ions per ferritin).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.g001"/></fig><sec id="s2a"><title>Steady State</title><p>Initial validation of the model was performed by assessing the ability to recreate experimentally-observed steady-state concentrations of metabolites and rates of reactions. Simulations were run to steady state using the parameters and initial conditions from <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t002">2</xref>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t003">Table 3</xref> compares steady-state concentrations of metabolites and reaction rates with experimental observations.</p><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003299-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Initial conditions.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003299-t002-2" xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial Concentration (mol/l)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e065.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Epsztejn1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPN1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e066.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e067.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Haile1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAMP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e068.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Zaritsky1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">haeme</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e069.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(Tf-Fe)-TfR1_Internal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e070.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(Tf-Fe)-TfR2_Internal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e071.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe-TfR2_Internal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e072.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe-TfR1_Internal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e073.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-TfR1_Internal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e074.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-TfR2_Internal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e075.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe-FT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e076.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e077.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Cozzi1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HO-1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e078.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Mateo1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e079.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe_intercell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e080.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fixed, <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Johnson1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e081.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe-TfR1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e082.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e083.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e084.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e085.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tf-Fe-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e086.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(Tf-Fe)-TfR1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e087.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2HFE-TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e088.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2HFE-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e089.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(Tf-Fe)-TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e090.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e091.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">haeme_intercell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e092.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Sassa1" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Initial concentrations of all metabolites and the source for their value.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003299-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Steady state validation&#x02014;Comparison between model and experimental observations.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003299-t003-3" xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolite</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Labile Iron Pool</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e093.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e094.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Epsztejn1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron Response Protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e095.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e096.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Cairo1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e097.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e098.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e099.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Cairo1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>, <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Summers1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e100.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e101.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-SalterCid1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e102.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e103.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron per Ferritin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e104.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e105.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Sibille1" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e106.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e107.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Swinkels1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBI import rate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e108.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e109.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chua1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>IRP, Ferritin and TfR are expressed in particles per cell assuming a cellular volume of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e110.jpg"/></inline-formula> l. Iron per Ferritin is a ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Chua <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chua1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> injected radio-labeled transferrin-bound iron into the serum of mice and measured the total uptake of the liver after 120 minutes. The uptake rate, when expressed as mol/s, was close to that found at steady state by the computational model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>A technical aspect of note in this steady-state solution, is that it is very stiff. This originates because one section of the model is orders or magnitude faster than the rest: the cycle composed of iron binding to ferritin, internalization and release. Arguably this could be resolved by simplifying the model, but the model was left intact because this cycling is an important aspect of iron metabolism and allows the representation of ferritin saturation. Even though the stiffness is high, our software is able to cope by using an appropriate numerical method.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Response to Iron Challenge</title><p>An oral dose of iron creates a fluctuation in serum transferrin saturation of approximately 10% <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Girelli1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. The fixed serum iron concentration in the simulation was replaced by a transient increase in concentration equivalent to a 10% increase in transferrin saturation as a simulation of oral iron dosage on hepatocytes. The simulated hepcidin response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g002">Figure 2</xref>) is consistent with the hepcidin response measured by Girelli <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Girelli1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. The time scale and dynamics of the hepcidin response to iron challenge has been accurately replicated in the simulation presented here. Although the exact dynamics of the simulated response is not validated by either experimental technique (mass spectrometry or ELISA) the simulation appears to present an approximation of the two experimental techniques reaching a peak between 4 and 8 hours and returning to around basal levels within 24 hours.</p><fig id="pcbi-1003299-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Simulated time course concentrations of hepcidin in response to changing serum transferrin-bound iron levels.</title><p>The model shows similar dynamics to time course samples from patients measured by mass spectrometry and ELISA by Girelli <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011 <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Girelli1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Hereditary haemochromatosis simulations show reduced hepcidin levels and peak response compared to WT (Wild Type).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Cellular Iron Regulation</title><p>The computational model supports the proposed role of HFE and TFR2 as sensors of systemic iron. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g003">Figure 3B</xref> shows that as the concentration of HFE bound to TfR2 (HFE-TfR2) increases with serum transferrin-bound iron (Tf-Fe_intercell), at the same time the abundance of HFE bound to TfR1 (HFE-TfR1) decreases. The increase in HFE-TfR2 complex, even though of small magnitude, promotes increased expression of hepcidin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). It is through this mechanism that liver cells sense serum iron levels and control whole body iron metabolism through the action of hepcidin. Although the labile iron pool increases with serum transferrin-bound iron in this simulation, this is only because the model does not include the action of hepcidin in reducing duodenal export of iron. Expression and secretion of hepcidin will have a global effect of reducing the labile iron pool.</p><fig id="pcbi-1003299-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Simulated steady state concentrations of metabolites in response to increasing serum Tf-Fe.</title><p>Increasing HFE-TfR2 complex as a result of HFE-TfR1 reduction induces increased hepcidin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Hereditary Haemochromatosis Simulation</title><p>Hereditary haemochromatosis is the most common hereditary disorder with a prevalence higher than 1 in 500 <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Asberg1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Type 1 haemochromatosis is the most common and is caused by a mutation in the HFE gene leading to a misregulation of hepcidin and consequent systemic iron overload.</p><p>A virtual HFE knockdown was performed by reducing 100-fold the rate constant for HFE synthesis in the model, to create a simulation of type 1 hereditary haemochromatosis. The simulation was run to steady state and results were compared with experimental findings.</p><p>Qualitative validation showed the <italic>in silico</italic> HFE knockdown could reproduce multiple experimental findings as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t004">Table 4</xref>. Quantitatively the model was unable to reproduce accurately the finding that <italic>Hfe &#x02212;/&#x02212;</italic> mice have 3 times higher hepatic iron levels <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Fleming1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. This was due to the fixed intercellular transferrin-bound iron concentration in the model, unlike in <italic>Hfe &#x02212;/&#x02212;</italic> mice where there is an increase in transferrin saturation as a result of increased intestinal iron absorption <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Fleming1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Despite fixed extracellular conditions the model predicted an intracellular hepatocyte iron overload which would be further compounded by the systemic effects of the misregulation of hepcidin. The simulation recreated increased ferroportin levels despite the expression of ferroportin remaining the same as wild type which was consistent with mRNA measurements from Ludwiczek <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Ludwiczek1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. mRNA based experiments can be used to validate expression rates and protein assays are able to validate steady state protein concentrations as both expression rates and steady state protein concentrations are available as results from the computational model. The model of haemochromatosis was also able to replicate the dynamics of experimental responses to changing dietary iron conditions. An approximate 2-fold increase in hepatic ferroportin expression is caused by increased dietary iron in both haemochromatosis and healthy mice <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Ludwiczek1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. The model presented here recreated this increase with increasing intercellular iron as can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g004">Figure 4</xref>.</p><fig id="pcbi-1003299-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Ferroportin expression rate in the model doubles in response to changing serum iron concentrations as verified experimentally.</title><p>HFE knock-down (HH) simulations and WT simulation of Fe-Tf against ferroportin (Fpn) expression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003299-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>HFE knockout validation&#x02014;The simulation of type-1 hereditary haemochromatosis closely matches experimental findings at steady state.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003299-t004-4" xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolite</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Riedel1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Riedel1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAMP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-vanDijk1" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Robb1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1/2 iron import</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Riedel1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Riedel1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Riedel1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPN expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02248;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Ludwiczek1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>HFE knockout has been shown to impair the induction of hepcidin by iron in mouse <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Ludwiczek1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> and human <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Piperno1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> hepatocytes and this was seen in the computational model as increasing transferrin-bound iron did not induce hepcidin as strongly as in HFE knockdown.</p><p>Although an increase in transferrin receptor 2 was observed in the model (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e111.jpg"/></inline-formula> healthy; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e112.jpg"/></inline-formula> type 1 haemochromatosis), the up-regulation was slightly smaller than the change observed in vivo <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Robb1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. This is due to the model having fixed extracellular transferrin-bound iron concentration, in contrast to haemochromatosis where this concentration increases due to higher absorption in the intestine.</p><p>Type 3 haemochromatosis results in similar phenotype as type 1 haemochromatosis, however the mutation is found in the TfR2 gene as opposed to HFE. A virtual TfR2 knockdown mutation was performed by decreasing 100-fold the rate constant of synthesis of TfR2 from the model. Model results were then compared with the findings of Chua <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chua1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. The simulation showed a steady state decrease of liver TfR1 from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e113.jpg"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e114.jpg"/></inline-formula> with TfR2 knockdown. This is supported by an approximate halving of TfR1 levels in TfR2 mutant mice <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chua1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. An increase in hepcidin and consequent decrease in ferroportin as seen in mice was matched by the simulation.</p><p>An iron overload phenotype with increased intracellular iron is not recreated by the model of the TfR2 mutant. This is, again, due to the fixed serum transferrin-bound iron concentration, while in the whole body there would be increased iron absorption from the diet through the effect of hepcidin.</p><sec id="s2d1"><title>Metabolic control analysis</title><p>Metabolic control analysis (MCA) is a standard technique to identify the reactions that have the largest influence on metabolite concentrations or reaction fluxes in a steady state <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Kacser1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Heinrich1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. MCA is a special type of sensitivity analysis and thus is used to quantify the distributed control of the biochemical network. A control coefficient measures the relative change of the variable of interest caused by a small change in the reaction rate (e.g. a control coefficient can be interpreted as the percentage change of the variable given a 1% change in the reaction rate).</p><p>The control over the concentration of the labile iron pool by each of the model reactions can be seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t005">Table 5</xref>. The synthesis and degradation of TfR2, TfR1, HFE and the formation of their complexes were found to have the highest control over the labile iron pool. Synthesis and degradation of IRP was also found to have some degree of control, but synthesis and degradation of hepcidin have surprisingly a very small effect on the labile iron pool.</p><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003299-t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Metabolic control analysis&#x02014;Concentration control coefficients for the labile iron pool.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003299-t005-5" xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.t005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Local</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Global</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894573</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.515971</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41255</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fpn Export</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.825483</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.924</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.698754</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.569815</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.298433</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901285</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.563132</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.898362</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.293111</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fpn degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.351397</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186176</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50289</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferroportin Expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.351397</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.502317</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.176245</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.313525</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.623067</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346532</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259758</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0652</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.496352</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259436</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06577</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.497636</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.258004</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.503067</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0657364</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP expresion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209893</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0748546</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.209893</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.347477</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0753367</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR2 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0341692</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.684936</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000229851</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0283652</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004375</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6553120</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0283652</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.791216</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000576136</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0162284</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0259426</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0386967</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0100938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.298433</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901285</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0100938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0194113</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00434313</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR2 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00668253</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0187053</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0218869</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR2 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0063856</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0205303</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018034</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 iron internalisation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00335169</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.156882</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000557494</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00143167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0120993</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000742</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00143166</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000760</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0121124</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00143166</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0121238</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0000739</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 release 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00143165</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000738</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0121135</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00143165</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0121249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0000737</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The control over the hepcidin concentration was also calculated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t006">Table 6</xref>), as the ability to control hepatic hepcidin levels could provide therapeutic opportunities to control whole system iron metabolism, due to its action on other tissues. Interestingly, in addition to the expression and degradation of hepcidin itself, the expression of HFE and degradation of HFETfR2 complex have almost as much control over hepcidin. The expression of TfR2 has a considerably lower effect, though still significant.</p><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003299-t006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Metabolic control analysis&#x02014;Concentration control coefficients for hepcidin.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003299-t006-6" xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.t006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Local</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Global</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512257</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.487664</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.00002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.00027</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.999001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR2 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.956041</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3943</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.380497</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9131</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274035</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30051</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243052</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0984356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.486305</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.153001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.293528</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0638787</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128436</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0558287</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.273304</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 iron internalisation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.128062</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.272967</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0557919</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.047263</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.102578</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0122656</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR2 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0245645</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00630724</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0573883</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR2 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.023473</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0557905</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00602681</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00227514</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000811688</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00589495</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00227514</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00589437</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000812498</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00093303</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00728765</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.22895e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000933028</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84169e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00697082</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000933028</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0073373</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.31758e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 release 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000933018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3417e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00731269</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000933018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00733725</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.69006e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000796332</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00607511</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.36181e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000790955</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.53395e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00623214</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP expresion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000544238</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00281211</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.71681e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000544238</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16666e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00351147</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fpn export</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00045206</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00277642</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.33404e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fpn degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000192436</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47897e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00153538</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferroportin expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000192436</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00153463</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.41905e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000142075</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78713e-06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00137383</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 release 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.36921e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000176906</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.18216e-05</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Flux control coefficients were also determined which indicate the control that reactions have on a chosen reaction flux. The flux control coefficients for the ferroportin mediated iron export reaction are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t007">Table 7</xref>. This reaction is of particular interest as it is the only method of iron export, therefore controlling this reaction rate could be important in treating various iron disorders including haemochromatosis and anemia. The reactions of synthesis and degradation of TfR1, TfR2 and HFE were found to have high control, despite not having direct interactions with ferroportin. TfR1 and TfR2 may show consistently high control due to having dual roles as iron importers and iron sensors which control hepcidin expression.</p><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003299-t007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.t007</object-id><label>Table 7</label><caption><title>Metabolic control analysis&#x02014;Flux-control coefficients for the iron export out of the liver compartment.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003299-t007-7" xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.t007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Local</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Global</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.910944</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449405</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38521</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.581149</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285737</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867434</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.573438</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.858215</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.278218</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.353566</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.669513</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.187987</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.266964</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0676606</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.510467</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.266601</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0675083</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51963</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR1 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.265162</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.51689</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0669265</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP expresion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182446</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063823</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310888</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRP degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.182446</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.313848</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0656558</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fpn Export</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151719</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0626056</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271594</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferroportin Expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0645849</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0189112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149717</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fpn degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0645849</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.149993</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0189094</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0183009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00812358</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0401559</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0102946</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.018781</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00414945</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TfR2 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0102946</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00414543</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0187846</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR2 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0077113</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0191638</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00292511</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR2 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00736866</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00282598</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0186586</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00521336</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1785377</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0000387334</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepcidin degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00521336</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77312e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224586</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE-TfR2 degradation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00226218</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0183295</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19571</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00143917</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0119501</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.50839e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 release</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00143917</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.49065e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0119095</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 binding 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.00143917</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0114124</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.49686e-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFE TfR1 release 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00143915</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.49046e-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0116242</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>A drawback of MCA, and any other local sensitivity analysis, is that it is only predictive for small changes of reaction rates. However, the changes that result in disease states are usually large, and experimental parameter estimation can result in large uncertainty. Thus a global sensitivity analysis was also performed following the method described in <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Sahle1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. This calculates the maximal and minimal values of the sensitivity coefficients within a large space of parameter values. This technique is useful, for example, if there is uncertainty about the values of the model parameters as it reveals the possible range of control of each one given the uncertainty. All parameters were allowed to vary simultaneously within <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e115.jpg"/></inline-formula> and the maximal and minimal control coefficients were measured (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t005">Tables 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t006">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t007">7</xref>).</p><p>In terms of the control of the labile iron pool (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t005">Table 5</xref>), the reactions with highest control in the reference steady state are still the ones with highest control in the global case (<italic>i.e.</italic> when all parameters have an uncertainty of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e116.jpg"/></inline-formula>). However TfR1 expression, TfR1 binding, TfR1 degradation, IRP expression and IRP degradation, which all have significant (but not the highest) control in the reference state, could have very low control in the global sense. On the other hand HFETfR2 degradation, hepcidin expression, hepcidin degradation and TfR2 binding 2, have low control in the reference steady state, but could have significant control in the global sense. All other reactions have low control in any situation.</p><p>In the case of the control of hepcidin concentration (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t006">Table 6</xref>) the differences between the reference state and the global are much smaller overall, and one could only identify a few reactions that have moderate control in the reference, but could have a bit less in the global sense (TfR2 expression, TfR2 binding, and TfR2 iron internalisation).</p><p>In the case of the control of the flux of iron export (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t007">Table 7</xref>), we find some reactions with high control in the reference that could have low control in the global sense: TfR1 expression, TfR1 biding, TfR1 degradation, IRP expression and IRP degradation. Hepcidin expression, hepcidin degradation, and HFETfR2 degradation have almost no control in the reference, but in the global sense they could exert considerable control. This is very similar to the situation of the control of the labile iron pool.</p><p>Chifman <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chifman1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> analysed the parameter space of their core model of iron metabolism in breast epithelial cells and concluded the system behavior is far more dependent on the network structure than the exact parameters used. The analysis presented here lends some support to that finding, since only a few reactions could have different effect on the system if the parameters are wrong. A further scan of initial conditions for metabolites found that varying initial concentrations over 2 orders of magnitude had no affect on the steady state achieved (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t003">Table 3</xref>), indicating that the steady state found in these simulations is possibly unique.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Receptor Properties</title><p>It is known that the iron sensing by the transferrin receptors is responsive over a wide range of intercellular iron concentrations <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. The present model reproduces this well (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g005">Figure 5</xref>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e117.jpg"/></inline-formula>). Becker <italic>et al.</italic> argued that a linear response of a receptor to its signal over a wide range could be achieved through a combination of: high receptor abundance, increased expression when required, recycling to the surface of internalised receptors and high receptor turnover <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. This was illustrated with the behaviour of the erythropoietin (EPO) receptor <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Since the present model contains essentially the same type of reactions that can lead to such a behaviour, simulations were carried out to investigate to what extent this linearity of response is present here. In this case it is the response of the total amount of all forms of TfR1 and TfR2 bound to Tf-Fe against the amount of Tf-Fe_intercell that is important. A variable was created in the model to reflect the total receptor response (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>), and this variable was followed in a time course response to an iron pulse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g006">Figure 6</xref>). The response to the iron pulse is remarkably similar to the response of the EPO receptor to EPO <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>.</p><fig id="pcbi-1003299-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Increasing receptor turnover increases the linearity of the response for transferrin receptor 1.</title><p>The range of linear response for the transferrin receptor depends on its half-life. This effect was first demonstrated in the EPO receptor by Becker <italic>et al.</italic> 2010 <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> who found similar behavior (compare to their <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.g005"/></fig><fig id="pcbi-1003299-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Iron and Epo receptors show a similar response following an impulse of ligand.</title><p>Ligand receptor binding for iron shows a distinctive curve which closely resembles EPO receptor binding studied by Becker <italic>et al.</italic> 2010 <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> (their <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.g006"/></fig><p>Becker et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> reported that the linearity of EPO-R response, <italic>i.e.</italic> the integral of the response curve, is increased by increasing turnover rate of the receptor and this property was also observed in the simulation of TfR1 response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The range in which the iron response is linear is smaller than that found for EPO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g005">Figure 5</xref>). As TfR1's half life in the model matches the experimentally determined value <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> the non-linear receptor response seen in the simulation is expected to be accurate. This suggests that TfR1 is a poor sensor for high levels of intercellular iron. On the other hand TfR2 is more abundant than TfR1 <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> and accordingly shows an increased linearity for a greater range of intercellular iron concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g007">Figure 7</xref>). This suggests the two transferrin receptors play different roles in sensing intercellular iron levels with TfR2 providing a wide range of sensing and TfR1 sensing smaller perturbations. The activation of TfR2 directly influences the expression of hepcidin and therefore it is desirable for it to sense large systemic imbalances. TfR1 does not modulate hepcidin expression itself instead it plays a primary role as an iron transporter.</p><fig id="pcbi-1003299-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003299.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>TfR2 response <italic>versus</italic> intercellular transferrin-bound iron.</title><p>The response is approximately linear over a wide range of intercellular iron concentrations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.g007"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Iron is an essential element of life, in humans it is involved in oxygen transport, respiration, biosynthesis, detoxification, and other processes. Iron regulation is essential because iron deficiency results in debilitating anemia, while iron excess leads to free radical generation and is involved in many diseases <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Kell1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. It is clear that healthy life depends on tight regulation of iron in the body. The mechanisms involved in iron absortion, transport, storage and regulation form a complex biochemical network <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Hower1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. The liver has a central role in the regulation of systemic iron metabolism through secretion of the peptide hormone hepcidin.</p><p>Here we analysed the hepatic biochemical network involved in iron sensing and regulation through a mathematical model and computer simulation. The model was constructed mostly based on <italic>in vitro</italic> biochemical data, such as protein complex dissociation constants. The model was then validated by comparison with experimental data from multiple physiological studies at both steady state and during dynamic responses. Where quantitative data were available the model matched these well and also qualitatively recreated many findings from clinical and experimental investigations. The simulation accurately modelled the highly prevalent iron disorder haemochromatosis. The disease state was simulated through altering a single parameter of the model and showed quantitatively how an iron overload phenotype occurs in patients with a HFE mutation.</p><p>Due to the limited availability of quantitative clinical data on human iron metabolism, various other data sources, particularly from <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments and animal models, were integrated for the parameterisation of this model. This computational modelling effort constitutes a clinical translational approach, enabling data from multiple sources to improve our understanding of human iron metabolism. Several arguments could be raised to cast doubt on this approach, such as the the failure of <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions to mimic those <italic>in vivo</italic> or the difference between animal models and humans. This means that this type of data integration must be carefully monitored in terms of establishing the validity of the resulting model. Examining the behaviour of the model by simulating it at different values of initial conditions or other parameters (parameter scans) is important to establish the limits of utility of the model. Global sensitivity analysis is another approach that determines the boundaries of parameter variation that the model tolerates before it becomes too distant from the actual system behaviour. Model validation is an essential step in modelling. Validation should be carried out by enquiring if the model is able to match experimental observations that were not used to calibrate it. Here the model was validated by the simulation of haemochromatosis disease, where the model behaviour matched the clinical data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t004">Table 4</xref>).</p><p>The precise regulatory mechanism behind transferrin receptors and HFE controlling hepcidin expression remains to be validated experimentally, however the model presented here supports current understanding that the interaction of TfR2 and HFE form the signal transduction pathway that leads to the induction of hepcidin expression <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Gao1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>.</p><p>The global metabolic control analysis results support the identification of the transferrin receptors, particularly TfR2, and HFE as potential therapeutic targets; a result that is robust even to inaccuracies in parameter values. Although hepcidin would be an intuitive point of high control of this system (and therefore a good therapeutic target), in the present model this is not the case. It seems that targeting the promoters of hepcidin expression may be more desirable. However this conclusion has to be expressed with some reservation that stems from the fact that the global sensitivity analysis identified the hepcidin synthesis and degradation reactions in the group of those with the largest uncertainty. By changing parameter values by no more than 10% it would be possible to have the hepcidin expression and degradation show higher control. So it seems important that the expression of hepcidin be studied in more detail. We also predict that the control of hepcidin over the system would be higher if the model had included the regulation of intestinal ferroportin by hepatic ferroportin.</p><p>The global sensitivity analysis, however, allows taking strong conclusions about the reactions for which the reference steady state is not much different from the maximal and minimal values. It turns out that these are the reactions that have the largest and the smallest control over the system variables. For example, the reactions with greatest control on the labile iron pool and iron export are those of the HFE-TfR2 system. But the reactions of the HFE-TfR1 system have always low control. These two conclusions are valid <italic>under a wide range of parameter values</italic>.</p><p>Construction of this model required several assumptions to be made due to lack of measured parameter values, as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. These assumptions may or may not have a large impact on the model behaviour, and it is important to identify those that have a large impact, as their measurement will improve our knowledge the most. Of all the assumptions made, the rates of expression and degradation of ferroportin are those that have a significant impact on the labile iron pool in the model (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t005">Table 5</xref>). This means that if the values assumed for these rate parameters were to be significantly different the model prediction for labile iron pool behaviour would also be different. The model is therefore also useful by suggesting experiments that will optimally improve our knowledge about this system.</p><p>Limitations on the predictive power of the model occur due to the scope of the system chosen. Fixed serum iron conditions, which were used as boundary conditions in the model, do not successfully recreate the amplifying feedbacks that occur as a result of hepcidin expression controlling enterocyte iron export. To relieve this limitation, a more advanced model should include dietary iron uptake and the action of hepcidin on that process.</p><p>The model predicts a quasi-linear response to increasing pulses of serum iron, similar to what has been predicted for the erythropoietin system <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Our simulations display response of the transferrin receptors to pulses of extracellular transferrin-bound iron that is similar to the EPO-R response to EPO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The integral of this response <italic>versus</italic> the iron sensed deviates very little from linearity in the range of physiological iron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g006">Figure 6</xref>).</p><p>Computational models are research tools whose function is to allow for reasoning in a complex nonlinear system. The present model can be useful in terms of predicting properties of the liver iron system. These predictions form hypotheses that lead to new experiments. Their outcome will undoubtedly improve our knowledge and will also either confirm the accuracy of the model or refute it (in which case it then needs to be corrected). The present model and its results identified a number of predictions about liver iron regulation that should be investigated further:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>changes in activity of the hepcidin gene in the liver have little effect on the size of the labile iron pool,</p></list-item><list-item><p>the rate of expression of HFE has a high control over the steady state level of hepcidin,</p></list-item><list-item><p>the strong effect of HFE is due to its interaction with TfR2 rather than TfR1,</p></list-item><list-item><p>the rate of liver iron export by ferroportin has a strong dependence on the expression of TfR1, TfR2 and HFE,</p></list-item><list-item><p>the rate of expression of hepcidin is approximately linear with the concentration of plasma iron within the physiological range.</p></list-item></list><p>The present model is the most detailed quantitative mechanistic model of cellular iron metabolism to date, allowing for a comprehensive description of its regulation. It can be used to elucidate the link from genotype to phenotype, as demonstrated here with hereditary haemochromatosis. The model provides the ability to investigate scenarios for which there are currently no experimental data available &#x02014; thus making predictions about the system and aiding in experimental design.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>The model is constructed using ordinary differential equations (ODEs) to represent the rate of change of each chemical species. COPASI <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Hoops1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> was used as the software framework for model construction, simulation and analysis. Cell Designer <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Funahashi1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref> was used for construction of a SBGN process diagram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003299-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>The model consists of 2 compartments representing the serum and the liver. Concentrations of haeme and transferrin-bound iron in the serum were fixed to represent constant extracellular conditions. Fixed metabolites simulate a constant influx of iron through the diet as any iron absorbed by the liver is effectively replenished. A labile iron pool (LIP) consumption reaction is added to represent various uses of iron and create a flow through the system. Some of the LIP consumption reaction would be attributed to heme biosynthesis however this process was not considered explicitly in this study to avoid unnecessary complexity and because the bone marrow is the major site of heme biosynthesis <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Ajioka1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>.</p><p>Initial concentrations for metabolites were set to appropriate concentrations based on a literature survey (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t002">Table 2</xref>). All metabolites formed through complex binding were set to zero initial concentrations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t002">Table 2</xref>). The concentration of a chemical species at a time point in the simulation is determined by integrating the system of ODEs. For some proteins a half-life was available in the literature, but sources could not be found for their synthesis rates (translation). In this occurrence, estimated steady-state concentrations were used from the literature and a synthesis rate was chosen such that at steady state the concentration of the protein would be approximately accurate, following <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003299.e118">Equation 1</xref>:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e118"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e118.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>This is solved for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e119.jpg"/></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e120.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the steady-state concentration of the protein and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e121.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the degradation rate obtained from the half-life (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e122.jpg"/></inline-formula>) using:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e123"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e123.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>Complex formation reactions, such as binding of TfR1 to Tf-Fe for iron uptake, are modelled using the on and off binding constants as a forward and reverse mass action reaction. For example:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e124"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e124.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>is modelled using two reactions:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e125"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e125.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e126"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e126.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>There is one ODE per each chemical species. The two reactions 4 and 5 add the following terms to the set of ODEs:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e127"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e127.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>Intracellular haeme levels are controlled by a balance between uptake, export and oxygenation. haeme import through the action of haeme carrier protein 1 (HCP1), export by ATP-binding cassette sub-family G member 2 (ABCG2) and oxygenation by haeme oxygenase-1 (HO-1) follow Michaelis-Menten kinetics. HO-1 expression is promoted by haeme through by a Hill function (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003299.e128">Equation (7)</xref>).<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e128"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e128.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e129"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e129.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>Where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e130.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the substrate, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e131.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the modifier, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e132.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the turnover number, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e133.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the ligand concentration which produces half occupancy of the binding sites of the enzyme, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e134.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the Hill coefficient. Values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e135.jpg"/></inline-formula> larger than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e136.jpg"/></inline-formula> produce positive cooperativity (<italic>i.e.</italic> a sigmoidal response); when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e137.jpg"/></inline-formula> the response is the same as Michaelis-Menten kinetics. A Hill coefficient of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e138.jpg"/></inline-formula> was assumed unless there is literature evidence for a different value. Where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e139.jpg"/></inline-formula> is not known it has been estimated to be of the order of magnitude of experimentally observed concentrations for the ligand.</p><p>IRP/Iron-responsive elements (IRE) regulation is represented by Hill kinetics using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003299.e128">Equation (7)</xref> to simulate the 3&#x02032; binding of IRP promoting the translation rate, and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003299.e129">Equation (8)</xref> to represent the 5&#x02032; binding of IRP reducing the translation rate. Ferroportin degradation is modelled using 2 reactions: one representing the standard half-life and the other representing the hepcidin-induced degradation. A Hill equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003299.e128">Equation 7</xref>) is used to simulate the hepcidin-induced degradation of ferroportin.</p><p>Hepcidin expression is the only reaction modelled using a Hill coefficient greater than 1. Due to the small dynamic range of HFE-TfR2 concentrations a Hill coefficient of 5 was chosen to provide the sensitivity required to produce the expected range of hepcidin concentrations. The mechanism by which HFE-TfR2 interactions induce hepcidin expression is not well understood, but is thought to involve the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signalling pathway <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Wallace1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. The stimulus/response curve of the MAPK cascade has been found to be equivalent to a cooperative enzyme with a Hill coefficient of 4&#x02013;5 <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Huang1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, making the steep Hill function appropriate to model hepcidin expression.</p><p>Ferritin modelling follows the work of Salgado <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Iron from the LIP binds to, and is internalised in, ferritin with mass action kinetics. Internalised iron release from ferritin occurs through 2 reactions (intact ferritin release and release due to ferritin degradation). The average amount of iron internalised per ferritin affects the iron release rate and this is modelled using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003299.e140">Equation 9</xref> (adapted from <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>):<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e140"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e140.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>Where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e141.jpg"/></inline-formula> is internalised iron, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e142.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the rate constant and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e143.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the ratio of iron internalised in ferritin to total ferritin available. The value 0.0048 was obtained by dividing the value given in Salgado <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> by 50 as that simulation was scaled for 50 iron atom packages.</p><p>Iron is also released from ferritin when the entire ferritin cage is degraded. The kinetics of ferritin degradation are mass action, however the amount of iron released when a ferritin cage is degraded is an average based on ferritin levels and total iron internalised in ferritin. Incorporating mass action and ferritin saturation ratio gives the following rate law for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e144.jpg"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e145"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e145.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>Iron export rate was modelled using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003299.e128">Equation 7</xref> with ferroportin as the modifier and a Hill coefficient of 1. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e146.jpg"/></inline-formula> was assumed to be around the steady state concentration of IRP (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e147.jpg"/></inline-formula>). A rate (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e148.jpg"/></inline-formula>) of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e149.jpg"/></inline-formula> was used from Sarkar <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Sarkar1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> and these values were substituted into the equation and solved for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e150.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>Ferroportin expression rates and degradation rates are poorly understood. Ferroportin abundance data <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> lead to an estimate of ferroportin concentration around <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e151.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The hepcidin induced degradation of ferroportin is represented in the model by a rate law in the form of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003299.e128">Equation 7</xref> with a Hill coefficient <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e152.jpg"/></inline-formula> (see above) and a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e153.jpg"/></inline-formula> equal to the measured concentration of hepcidin <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Zaritsky1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003299-t002">Table 2</xref>). We then assume a maximal rate of degradation to be <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e154.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and using the steady state concentration of ferroportin, the rate constant can be estimated as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e155.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The ferroportin synthesis rate was then calculated to produce the required steady-state concentration of ferroportin at the nominal hepcidin concentration.</p><p>The HFE-TfR2 binding and dissociation constants were also not available and so it was assumed that they were the same as those of TfR1-HFE. Finally, the HFE-TfR and HFE-TfR2 degradation rates are also not known; we used a value that is an order of magnitude lower than the half life for unbound TfR (<italic>i.e.</italic> we assume the complex to be more stable than the free form of TfR).</p><p>Although DMT1 may contribute towards transferrin-bound iron uptake in hepatocytes this contribution has been found to be minor and DMT1 knockout has little affect on iron metabolism <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Wang2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, therefore DMT1 was not included in the model.</p><p>The two iron response proteins (IRP1 and IRP2), which are responsible for cellular iron regulation, were modelled as a single pool in this study as the mechanistic differences in their regulatory roles are poorly understood. Equivalent regulation by both IRPs has been found in multiple studies <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Erlitzki1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.</p><p>Global sensitivity analysis was performed using the method proposed by Sahle <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Sahle1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, where all parameter values were allowed to vary within <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e156.jpg"/></inline-formula> of their nominal value in the model and we search for the maximum and minimum value that concentration- or flux-control coefficients of interest are able to reach within that parameter space. The searches were carried out with the particle swarm optimisation algorithm <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Kennedy1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. In order to process these optimisations in a reasonable time a HTCondor <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Litzkow1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref> distributed computing system was used, managed through the Condor-COPASI package <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Kent1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>.</p><p>To perform analysis of receptor response in a similar manner to the EPO system studied by Becker <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> initial conditions were adjusted to recreate a similar virtual experiment. Haeme concentration was fixed at zero to isolate transferrin-bound iron uptake. The rate constant of the labile iron pool depletion reaction was reduced to balance the reduced iron uptake (which results in iron having a similar half-life to EPO in <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>). Initial concentrations for all metabolites were set to steady-state concentrations with the exception of the labile iron pool and iron bound to all receptors which were set to zero. Extracellular transferrin-bound iron was set at increasing concentrations to determine receptor response. Time courses were calculated for Tf-Fe-TfR1, 2(Tf-Fe)-TfR1, Tf-Fe-TfR2 and 2(Tf-Fe)-TfR2 as iron binds its two receptors in a two-staged process. Two new variables were defined in COPASI which integrated the results of the time courses corresponding to the two receptors (in their different ligand states):<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e157"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e157.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003299.e158"><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.e158.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1003299.s001"><label>Model S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Model in SBML format.</bold> This SBML l2v4 file encodes the model described in the text and can be loaded into any SBML-compatible software.</p><p>(ZIP)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.s001.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1003299.s002"><label>Model S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Model in COPASI format.</bold> This CopasiML file encodes the model described in the text and can be loaded into the COPASI software <xref rid="pcbi.1003299-Hoops1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> which was used for all the simulations described here.</p><p>(ZIP)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1003299.s002.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Steve Ackman, Douglas Kell, Reinhard Laubenbacher, Frank Torti and Suzy Torti for many discussions. We thank Ed Kent and the EPS IT Research Services staff for help with running the HTCondor pool. We also thank Anthony West for sharing binding data for HFE, TfR1 and TfR2. SM is grateful to the Virginia Bioinformatics Institute and the Wake Forest University Department of Cancer Biology for hosting visits.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Aisen1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Aisen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Enns</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wessling-Resnick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Chemistry and biology of eukaryotic iron metabolism</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>940</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>959</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-TussingHumphreys1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tussing-Humphreys</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pustacioglu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Braunschweig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Rethinking iron regulation and assessment in iron deficiency, anemia of chronic disease, and obesity: introducing hepcidin</article-title>. <source>J Acad Nutrition Dietetics</source>
<volume>112</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Kell1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Iron behaving badly: inappropriate iron chelation as a major contributor to the aetiology of vascular and other progressive inflammatory and degenerative diseases</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Genomics</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19133145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Hentze1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hentze</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muckenthaler</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Balancing acts: molecular control of mammalian iron metabolism</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>117</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15109490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Dunn1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rahmanto</surname><given-names>YSS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Iron uptake and metabolism in the new millennium</article-title>. <source>Trends Cell Biol</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17194590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Hower1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hower</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Torti</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laubenbacher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A general map of iron metabolism and tissue-specific subnetworks</article-title>. <source>Mol BioSystems</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>443</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Frazer1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The orchestration of body iron intake: how and where do enterocytes receive their cues</article-title>? <source>Blood Cells, Molecules &#x00026; Diseases</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Park1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valore</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waring</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Hepcidin, a urinary antimicrobial peptide synthesized in the liver</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>276</volume>: <fpage>7806</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7810</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11113131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Pigeon1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pigeon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ilyin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Courselaud</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leroyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turlin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A new mouse liver-specific gene, encoding a protein homologous to human antimicrobial peptide hepcidin, is overexpressed during iron overload</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>276</volume>: <fpage>7811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7819</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11113132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-VanZandt1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Van Zandt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sow</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Florence</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zwilling</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Satoskar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The iron export protein ferroportin 1 is differentially expressed in mouse macrophage populations and is present in the mycobacterial-containing phagosome</article-title>. <source>J Leukocyte Biol</source>
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>700</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18586980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Hentze2"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hentze</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>K&#x000fc;hn</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Molecular control of vertebrate iron metabolism: mRNA-based regulatory circuits operated by iron, nitric oxide, and oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>8175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8710843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Harrison1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Ferritin: an iron-storage molecule</article-title>. <source>Sem Hematol</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-West1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giannetti</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nangiana</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Mutational analysis of the transferrin receptor reveals overlapping HFE and transferrin binding sites</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>313</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11800564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Salgado1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Salgado</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nappa</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerdtzen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tapia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Mathematical modeling of the dynamic storage of iron in ferritin</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21047430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Achcar1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Achcar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Camadro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mestivier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A Boolean probabilistic model of metabolic adaptation to oxygen in relation to iron homeostasis and oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21489274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Chifman1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chifman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kniss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The core control system of intracellular iron homeostasis: a mathematical model</article-title>. <source>J Theoret Biol</source>
<volume>300</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22286016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Mobilia1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mobilia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donz&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moulis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fanchon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A model of the cellular iron homeostasis network using semi-formal methods for parameter space exploration</article-title>. <source>Electronic Proceedings in Theoretical Computer Science</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Gille1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gille</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bolling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bulik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>HepatoNet1: a comprehensive metabolic reconstruction of the human hepatocyte for the analysis of liver physiology</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20823849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Krauss1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borchers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Findeisen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lippert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Integrating cellular metabolism into a multiscale whole-body model</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002750</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23133351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Thiele1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swainston</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>RMT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A community-driven global reconstruction of human metabolism</article-title>. <source>Nature Biotechnol</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23455439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-LeNovre1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Le Nov&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broicher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Courtot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donizelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>BioModels database: a free, centralized database of curated, published, quantitative kinetic models of biochemical and cellular systems</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>D689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D691</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Novere1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Novere</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hucka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moodie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Systems Biology Graphical Notation</article-title>. <source>Nature Biotechnol</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>741</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19668183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Chua1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delima</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herbison</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tirnitz-Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Iron uptake from plasma transferrin by a transferrin receptor 2 mutant mouse model of haemochromatosis</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>431</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Girelli1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Girelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trombini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Busti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campostrini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sandri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A time course of hepcidin response to iron challenge in patients with HFE and TFR2 hemochromatosis</article-title>. <source>Haematologica</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>506</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21173098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Asberg1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Asberg</collab> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Screening for hemochromatosis: High prevalence and low morbidity in an unselected population of 65,238 persons</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian J Gastroenterol</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1115</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Fleming1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomatsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waheed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunt</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Mouse strain differences determine severity of iron accumulation in hfe knockout model of hereditary hemochromatosis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>2707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2711</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11226304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Ludwiczek1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ludwiczek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theurl</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bahram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;mann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Regulatory networks for the control of body iron homeostasis and their dysregulation in HFE mediated hemochromatosis</article-title>. <source>J Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>204</volume>: <fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>499</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15744772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Piperno1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Piperno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trombini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bozzini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Blunted hepcidin response to oral iron challenge in HFE-related hemochromatosis</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>4096</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17724144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Robb1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Robb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wessling-Resnick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regulation of transferrin receptor 2 protein levels by transferrin</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>4294</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Kacser1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kacser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>The control of flux</article-title>. <source>Symposia of the Society for Experimental Biology</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4148886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Heinrich1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>A linear steady-state treatment of enzymatic chains</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4830198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Sahle1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sahle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoops</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kummer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A new strategy for assessing sensitivities in biochemical models</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc A</source>
<volume>366</volume>: <fpage>3619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3631</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18632455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Lin1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valore</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodnough</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabayan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Iron transferrin regulates hepcidin synthesis in primary hepatocyte culture through hemojuvelin and BMP2/4</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>2182</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2189</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17540841</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Becker1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raue</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Covering a broad dynamic range: Information processing at the erythropoietin receptor</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>328</volume>: <fpage>1404</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20488988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Chloupkov1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chloupkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Enns</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Stoichiometries of transferrin receptors 1 and 2 in human liver</article-title>. <source>Blood Cells, Molecules, &#x00026; Diseases</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Gao1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ASS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Interaction of the hereditary hemochromatosis protein hfe with transferrin receptor 2 is required for transferrin-induced hepcidin expression</article-title>. <source>Cell Metabolism</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19254567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Hoops1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hoops</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sahle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gauges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pahle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>COPASI &#x02014; a COmplex Pathway SImulator</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>3067</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3074</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Funahashi1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Funahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morohashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanimura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>CellDesigner: a process diagram editor for gene-regulatory and biochemical networks</article-title>. <source>BIOSILICO</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Ajioka1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ajioka</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Biosynthesis of heme in mammals</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1763</volume>: <fpage>723</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>736</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16839620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Wallace1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Summerville</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crampton</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Combined deletion of HFE and transferrin receptor 2 in mice leads to marked dysregulation of hepcidin and iron overload</article-title>. <source>Hepatol</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1992</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2000</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Huang1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferrell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Ultrasensitivity in the mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>10078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10083</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8816754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Sarkar1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tripoulas</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ketterer</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Role of ceruloplasmin in macrophage iron efflux during hypoxia</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>278</volume>: <fpage>44018</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44024</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Wang1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simonovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haertinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schrimpf</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>PaxDb, a database of protein abundance averages across all three domains of life</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Proteom</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>500</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Zaritsky1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zaritsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gales</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Reduction of serum hepcidin by hemodialysis in pediatric and adult patients</article-title>. <source>Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1010</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1014</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20299375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Wang2"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CYY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Hepatocyte divalent metal-ion transporter-1 is dispensable for hepatic iron accumulation and non-transferrin-bound iron uptake in mice</article-title>. <source>Hepatol</source>
<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>788</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>798</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Kim1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klausner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rouault</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Translational repressor activity is equivalent and is quantitatively predicted by in vitro RNA binding for two iron-responsive element-binding proteins, IRP1 and IRP2</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>270</volume>: <fpage>4983</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4986</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7890603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Ke1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leibold</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walden</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Loops and bulge/loops in iron-responsive element isoforms influence iron regulatory protein binding. Fine-tuning of mRNA regulation</article-title>? <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>273</volume>: <fpage>23637</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23640</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9726965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Erlitzki1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Erlitzki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Multiple, conserved iron-responsive elements in the 3&#x02032;- untranslated region of transferrin receptor mRNA enhance binding of iron regulatory protein 2</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>277</volume>: <fpage>42579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42587</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12200453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Kennedy1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kennedy J, Eberhart R (1995) Particle swarm optimization. In: Proceedings of the Fourth IEEE International Conference on Neural Networks, Perth, Australia. pp. 1942&#x02013;1948.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Litzkow1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Litzkow MJ, Livny M, Mutka MW (1988) Condor&#x02014;a hunter of idle workstations. In: 8th International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems. pp. 104&#x02013;111.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Kent1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoops</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Condor-COPASI: high-throughput computing for biochemical networks</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22834945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Johnson1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Enns</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Diferric transferrin regulates transferrin receptor 2 protein stability</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>4287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Pantopoulos1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pantopoulos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hentze</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Differential regulation of two related RNA-binding proteins, iron regulatory protein (IRP) and IRPB</article-title>. <source>RNA</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7585245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Wang3"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pantopoulos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The haemochromatosis protein HFE induces an apparent iron-deficient phenotype in H1299 cells that is not corrected by co-expression of beta 2- microglobulin</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<volume>370</volume>: <fpage>891</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>899</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12464008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Rivera1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabayan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farshidi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Synthetic hepcidin causes rapid dose-dependent hypoferremia and is concentrated in ferroportin-containing organs</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>2196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2199</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15933050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Kinobe1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kinobe</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dercho</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vlahakis</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brien</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szarek</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of the enzymatic activity of heme oxygenases by azole-based antifungal drugs</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Therap</source>
<volume>319</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>284</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16807364</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-West2"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Enns</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Comparison of the interactions of transferrin receptor and transferrin receptor 2 with transferrin and the hereditary hemochromatosis protein HFE</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>275</volume>: <fpage>38135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Byrne1"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chasteen</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steere</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The unique kinetics of iron release from transferrin: the role of receptor, lobe-lobe interactions, and salt at endosomal pH</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>396</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19917294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Cozzi1"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cozzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Role of iron and ferritin in TNFa-induced apoptosis in HeLa cells</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>537</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12606055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Pimstone1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pimstone</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tenhunen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marver</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Inducible heme oxygenase in the kidney: a model for the homeostatic control of hemoglobin catabolism</article-title>. <source>J Clin Investigation</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>2042</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2050</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Bao1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Plasma heme oxygenase-1 concentration is elevated in individuals with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e12371</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20811623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Shayeghi1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shayeghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Latunde-Dada</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oakhill</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laftah</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Identification of an intestinal heme transporter</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>801</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16143108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Tamura1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kamachi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Functional validation of the genetic polymorphisms of human ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter ABCG2: identification of alleles that are defective in porphyrin transport</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharmacol</source>
<volume>70</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16608919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Epsztejn1"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Epsztejn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kakhlon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glickstein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cabantchik</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Fluorescence analysis of the labile iron pool of mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>
<volume>248</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9177722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Haile1"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hentze</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rouault</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harford</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klausner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Regulation of interaction of the iron-responsive element binding protein with iron-responsive RNA elements</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>5055</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5061</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2601708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Mateo1"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mateo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Infante</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Juan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Gorostiaga</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Serum heme oxygenase-1 levels are increased in Parkinson's disease but not in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scandinavica</source>
<volume>121</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Sassa1"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sassa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Why heme needs to be degraded to iron, biliverdin ixalpha, and carbon monoxide</article-title>? <source>Antioxidants &#x00026; Redox Signaling</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>824</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15345141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Cairo1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cairo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tacchini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pietrangelo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Lack of coordinate control of ferritin and transferrin receptor expression during rat liver regeneration</article-title>. <source>Hepatol</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>178</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Summers1"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Worwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Ferritin in normal erythrocytes, lymphocytes, polymorphs, and monocytes</article-title>. <source>British J Haematol</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-SalterCid1"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Salter-Cid</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunmark</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leturcq</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Transferrin receptor is negatively modulated by the hemochromatosis protein hfe: implications for cellular iron homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>5434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5439</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10318901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Sibille1"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sibille</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aisen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Interactions between isolated hepatocytes and Kupffer cells in iron metabolism: a possible role for ferritin as an iron carrier protein</article-title>. <source>Hepatol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Swinkels1"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Swinkels</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laarakkers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kroot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campostrini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Advances in quantitative hepcidin measurements by time-of-flight mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-Riedel1"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Riedel</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muckenthaler</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gehrke</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>HFE downregulates iron uptake from transferrin and induces iron-regulatory protein activity in stably transfected cells</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>94</volume>: <fpage>3915</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3921</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10572108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1003299-vanDijk1"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laarakkers</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klaver</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Tits</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Serum hepcidin levels are innately low in HFE-related haemochromatosis but differ between C282Y-homozygotes with elevated and normal ferritin levels</article-title>. <source>British J Haematol</source>
<volume>142</volume>: <fpage>979</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>985</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>