<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gen Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Gen. Physiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of General Physiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1295</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-7748</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10352035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2225599</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Agonist-dependent Phosphorylation of the Inositol 1,4,5-Trisphosphate Receptor </article-title><subtitle>A Possible Mechanism for Agonist-specific Calcium Oscillations in Pancreatic Acinar Cells</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>LeBeau</surname><given-names>Andrew P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yule</surname><given-names>David I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c9a340N0x1d38fe8">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Groblewski</surname><given-names>Guy E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c9a340N0x1d38fe8">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sneyd</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c9a340N0x1d38fe8">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1c9a340N0x1d38fe8">From the Mathematical Research Branch, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland; <label>&#x02021;</label>Department of Physiology and <label>&#x000a7;</label>Department of Mathematics, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109-1109</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Dr. James Sneyd, Department of Mathematics, University of Michigan, 525 E. University Ave., East Hall, Ann Arbor, MI 48109-1109. Fax: 734-763-0937; E-mail: <email>jsneyd@math.lsa.umich.edu</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>1998</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>1999</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>1999</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The properties of inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (IP<sub>3</sub>)-dependent intracellular calcium oscillations in pancreatic acinar cells depend crucially on the agonist used to stimulate them. Acetylcholine or carbachol (CCh) cause high-frequency (10&#x02013;12-s period) calcium oscillations that are superimposed on a raised baseline, while cholecystokinin (CCK) causes long-period (&#x0003e;100-s period) baseline spiking. We show that physiological concentrations of CCK induce rapid phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor, which is not true of physiological concentrations of CCh. Based on this and other experimental data, we construct a mathematical model of agonist-specific intracellular calcium oscillations in pancreatic acinar cells. Model simulations agree with previous experimental work on the rates of activation and inactivation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor by calcium (DuFour, J.-F., I.M. Arias, and T.J. Turner. 1997. <italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic> 272:2675&#x02013;2681), and reproduce both short-period, raised baseline oscillations, and long-period baseline spiking. The steady state open probability curve of the model IP<sub>3</sub> receptor is an increasing function of calcium concentration, as found for type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptors by Hagar et al. (Hagar, R.E., A.D. Burgstahler, M.H. Nathanson, and B.E. Ehrlich. 1998. <italic>Nature</italic>. 396:81&#x02013;84). We use the model to predict the effect of the removal of external calcium, and this prediction is confirmed experimentally. We also predict that, for type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptors, the steady state open probability curve will shift to lower calcium concentrations as the background IP<sub>3</sub> concentration increases. We conclude that the differences between CCh- and CCK-induced calcium oscillations in pancreatic acinar cells can be explained by two principal mechanisms: (a) CCK causes more phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor than does CCh, and the phosphorylated receptor cannot pass calcium current; and (b) the rate of calcium ATPase pumping and the rate of calcium influx from the outside the cell are greater in the presence of CCh than in the presence of CCK.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor</kwd><kwd>phosphorylation</kwd><kwd>protein kinase A</kwd><kwd>mathematical model</kwd><kwd>calcium oscillations</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Introduction"><title>introduction</title><p>The production of the intracellular signaling factor inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (IP<sub>3</sub>)<sup>1</sup> and the subsequent release of Ca<sup>2+</sup> stored in intracellular organelles is a fundamental cellular signaling function (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Berridge, 1997</xref>). The form of the resultant change in the intracellular free Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>) is highly variable. Specific, well-characterized response types include a single, large increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, which may virtually deplete the stores, and smaller, maintained oscillations of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Berridge, 1990</xref>). Often both patterns may be observed in a single cell type, depending on the agonist concentration.</p><p>The release of Ca<sup>2+</sup> by IP<sub>3</sub> occurs through the activation of a specific receptor for IP<sub>3</sub>, which is located on the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) surface, and which is also a functional calcium channel (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bezprozvanny and Ehrlich, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Traynor, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Joseph, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Yoshida and Imai, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Taylor, 1998</xref>). In addition to its IP<sub>3</sub> binding site (at the NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal end) and its pore-forming region (the COOH-terminal end, containing six membrane-spanning regions), the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor (IP<sub>3</sub>R) also contains a large regulatory domain between the NH<sub>2</sub>- and COOH-terminal regions. A number of cytosolic factors have been suggested to modulate IP<sub>3</sub>R activity, including, but not restricted to, PKA, PKC, Ca<sup>2+</sup>-calmodulin kinase II (CaMK-II), adenine, and possibly guanine nucleotides. These additional factors may permit the wide range of response types that are seen for IP<sub>3</sub>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release.</p><p>In addition to factors such as kinases modulating IP<sub>3</sub>R activity, Ca<sup>2+</sup> itself plays a fundamental role. A number of studies have shown that the steady state open probability of the type-I IP<sub>3</sub>R displays a bell-shaped dependence on [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, with a peak at approximately [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> = 300 nM (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bezprozvanny and Ehrlich, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Traynor, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Joseph, 1996</xref>), while for type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptors the open probability curve is a monotonically increasing function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Hagar et al., 1998</xref>). However, the steady state behavior of the receptor is much less important than the dynamic response of the receptor to a sudden increase of either [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> or [IP<sub>3</sub>]. When exposed to a sudden change in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> or [IP<sub>3</sub>], the receptor responds by a transient increase in open probability, followed by adaptation or recovery, to a lower level (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Finch et al., 1991</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Marchant and Taylor, 1998</xref>). Direct injection of IP<sub>3</sub>, or the use of nonhydrolyzable IP<sub>3</sub> analogues, has shown that in mouse pancreatic acinar cells oscillations of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> can occur when the IP<sub>3</sub> concentration is constant (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Wakui et al., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Berridge and Potter, 1990</xref>). Thus, dynamic regulation of the receptor by Ca<sup>2+</sup> may represent the mechanism by which oscillations of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> arise, with Ca<sup>2+</sup> initially promoting its own release, and then secondarily inhibiting further release. In the <sc>discussion</sc>, we discuss the possible effects on the model of changing IP<sub>3</sub> concentrations.</p><p>A number of mathematical models have been developed to simulate IP<sub>3</sub>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">De Young and Keizer, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Atri et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Sneyd et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al. 1996</xref>), although, to date, all models have been based on the properties of the type-I receptor. In the model of <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">De Young and Keizer (1992)</xref>, each subunit of the tetrameric IP<sub>3</sub>R contains one binding site for IP<sub>3</sub> and two binding sites for Ca<sup>2+</sup>, an activating site and an inactivating state. It was assumed that Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux occurred only when the IP<sub>3</sub> binding site and the activating Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding site were occupied, and the Ca<sup>2+</sup> inactivating site was unoccupied. This formulation resulted in an eight-state model, only one of which was a conducting state. With rate constants for interconversion between the eight states chosen, where possible, to correspond to experimental values, this model displayed oscillatory behavior over a range of [IP<sub>3</sub>] (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">De Young and Keizer, 1992</xref>). A fundamental feature of this model, necessary to allow oscillations to occur, is that IP<sub>3</sub> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to the activation site are fast processes, whereas Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to the inhibitory site is a slow process. Other models of IP<sub>3</sub>R kinetics (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Atri et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Sneyd et al., 1995</xref>) are based on the same premise of fast activation and slow inhibition by Ca<sup>2+</sup>, and <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al. (1996)</xref> showed that these are essentially equivalent formulations. A model of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> dynamics in pituitary gonadotroph cells (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 1994</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>) is perhaps the most highly developed of these in terms of the specific cellular mechanisms controlling [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and equivalence of the model behavior to experimental single cell data.</p><p>Experimental data on the relative rates of activation and inactivation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R by Ca<sup>2+</sup> is consistent with inactivation being a slower process (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Parker and Ivorra, 1990</xref>). However, careful analysis of data with higher kinetic resolution (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Finch et al., 1991</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Marchant et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Marchant and Taylor, 1998</xref>) suggests that the difference between the rates of activation and inactivation is not as great as is typically used in mathematical models. Furthermore, despite the fact that inactivation is apparently too slow in the models, the models are unable to reproduce long-period, baseline oscillations (up to 2 min or longer in period) observed in cells such as hepatocytes (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Kawanishi et al., 1989</xref>) and pancreatic acinar cells (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1991</xref>). Recent models have addressed the issue of long-period oscillations (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Dupont and Swillens, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Laurent and Claret, 1997</xref>), but their relevance to any particular cell type is, as yet, unclear.</p><p>From the point of view of modeling Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations and waves, pancreatic acinar cells present particular difficulties. Firstly, in response to different agonists, pancreatic cells exhibit markedly different Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses (Petersen et al., 1991b; <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1991</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Lawrie et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Thorn et al., 1993b</xref>). Application of acetylcholine (ACh) to pancreatic acinar cells results in the generation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations that are roughly sinusoidal with a frequency of &#x0223c;4&#x02013;6/min. The [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations are superimposed on a raised baseline such that [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> does not fall to basal levels before the generation of the next peak (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1991</xref>). In contrast, the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response to cholecystokinin (CCK) is very different, consisting of baseline spikes of much longer period.</p><p>Despite these differences, there is much evidence that both types of oscillations result from agonist- dependent activation of phospholipase C, and the resulting increase in intracellular [IP<sub>3</sub>] (see <sc>discussion</sc>). How might these two very different patterns of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release occur, with apparently the same basic intracellular processes? In particular, how do the long baseline spikes observed with CCK occur, given that [IP<sub>3</sub>] is thought to be maintained above basal levels throughout the period of stimulation, whereas [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, which initially provides the negative feedback signal to end Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux from the stores, has returned to its basal values long before the next spike occurs? In studying these questions, it is important to keep in mind that pancreatic acinar cells contain a preponderance of type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptors (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Wojcikiewicz, 1995</xref>), and thus any model to explain the observed oscillations should be based on data from the correct receptor subtype wherever possible. Fortunately, data on the steady state properties of type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptors have recently become available, although their adaptational and time-dependent properties are still unknown in detail.</p><p>Our goal is to understand the mechanisms underlying these different oscillatory patterns and provide a single explanation for these seemingly diverse phenomena. Of course, such an explanation can be simplistic at best and cannot take into account all the complexities of the real cell. Nevertheless, it will provide a framework to help us understand how a set of relatively simple cellular interactions can result in diverse and complex behavior. We begin by showing (experimentally) that in mouse and rat pancreatic acinar cells physiological concentrations of CCK cause rapid phosphorylation of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R, but physiological concentrations of ACh do not. Assuming that the phosphorylated receptor does not pass Ca<sup>2+</sup> current (see <sc>discussion</sc>), it follows that the rate at which the IP<sub>3</sub>R recovers from inactivation depends crucially on the agonist. Secondly, we show that the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> removal from the cytoplasm is an order to magnitude slower after application of CCK than after application of ACh. These data are then incorporated into a model of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R, and thus into a whole-cell model of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> response. The model provides a unified explanation of seemingly disparate results; it agrees with the rates of activation and inactivation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R by Ca<sup>2+</sup>, as measured by <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Finch et al. (1991)</xref> and <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al. (1997)</xref>, but can nevertheless produce oscillations of very long period and generate oscillations of the two observed types. Furthermore, the steady state open probability of the model type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptor is an increasing function of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, as found experimentally by <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Hagar et al. (1998)</xref>, thus showing that such monotonic steady state curves are consistent with oscillatory behavior, a fact that is not always appreciated. Predictions of the model are then tested, and confirmed, experimentally.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="Methods"><title>methods</title><sec><title>Materials</title><p>Fura-2/AM was purchased from Molecular Probes, Inc., collagenase (CLSPA grade) from Worthington Biochemicals, bovine serum albumin (fraction V) from ICN Immunobiologicals, and minimal essential amino acid supplement from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="gibco">GIBCO BRL</named-content>. [<sup>32</sup>P]orthophosphate (9,000 Ci/mmol) was obtained from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="dupont">Dupont NEN</named-content>. Monoclonal antisera directed against the type-III inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor was obtained from Transduction Laboratories. All other materials were obtained from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content>
</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of Pancreatic Acini</title><p>Acini were prepared by methods previously described (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 1978</xref>; <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1996</xref>). In brief, pancreata were excised from freely fed adult male Sprague-Dawley rats (200&#x02013;250 g) or mice. Acini were prepared by enzymatic digestion with purified collagenase, followed by mechanical shearing. Acini were then filtered through 150 &#x003bc;m Nitex mesh, purified by sedimentation through 4% BSA in HEPES ringer, and then suspended in a physiological salt solution containing 10 mg/ml bovine serum albumin, 0.1 mg/ml soybean trypsin inhibitor, and (mM): 137 NaCl, 4.7 KCl, 0.56 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.28 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.0 Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 10 HEPES, 2 <sc>l</sc>-glutamine, 5.5 <sc>d</sc>-glucose, essential amino acids. The pH was adjusted to 7.4 and equilibrated with 100% O<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurement of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>
</title><p>Isolated acini were incubated with 2.5 &#x003bc;M fura-2/AM at ambient temperature for 30 min, and then washed and resuspended in fresh physiological salt solution without BSA. For measurement of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, fura-2&#x02013;loaded acini were transferred to a chamber, mounted on the stage of an Axiovert 35 microscope (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="zeiss">Carl Zeiss, Inc.</named-content>), and continuously superfused at 1 ml/min with PSS without BSA. Solution changes were rapidly accomplished by means of a valve attached to an eight-chambered superfusion reservoir, which was maintained at 37&#x000b0;C. Determination of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> was performed using digital imaging microscopy with an ATTOFLUOR ratiovision system (ATTO Inc.) as previously described (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1996</xref>). Briefly, excitation at 340/380 nm was alternately achieved by a computer controlled filter and shutter system and the resultant emission at 505 nm was recorded at the rates indicated in the figures by an intensified CCD camera, and subsequently digitized. Mean gray values obtained by excitation at 340 and 380 nm, in user-defined areas of interest, were used to compute 340/380 ratios. Calibration of fluorescent ratio signals was accomplished as previously described according to the equation of <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Grynkiewicz et al. (1985)</xref> by comparing the fluorescence of known standard Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffers containing fura-2.</p></sec><sec><title>Assessement of Phosphorylation of the Type-III IP<sub>3</sub> Receptor</title><p>Acini were labeled with 0.3 mCi/ml <sup>32</sup>PO<sub>4</sub> for 2 h in HEPES ringer devoid of added phosphate. Aliquots of labeled acinar cells were then treated as indicated. At the end of the incubations, the acini were rapidly centrifuged in a microcentrifuge and the pellets were resuspended in ice-cold lysis buffer containing 100 mM NaF, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM EDTA, 1 mM benzamidine, 1% Triton X-100, 10 &#x003bc;g/ml leupeptin, and 10 &#x003bc;g/ml pepstatin, at pH 7.4). The homogenates were then sonicated. After 30 min on ice, the samples were precleared by addition of 100 &#x003bc;l of protein A-agarose beads and rotation for 2 h at 4&#x000b0;C. The protein A beads were removed by centrifugation and the protein content of the samples was assayed. Type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R was immunoprecipitated from the samples of equal protein by incubation with 1 &#x003bc;g antibody/mg of protein (Transduction Laboratories) for 3 h. After incubation, the beads were washed five times with the lysis buffer by centrifugation and resuspension. After the final wash, the beads were boiled in Laemmli buffer and immunoprecipitated proteins separated by electrophoresis on 5% SDS-PAGE gels. The gel was dried and exposed to a Phosphoimager intensifing screen (Bio-Rad Laboratories) for visualization and analyzed by molecular analyst software for quantification (Bio-Rad Laboratories).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Results"><title>results</title><sec disp-level="4"><title>Secretagogue phosphorylation of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptor.</title><p> Aliquots of acini (in duplicate), metabolically labeled with <sup>32</sup>P, were stimulated with secretagogues for 2 min and the extent of phosphorylation of the receptor was assessed by immunoprecipitating the receptor, separation on SDS-PAGE, and then autoradiography. Acini were initially treated with varying concentrations of CCK. In unstimulated acini, phosphorylation of one major band of &#x0223c;300 kD, corresponding to the type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R, could be detected. An increase in the degree of phosphorylation could be demonstrated at 10 pM CCK (170 &#x000b1; 15% above basal) and reached a maximum at 100 nM CCK (252 &#x000b1; 23% of control). Phosphorylation of the receptor was not significantly greater at 1 or 10 nM CCK (<italic>n</italic> = 4 rat and 2 mouse preparations gave qualitatively similar results). It should be noted that the onset and maximum phosphorylation of the receptor achieved coincides with concentrations of CCK that can be demonstrated to induce calcium oscillations (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1991</xref>, <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>). Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows a typical experiment. The extent of receptor phosphorylation was also investigated upon stimulation by the muscarinic agonist, carbachol. In this series of experiments, an increased phosphorylation of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R was also consistently observed 2 min after stimulation with agonist. Phosphorylation could be detected at 1 &#x003bc;M CCh (160 &#x000b1; 22%) and reached a peak at 10 &#x003bc;M (203 &#x000b1; 28% of control). In contrast to stimulation by CCK, no significant phosphorylation of the receptor was observed at concentrations of CCh below 1 &#x003bc;M, concentrations that can be demonstrated to induce an oscillatory calcium signal (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1991</xref>; <italic>n</italic> = 3 rat and 2 mouse preparations gave quantitatively similar results). A typical experiment is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. </p><p>It is known that, in pancreatic acinar cells, CCK activates both the adenylate cyclase pathway as well as the phospholipase C pathway, while ACh activates only the latter pathway (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Schulz, 1989</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Petersen and Wakui, 1990</xref>). Thus, a plausible working hypothesis is that the CCK-induced receptor phosphorylation is caused by the activation of PKA, a pathway that is not stimulated by ACh, or at least not to the same extent.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Phosphorylation of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptor by second messengers.</title><p>To investigate the mediator generated upon agonist stimulation that results in phosphorylation of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R, duplicate aliquots of acini were incubated for 5 min with agents known to activate or be a mediator in discrete second-messenger pathways: acini were incubated in either cyclopiazonic acid (CPA), which leads to an elevation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> by inhibition of the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase present on intracellular calcium stores, TPA, an activator of protein kinase C, or CPT-cAMP, a cell-permeable cAMP analog. In three experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 2 rat and 1 mouse preparation) no enhanced phosphorylation of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R was ever observed from acini incubated with either TPA or CPA, indicating that a calcium-dependent kinase or protein kinase C is apparently not responsible for phosphorylation of the receptor. A marked increase in phosphorylation was, however, always observed when the acini were incubated with CPT-cAMP. The extent of phosphorylation, &#x0003e;427 &#x000b1; 52% above basal, was greater than observed with phospholipase C&#x02013;coupled agonists. These data indicate that a cAMP-dependent pathway is capable of phosphorylating the receptor. A typical experiment is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>. </p></sec><sec><title>Model Construction</title><p>Previous mathematical models of the IP<sub>3</sub>R have tended to treat IP<sub>3</sub> as a permissive factor; its binding is regarded as obligatory for channel activation, but beyond that it has a passive role, with [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> providing the dynamics underlying oscillations. However, two lines of experimental evidence suggest that IP<sub>3</sub> binding may play a more important, dynamic role. Firstly, binding studies have shown the affinity of IP<sub>3</sub> for its receptor is dependent on the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. For type-I receptors, increasing [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> causes either a decrease in IP<sub>3</sub>-binding affinity (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yoneshima et al., 1997</xref>) or a biphasic effect (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Sienaert et al., 1997</xref>), whereas, for the type-III receptor, increasing [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> enhances IP<sub>3</sub> binding (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yoneshima et al., 1997</xref>). Secondly, there is evidence that IP<sub>3</sub> itself may inactivate the IP<sub>3</sub>R. For example, experiments with high kinetic resolution performed under Ca<sup>2+</sup>-clamp conditions have shown that during continuous perfusion with a particular medium-Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration, the introduction of IP<sub>3</sub> causes a transient release of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> from microsomes derived from rat brain synaptosomes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Finch et al., 1991</xref>) or rat hepatocytes (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Marchant and Taylor, 1998</xref>). This suggests either that IP<sub>3</sub> can inactivate the receptor or that at least some of the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-induced inactivation occurs only during permeation of the channel. The Mn<sup>2+</sup> quench experiments of <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Hajn&#x000f3;czky et al. (1993)</xref> demonstrate that IP<sub>3</sub> can inactivate the receptors without permeation of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Furthermore, they found that Ca<sup>2+</sup> enhanced IP<sub>3</sub>-induced channel inactivation.</p><sec disp-level="4"><title>Reaction scheme.</title><p>We assume that the complete IP<sub>3</sub>R is composed of four, functionally identical, independent subunits. The reaction scheme governing transitions of each subunit is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>. S denotes the fraction of subunits in the shut state (S), in which the receptor channel is closed and IP<sub>3</sub> is not bound. Binding of IP<sub>3</sub> causes the receptor to be converted to the open state, O, and we let <italic>O</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) denote the fraction of receptors in state O. Although several subconductance states of IP<sub>3</sub>R have been observed, the channels most often open to just one of these (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Watras et al., 1991</xref>). We therefore assume that IP<sub>3</sub> must be bound to all four subunits for the receptor to be in the conducting state. Thus, the fraction of conducting receptors is <italic>O</italic>
<sup>4</sup>. </p><p>To explain the apparent IP<sub>3</sub>-induced inactivation (described above), we propose that the O state is relatively unstable, and the subunits will progress through to the more stable I<sub>1</sub> (inactivated) state, in which IP<sub>3</sub> is still bound but the channels do not conduct. Thus, binding of IP<sub>3</sub> to a single binding site accounts for both channel activation and at least one aspect of inactivation. We assume that the reverse transition (I<sub>1</sub> &#x02192; O) has a very slow rate, and so exclude it from our reaction scheme. It is reasonable to consider that a direct transition from S to I<sub>1</sub> could occur. However, we suggest that the S &#x02192; O transition is greatly favored, and will therefore strongly dominate the S &#x02192; I<sub>1</sub> transition, and so we make the simplifying assumption of setting the rate of the latter transition to zero.</p><p>In our model, we do not specifically include any binding sites for Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Although it appears there may be several of these on the IP<sub>3</sub>R (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Sienaert et al., 1997</xref>), these have not been well characterized. Because of this, we instead incorporate the effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> by making the rate of the S to O transition a function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. By doing this, we are able to correlate model behavior with experimentally observed effects of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, without having to speculate on the number or nature of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites on the receptors. This approach has the added advantage that the reaction scheme is kept simpler. However, a more complex model that assumes that Ca<sup>2+</sup> governs the interconversion of the receptor between two different states, one with a high IP<sub>3</sub> affinity, the other with a low IP<sub>3</sub> affinity (Cardy et al.; 1997; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Hajn&#x000f3;czky and Thomas, 1997</xref>), behaves in exactly the same manner (Sneyd, LeBeau, and Yule, manuscript submitted for publication). In fact, it can be shown that, if it is assumed that Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding is fast, the model presented here can be derived from this more complex model.</p><p>We set the transition S &#x02192; O to be an increasing function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. This is based on two separate experimental observations. First, raising [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] increased the rate of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux in superfusion experiments (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 1997</xref>, data reproduced here in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Second, in permeabilized hepatocytes, raising the medium [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] reduced the EC<sub>50</sub> for IP<sub>3</sub>-induced <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from internal stores (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Marshall and Taylor, 1993</xref>). Both of these experimental observations are consistent with Ca<sup>2+</sup> enhancing the affinity of IP<sub>3</sub> for the receptors. More than 80% of hepatocyte IP<sub>3</sub>R are type II, with the remainder being type I (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Wojcikiewicz, 1995</xref>), suggesting that IP<sub>3</sub> binding to type-II receptors is enhanced by increasing [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], similar to type-III receptors (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yoneshima et al., 1997</xref>). The pancreas (most of which is exocrine acinar cells) contains mostly type-III receptors, with a significant number of type-II receptors, but few type-I receptors (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Wojcikiewicz, 1995</xref>). Thus, we have assumed that Ca<sup>2+</sup> enhances IP<sub>3</sub> binding to the receptors in the model.</p><p>The transition I<sub>1</sub> &#x02192; S represents the normal pathway by which the IP<sub>3</sub>R recovers from inactivation, with IP<sub>3</sub> dissociating from its binding site. The receptor can then rebind IP<sub>3</sub> and repeat the cycle. We refer to this pathway (involving S, O, and I<sub>1</sub> only) as the &#x0201c;intrinsic&#x0201d; receptor pathway, on the basis that this reflects the direct effects of IP<sub>3</sub> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> on receptor activity. However, we also include a transition from I<sub>1</sub> to I<sub>2</sub>, where I<sub>2</sub> represents a second inactivated state of the receptor in which IP<sub>3</sub> is no longer bound (i.e., IP<sub>3</sub> dissociates during this transition). This pathway is agonist specific and involves phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R. As shown above, physiological concentrations of CCK cause rapid phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R, (possibly via the activation of PKA), while physiological concentrations of ACh do not. Hence, to model the application of CCK, <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> is set to be nonzero, while the application of ACh is modeled by setting <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> = 0. Phosphatase actions eventually dephosphorylate the receptor, converting it to the S state, whereupon it may rebind IP<sub>3</sub>. A crucial element of this scheme is that while in the I<sub>2</sub> state the receptor is unaffected by either the IP<sub>3</sub> or Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations. We refer to the pathway involving all four states of the channel as the &#x0201c;full&#x0201d; pathway, with the inclusion of the generation of I<sub>2</sub> representing a &#x0201c;mediated&#x0201d; effect, as distinct from the intrinsic effects described above. The distinction between intrinsic and mediated effects is largely for descriptive convenience.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Receptor kinetics.</title><p>By the law of mass action differential, equations for the various receptor states can be determined. The equation for the fraction of receptor subunits in the open state (<italic>O</italic>) is <disp-formula id="E1"><label>1</label><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{d{\mathit{O}}}{dt}=k_{1}p{\mathit{S}}-k_{-1}{\mathit{O}}-k_{2}{\mathit{O}},\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>where <italic>p</italic> is [IP<sub>3</sub>]. The variable S can be eliminated using the conservation law <italic>S</italic> = 1 &#x02212; (<italic>O</italic> + <italic>I</italic>
<sub>1</sub> + <italic>I</italic>
<sub>2</sub>). Here, <italic>I</italic>
<sub>1</sub> and <italic>I</italic>
<sub>2</sub> are the fraction of receptors in states I<sub>1</sub> and I<sub>2</sub>, respectively. As previously stated, we assume that all four of the subunits must be in this state before the receptor will pass any Ca<sup>2+</sup> current. Thus the conducting state is <italic>O</italic>
<sup>4</sup>.</p><p>The equation for <italic>I</italic>
<sub>1</sub> is given by <disp-formula id="E2"><label>2</label><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{dI_{1}}{dt}=k_{2}{\mathit{O}}-(k_{3}+k_{4})I_{1},\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>and for <italic>I</italic>
<sub>2</sub> by <disp-formula id="E3"><label>3</label><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{dI_{2}}{dt}=k_{4}I_{1}-k_{5}I_{2}.\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>As described above, the rate <italic>k</italic>
<sub>1</sub> is a function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, which is denoted by <italic>c</italic>: <disp-formula id="E4"><label>4</label><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}k_{1}=\frac{{\alpha}_{1}c^{3}}{{\beta}^{3}_{1}+c^{3}},\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>whereas <italic>k</italic>
<sub>&#x02212;1</sub>, <italic>k</italic>
<sub>2</sub>, <italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub>, and <italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub> are constants. The constant &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub> is the maximum rate of the S to O transition, and &#x003b2;<sub>1</sub> is the Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration at which the rate of the S to O transition is half its maximum rate. The function <italic>k</italic>
<sub>1</sub> is an increasing function of <italic>c</italic>, representing our assumption that [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> enhances the affinity of IP<sub>3</sub> binding. Little is known regarding the mechanism(s) by which Ca<sup>2+</sup> exerts its effects on the IP<sub>3</sub>R, and therefore, although Ca<sup>2+</sup> may act by directly binding to the receptor, our reaction scheme does not explicitly indicate such a mechanism. However, as discussed above, the present model can be derived from a more general model in which Ca<sup>2+</sup> regulates the binding affinity of IP<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Hajn&#x000f3;czky and Thomas, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cardy et al., 1997</xref>; Sneyd, LeBeau, and Yule, manuscript submitted for publication).</p><p>Since we have not suggested explicit mechanisms representing the transitions governed by <italic>k</italic>
<sub>1</sub>, <italic>k</italic>
<sub>2</sub>, and <italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub>, we use the simplest possible functions. Thus, we chose <italic>k</italic>
<sub>2</sub> and <italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub> as constants, and let <italic>k</italic>
<sub>1</sub> be a sigmoidal function of <italic>c</italic>, with a Hill coefficient of 3. If <italic>k</italic>
<sub>1</sub> is assumed to have a smaller Hill coefficient, it is more difficult to get oscillations in the model. It thus appears that cooperativity in the action of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on IP<sub>3</sub> binding may be an important physiological mechanism. These choices for the rate constants are easily modified to give bell-shaped steady state open probability curves if one wishes to model other types of IP<sub>3</sub> receptors. For instance, with a bell-shaped open probability curve, oscillations occur in the model even when <italic>k</italic>
<sub>1</sub> has a Hill coefficient of 1 (computations not shown).</p><p>The rate constant <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> is given by <disp-formula id="E5"><label>5</label><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}k_{4}=\frac{{\alpha}_{4}p}{{\beta}_{4}+p},\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>and models the action of a kinase (possibly PKA) on the IP<sub>3</sub>R, and is assumed to be dependent on the type of agonist used to initiate Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations. The constant &#x003b1;<sub>4</sub> denotes the maximum rate of the reaction attained at high <italic>p</italic>, while &#x003b2;<sub>4</sub> denotes the value of <italic>p</italic> at which the rate is half maximal. When activated, <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> shunts the receptors through the I<sub>2</sub> pathway. Since it is reasonable to assume that greater levels of agonist stimulation will result in greater kinase activity, we assume that <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> is a saturating function of the IP<sub>3</sub> concentration. As can be seen from Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>, &#x003b2;<sub>4</sub> is chosen to be relatively small, so that the rate of phosphorylation saturates quickly, and, in most physiological regimes, is approximately constant. </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Simulation of IP<sub>3</sub>- and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-clamp experiments.</title><p>To determine reasonable values for the transition rates, we simulated experiments in which a superfusion system was used to determine the rapid kinetics of IP<sub>3</sub>R activation and inactivation. This technique has the feature that extravesicular [IP<sub>3</sub>] and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] can be rapidly changed under otherwise clamped conditions (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Finch et al., 1991</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Marchant and Taylor, 1998</xref>). Unfortunately, such data are not available from type-III receptors, and so it is unknown whether their time- dependent behavior is similar to that of type-I or -II receptors. In the absence of evidence to the contrary, we shall assume it is, although the model does point out some likely important differences, as we shall see.</p><p>The experimental observations we are attempting to reproduce are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, A and B. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> A depicts <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> efflux for various extravesicular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], with a constant [IP<sub>3</sub>] of 10 &#x003bc;M. Initially, increasing the bathing [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] increased both the initial rate and peak response of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> efflux, but these factors decreased at high [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. The cumulative release was also found to increase initially, but then decrease at higher [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 1997</xref>, not shown). Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> B shows the results of similar experiments in which extravesicular [IP<sub>3</sub>] was changed, while the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] was fixed at 400 nM. Here, again, increasing [IP<sub>3</sub>] caused an increase in both the initial rate and cumulative <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> release, although in this case neither factor was observed to decline at high [IP<sub>3</sub>] (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>Simulations of these experiments are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>. Since only direct effects of IP<sub>3</sub> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> would be expected to affect IP<sub>3</sub>R activity, only the intrinsic pathway was used for these simulations (i.e., generation of I<sub>2</sub> was excluded by setting <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> = 0). The simulated experiments used the same concentrations of agonists, although the full range was not used. The qualitative behavior of the simulations was in good agreement with the experimental data, with one significant difference. The rate of inactivation of the receptor is an increasing function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> in the data but not in the model. In other words, the data from type-II receptors indicates that <italic>k</italic>
<sub>2</sub> is an increasing function of <italic>c</italic>, but this was not included in the model. The principal reason for this is that we found, in order to obtain a monotonic steady state open probability curve (see below), it was simplest to set <italic>k</italic>
<sub>2</sub> to be a constant, rather than an increasing function of <italic>c</italic>. Although the dynamic properties of type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptors have not yet been measured, our model predicts that a monotonic steady state curve will likely be associated with receptors whose rate of inactivation is independent of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. The simulated dose responses of the model also agree qualitatively with the results of <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Marchant and Taylor (1998)</xref>. </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Monotonic steady state [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] dependence.</title><p>For type-I IP<sub>3</sub> receptors, the steady state open probability has been found to have a bell-shaped dependence on [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bezprozvanny and Ehrlich, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Traynor, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kaftan et al., 1997</xref>), and this can easily be reproduced by our model (computations not shown). However, recent results (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Hagar et al., 1998</xref>) have shown that the type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R has a steady state open probability curve that is a monotonic increasing function of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Since it appears that Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in pancreatic acinar cells are governed by Ca<sup>2+</sup> release through type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R, we chose parameter values so as to obtain a monotonically increasing steady state open probability curve as a function of Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). </p><p>Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> shows that as [IP<sub>3</sub>] is increased, the point of inflexion (i.e., where the slope is greatest) shifts to the left. Since the measurement of the steady state open probability curve has been measured at only a single IP<sub>3</sub> concentration, this is a prediction from our model that has not yet been tested.</p><p>In the <xref ref-type="app" rid="N0x1c9a340N0x347d0e0">Appendix</xref>, we show that, at least in most current models, including those of <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al. (1996)</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">De Young and Keizer (1992)</xref>, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Atri et al. (1993)</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bezprozvanny (1994)</xref>, and <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Li and Rinzel (1994)</xref>, the position of the steady state open probability curve as a function of IP<sub>3</sub> concentration is crucially dependent on the assumed effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on IP<sub>3</sub> binding. When an increased Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration enhances IP<sub>3</sub> binding to the receptor, the models predict that the steady state curve will move to the left as the background [IP<sub>3</sub>] increases. Conversely, when an increased Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration decreases IP<sub>3</sub> binding to the receptor, the steady state curve is predicted to move to the right as [IP<sub>3</sub>] increases.</p><p>The rightward shift of the peak of the bell-shaped steady state curve observed by <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kaftan et al. (1997)</xref> came from studies of the type-I IP<sub>3</sub>R. Binding of IP<sub>3</sub> to the type-I receptor is decreased by raising [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yoneshima et al., 1997</xref>; but see <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Sienaert et al., 1997</xref> for more complex effects), whereas IP<sub>3</sub> binding to type-III receptors was enhanced by raising [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yoneshima et al., 1997</xref>). Thus, from analysis of our model, the rightward shift of the steady state curve observed by <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kaftan et al. (1997)</xref> is the expected effect for type-I receptors, but the opposite should occur in cases where Ca<sup>2+</sup> enhances IP<sub>3</sub> binding, which appears to be the appropriate situation for pancreatic acinar cells.</p><p>We emphasise another crucial point that is often overlooked. The exact nature of the steady state open probability curve has little effect on the dynamic properties of the receptor, and thus has little influence on whether or not the receptor is able to mediate Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations. This is because it is the initial fast activation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R, followed by a slower inactivation, that is the crucial mechanism underlying Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations. As we shall see, a model with a monotonic steady state curve is quite capable of generating oscillations, and in fact these oscillations are almost the same as those of a similar model in which the steady state open probability curve is bell shaped (computations not shown).</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Incorporation into a whole-cell model.</title><p>We now incorporate the receptor model into a description of acinar cell [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses, endeavoring to keep the model as simple as is reasonably possible so as to retain the focus on the kinetics of the IP<sub>3</sub>R. Hence, we do not include any possible effects of ryanodine receptors (see <sc>discussion</sc>).</p><p>The equation for [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<italic>c</italic>) is given by <disp-formula id="E6"><label>6</label><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{dc}{dt}=J_{rel}-\;J_{pump}+\;J_{influx},\;\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>where <italic>J</italic>
<sub>rel</sub> represents the IP<sub>3</sub>-induced release of Ca<sup>2+</sup> from the ER and is given by <disp-formula id="E7"><label>7</label><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}J_{rel}=k_{flux}{\mathit{O}}^{4},\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>in which <italic>k</italic>
<sub>flux</sub> is the maximum rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from the ER.</p><p>
<italic>J</italic>
<sub>pump</sub> represents the combined activity of all Ca<sup>2+</sup> pumps that remove Ca<sup>2+</sup> from the cytosol and is given by <disp-formula id="E8"><label>8</label><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}J_{pump}=\frac{V_{p}c^{2}}{K^{2}_{p}+c^{2}},\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>where <italic>V</italic>
<sub>p</sub> represents the maximum rate of pumping and <italic>K</italic>
<sub>p</sub> is the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> for half-maximal pumping. The Ca<sup>2+</sup> ATPase pump is assumed to operate in a cooperative manner, with a Hill coefficient of 2 (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Lytton et al., 1992</xref>).</p><p>
<italic>J</italic>
<sub>influx</sub> is an adjustable parameter that represents a constant rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx into the cytosol. This term includes both influx from outside the cell and any leak of Ca<sup>2+</sup> from intracellular stores such as the ER and mitochondria.</p><p>The standard parameter values are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>. The values in brackets correspond to those values used to model CCK-induced oscillations, as described in more detail below.</p><p>To keep the model as simple as possible at this stage, we do not consider effects such as spatial variation in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> signals, separation of either Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx versus leak from internal stores, or the various forms of Ca<sup>2+</sup> pumping both into internal stores or out of the cell. We also do not consider the aspect of store filling state and the dependence on this of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> signals, nor do we include capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry. Thus, we are concerned only with the initial phases of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> signals (i.e., the generation of the responses), when the filling state of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores will not yet have been compromised, as opposed to the sustained phases of the responses. We leave such aspects for further investigation.</p><p>In addition to our need to keep the model as simple as possible at this stage, there is another very good reason to omit consideration of spatial effects at this stage. It is well known that, to understand the behavior of a reaction&#x02013;diffusion system (such as this would be in the presence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> diffusion), it is necessary first to understand the behavior of the model in the absence of diffusion; i.e., the reaction kinetics must be understood in detail before it is possible to understand how diffusion will affect the system. Although diffusion and spatial heterogeneities will modulate the amplitude and period of the oscillations, they are unlikely, by themselves, to explain the gross features of the different oscillation types. Only a study of the reaction mechanisms will do that.</p><p>Finally, we assume that Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering is fast and linear, so that all the fluxes in the model are effective fluxes of free Ca<sup>2+</sup>. In the absence of any specific information on the properties of calcium buffers in pancreatic acinar cells, this is the simplest assumption.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Theoretical Results</title><sec disp-level="4"><title>Parameter values.</title><p>The parameter values used in the model simulations are presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>. The values for the rates of activation and inactivation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor by Ca<sup>2+</sup> (&#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>, &#x003b2;<sub>1</sub>, &#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>, &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>, &#x003b3;<sub>2</sub>, &#x003b1;<sub>3</sub>, &#x003b2;<sub>3</sub>, <italic>k</italic>
<sub>&#x02212;1</sub>, and <italic>k</italic>
<sub>2</sub>) were determined by ensuring the model agrees with the results of <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al. (1997)</xref>. This was not done by a detailed fitting procedure, only approximate agreement was required. The parameters governing the rate of phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor by PKA (&#x003b1;<sub>4</sub> and &#x003b2;<sub>4</sub>), and the recovery from the I<sub>2</sub> state (<italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub>), were not determined from experimental data; the values in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref> were chosen so as to give reasonable agreement with the observed CCK-induced oscillations. For ACh-induced oscillations, &#x003b1;<sub>4</sub> was set to zero to mimic the much decreased rate of receptor phosphorylation.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Pumping rates.</title><p>To measure the approximate rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> ATPase activity, exponential functions were fit to the downward slopes of the oscillations induced by either ACh or CCK (data not shown). Although this assumes that the decline in Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration during the decreasing phase of the oscillation is due to Ca<sup>2+</sup> pumping, and although it assumes the pumping has linear kinetics, these assumptions will have little, if any, qualitative effect on the result, and are accurate enough for our purposes; we are not doing a detailed fit of the model to data, merely using the data to determine approximate values for the parameters.</p><p>ACh-induced oscillations have a declining phase that approximates an exponential curve, with a decay rate that varies from &#x0223c;0.2 to &#x0223c;0.4 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. On the other hand, the decay rate for the decreasing phase of CCK- induced oscillations ranges from &#x0223c;0.03 to &#x0223c;0.06 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p><p>Based on these experimentally measured time constants for the removal of Ca<sup>2+</sup> from the cytoplasm, we chose two different values for <italic>V</italic>
<sub>p</sub>, the maximum pumping rate, corresponding to the two different agonists. For ACh, we chose <italic>V</italic>
<sub>p</sub> = 2.6 &#x003bc;M s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, while for CCK we chose <italic>V</italic>
<sub>p</sub> = 0.2 &#x003bc;M s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>). Note that, although <italic>V</italic>
<sub>p</sub> does not correspond directly to the time constants measured by fitting an exponential to the experimental data, these maximum pumping rates will give rates of decline of the correct orders of magnitude for the two different agonists. Based on the data of <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Lytton et al. (1992)</xref>, the pump was assumed to operate in a cooperative fashion, with a half-maximal rate occurring at 0.54 &#x003bc;M. The parameter <italic>k</italic>
<sub>flux</sub> was determined by requiring a physiologically reasonable resting Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Calcium influx.</title><p>There remains only one parameter, the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx, to discuss. We hypothesise that this parameter is agonist dependent. In addition to the very different kinetics of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> transients evoked by the two agonists, the transients also differ greatly in their sensitivity to removal of external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. ACh-induced transients are very sensitive, such that if the medium bathing cells is switched from normal (1.2 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]) to nominally Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free during repetitive [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations, the oscillations are abolished within &#x0223c;30 s (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al. 1991</xref>). This behavior has also been observed by <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Muallem et al. (1990)</xref>, and for bombesin-stimulated oscillations in rat pancreatic acinar cells by <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. (1997)</xref>.</p><p>The same treatment has only a slow effect on CCK- induced oscillations (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al. 1991</xref>; see also <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 1997</xref>). Here, the oscillations may continue for up to 20 min, with the peak of the transients slowly reducing. The slow decay, and eventual loss, of CCK-induced oscillations probably reflects Ca<sup>2+</sup> store depletion, which is normally prevented, when Ca<sup>2+</sup> is present in the medium, by capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 1995</xref>, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>), which is not included in the model at this stage. It seems unlikely that the same explanation can account for the effects of removal of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> on ACh- induced oscillations because of the contrasting rapidity of the loss of oscillations. Instead, the experimental observations suggest that ACh may activate a Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry pathway that is necessary for the generation of oscillations. This is consistent with the raised baseline Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations observed during ACh-induced oscillations. Although it is clear that the mechanisms of Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry are much more complicated than our model assumes (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Loessberg et al., 1991</xref>; <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 1995</xref>, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>), we ignore these complications for now and just treat Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx as a simple leak. It is unclear what qualitative effect this will have on the model conclusions.</p><p>Based on the above argument, we assume that ACh increases the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx from outside the cell, while CCK does so to a much lesser extent, and thus, to simulate the two different types of oscillations, we use the two different values shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>.</p><p>It is important to note that only three parameters are dependent on the agonist. All other parameters are invariant for all the simulations. Thus, we hypothesise that the differences between oscillations induced by ACh, and those induced by CCK, are due to the following two things. (a) CCK activates PKA, and causes greater phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor, thus shunting it through the closed state I<sub>2</sub>. ACh-induced phosphorylation is much less significant, and thus the state I<sub>2</sub> is bypassed. (b) ACh increases the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> turnover much more than CCK does. Thus, the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx from outside the cell, and the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> removal from the cytoplasm, are greater in the presence of ACh than in the presence of CCK.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>ACh-induced oscillations.</title><p>We investigated the effects of increasing [IP<sub>3</sub>] on [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses in the model, with the pathway regulated by <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> switched off. The rates of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx and pumping were set to 0.4 and 2.6 &#x003bc;M s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>). Raising [IP<sub>3</sub>] to 0.66 &#x003bc;M caused the generation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations with a period of &#x0223c;15 s (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). During the oscillatory behavior, the nadir of the oscillations occurred at &#x0223c;300 nM, well above the resting [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. </p><p>For the simulation in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, [IP<sub>3</sub>] was not raised immediately to its final level, but was instead raised gradually, with a time contant of 10 s. Thus, our simulations include the effects of a continually varying IP<sub>3</sub> concentration, as would be expected to occur upon agonist stimulation. Although slow variations in [IP<sub>3</sub>] modulate the exact shape of the oscillations, their overall behavior can still be predicted by considering the behavior in response to a constant [IP<sub>3</sub>]. Similarly, if [IP<sub>3</sub>] is allowed to decrease gradually, the oscillations eventually disappear (computations not shown). The crucial point to notice is that, although [IP<sub>3</sub>] is changing slightly throughout the course of an oscillation (particularly during the first few peaks), such changes are not a crucial part of the oscillatory mechanism. Oscillations can occur in the presence of a fixed [IP<sub>3</sub>] in the oscillatory range.</p><p>The behavior of the system over a full range of [IP<sub>3</sub>] can be seen in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>. In this figure, the effect of increasing [IP<sub>3</sub>] progressively on the behavior of the system is shown. In particular, this analysis examines the effect of [IP<sub>3</sub>] on [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses, showing where they are stable and where they are oscillatory. Starting at low [IP<sub>3</sub>] values, the system is stable, as depicted by the solid line. As [IP<sub>3</sub>] is progressively increased, [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> gradually rises, but it still stable (i.e., it remains at a single value over time). However, at [IP<sub>3</sub>] = 0.62, a critical point is reached where the steady state solution becomes unstable (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>, dotted line) and a stable periodic solution (i.e., oscillations) emerges. The maximum and minimum amplitudes of the periodic solution are depicted by the solid lines. This &#x0201c;oscillatory regime&#x0201d; reflects values of [IP<sub>3</sub>] at which steady oscillations of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> are observed. When [IP<sub>3</sub>] exceeds 0.67, the periodic solution collapses back to a stable, steady state value that is raised considerably compared with that at [IP<sub>3</sub>] before the periodic region. </p><p>From Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>, two other important features are apparent. The first is that, at [IP<sub>3</sub>] just before the oscillatory regime, [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> is raised relative to the resting level and, for [IP<sub>3</sub>] values that give oscillations, the minimum value of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> during the oscillations also remains elevated compared with the resting [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. This feature therefore corresponds to the raised baseline [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> during oscillations that are observed in both the experimental and simulated oscillations (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al. 1991</xref>; and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>).</p><p>The second feature from Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> is that the range of [IP<sub>3</sub>] over which oscillations are generated is very narrow (&#x02248;50 nM). This feature is consistent with the experimental observation that only a narrow range of ACh concentrations is able to elicit oscillations of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Yule and Gallacher, 1988</xref>). It seems reasonable to assume that the narrow range of ACh concentrations generates a relatively narrow range of [IP<sub>3</sub>], although assays for IP<sub>3</sub> are not yet sensitive enough to test this prediction.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>CCK-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations.</title><p>The experimental results indicate that CCK (but not ACh) activates PKA, which phosphorylates the inactivated (I<sub>1</sub> state) receptors, converting them to the I<sub>2</sub> state. The receptors remain in the I<sub>2</sub> state, where they are insensitive to [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, until the action of phosphatases converts them back to the S state. The action of PKA was modeled by increasing <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> to 0.05 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Furthermore, we reduced the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> turnover by decreasing V<sub>p</sub>, the maximum pump rate, to 0.2 &#x003bc;M s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, while the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx was reduced to 0.025 &#x003bc;M s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p><p>Simulated CCK-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>. At 0.6 &#x003bc;M [IP<sub>3</sub>], after a large initial spike, repetitive [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> transients occur with a period of &#x0223c;150 s. The [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> spike kinetics are consistent with the experimental data and the spikes originate from close to the basal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, in contrast to the ACh- induced oscillations. Again, for this simulation, [IP<sub>3</sub>] was raised gradually with a time constant of 100 s to mimic more realistically the effects of agonist application. </p><p>The bifurcation diagram for the full (CCK-activated) model is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>. The threshold [IP<sub>3</sub>] for generating oscillations occurs at &#x0223c;0.56 &#x003bc;M, at which large oscillations occur. Before this, raising [IP<sub>3</sub>] causes little increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. As [IP<sub>3</sub>] is increased through the oscillatory regime, the nadir of the periodic solution (i.e., the minimum [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> value during repetitive oscillations) remains close to the resting value, corresponding to the baseline nature of the oscillations. The minimum [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> only starts to increase as the periodic solution collapses to the stable steady state solution at &#x0223c;0.77 &#x003bc;M [IP<sub>3</sub>]. In contrast, the maximum [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> during oscillations is large at the threshold [IP<sub>3</sub>] and falls markedly as [IP<sub>3</sub>] is further increased. It should be noted though, that the maximum amplitude of the initial [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> spike will depend on the rate of IP<sub>3</sub> accumulation and will typically overshoot the maximum value of the periodic solution. </p><p>The bifurcation diagram shows that simulated CCK-induced oscillations occur for a larger range of [IP<sub>3</sub>] than is the case of ACh (compare Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref> with 9). This is consistent with experimental observations that ACh- induced oscillations occur for only a very narrow concentration range, whereas a wider range of CCK concentration is effective at generating oscillations (Yule, D.I., unpublished data). Finally, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref> shows that, for [IP<sub>3</sub>] above &#x0223c;0.77 &#x003bc;M, a stable steady state solution corresponding to a maintained plateau [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> occurs.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Testing Model Predictions</title><sec disp-level="4"><title>Experiments with Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free media.</title><p>We used the model to investigate the relationship between the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx and generation of ACh-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations. By reducing <italic>J</italic>
<sub>influx</sub>, we can simulate the effect of reducing extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. It turns out that, as <italic>J</italic>
<sub>influx</sub> is decreased, the range of IP<sub>3</sub> concentrations for which oscillations are observed shifts to the right; i.e., to higher [IP<sub>3</sub>]. Thus, a decrease in calcium influx would be expected to abolish oscillations, while an increase in [IP<sub>3</sub>] would be expected to restore them. This behavior is demonstrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref> A. The values for <italic>J</italic>
<sub>influx</sub> and [IP<sub>3</sub>] are indicated at the top of the figure. At the normal <italic>J</italic>
<sub>influx</sub> value of 0.4 &#x003bc;M s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, oscillations are induced when the concentration of IP<sub>3</sub> is raised to 0.66 &#x003bc;M. Reducing <italic>J</italic>
<sub>influx</sub> to 0.35 &#x003bc;M s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> abolishes the oscillations, but these are recovered when [IP<sub>3</sub>] is increased to 0.75 &#x003bc;M. </p><p>Experiments were conducted to test these model predictions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref> B). Acinar cells were exposed to 70 nM ACh, which evoked repetitive oscillations in the presence of 1.2 mM external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. At <italic>t</italic> = 280 s, the external Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration was reduced to 100 mM, which abolished oscillations within one to two oscillation periods. An increase in the ACh concentration (to 100 nM) at 350 s, still in the presence of low external Ca<sup>2+</sup>, restored the oscillations, this time with an increased frequency. The increased frequency is also sometimes seen in the model (computations not shown).</p><p>Comparison of Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>, A and B, shows that the model predictions are confirmed by the experimental data. In the presence of CCK, removal of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> has no immediate effect on the Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1991</xref>), and this effect is also reproduced by the model (computations not shown).</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Effects of phosphorylation on ACh-induced oscillations.</title><p>Using the model, we studied the effects of phosphorylating the IP<sub>3</sub> receptors during ACh-induced oscillations (computations not shown). Oscillations are initiated by 0.66 &#x003bc;M IP<sub>3</sub>, with the other parameters the same as for ACh-induced oscillations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>); in particular, &#x003b1;<sub>4</sub> = 0 to simulate the absence of phosphorylation. Then, at 100 s, &#x003b1;<sub>4</sub> was increased to 0.05 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, to simulate the cAMP-induced phosphorylation of the receptor by PKA. Oscillations are quickly abolished. This prediction is confirmed by existing experimental data (Camello et al., 1996) and our own experiments, in which oscillations induced by 100 ACh are quickly abolished by the addition of 0.1 mM CPT-cAMP (Yule, D.I., unpublished data).</p><p>Although phosphorylation of the receptor can lead to long-period oscillations in the absence of fast membrane transport of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (recall that CCK does not increase the membrane transport of Ca<sup>2+</sup> as much as ACh does), it is unable to do so in the presence of large fluxes of Ca<sup>2+</sup> across the membrane. Essentially, the Ca<sup>2+</sup> ATPase pumps remove Ca<sup>2+</sup> so quickly from the cytoplasm that the Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux through the IP<sub>3</sub>R (which, it must be recalled, is now sitting in a closed phosphorylated state much of the time) cannot keep up the oscillatory cycle. It is only when the IP<sub>3</sub>R is not shunted into the phosphorylated state that the receptor cycle is fast enough to maintain the oscillations.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Discussion"><title>discussion</title><p>Based on old and new experimental data, we have constructed a new model of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R and incorporated it into a whole-cell model for intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in pancreatic acinar cells. This model agrees with recent data on the rates of activation and inactivation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R by Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 1997</xref>), and can reproduce both the short-period, raised baseline oscillations induced by ACh in pancreatic acinar cells, as well as the long-period baseline spiking induced by CCK. The steady state open probability of the model IP<sub>3</sub>R is a monotonically increasing function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, as shown experimentally by <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Hagar et al. (1998)</xref>.</p><p>The ability of the model to reproduce this wide variety of experimental data is based principally on two things. (a) Physiological concentrations of CCK cause rapid phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R while physiological concentrations of ACh do not. Phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R does not appear to be Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependent, and can also result from the addition of CPT-cAMP. Hence, we hypothesize that CCK, via production of cAMP and activation of PKA, shunts the IP<sub>3</sub>R through a phosphorylation pathway that prevents rapid recovery from receptor inactivation. Inactivation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R by Ca<sup>2+</sup> is rapid, as indicated by the data of <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al. (1997)</xref>, and then receptor phosphorylation holds the receptor in an inactivated state. The resulting long-period oscillations are then governed by the time taken to recover from the phosphorylated state. In the absence of phosphorylation (i.e., after stimulation by ACh), the oscillation period is governed principally by the rate of recovery from Ca<sup>2+</sup>-induced inactivation of the receptor. (b) In the presence of ACh, the flux of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in both directions across the plasma membrane is greater than in the presence of CCK. Measurement of the rates of Ca<sup>2+</sup> removal during the downstroke of the oscillations indicates that the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> ATPase activity is much greater in the presence of ACh than in the presence of CCK. Furthermore, it appears that ACh increases the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry from outside the cell much more than does CCK. Indirect evidence for this has appeared before; <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al. (1991)</xref> showed that removal of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> abolishes ACh-induced oscillations, but has little effect on CCK-induced oscillations. By making this assumption in the model, we were able to predict the effect of both reducing external Ca<sup>2+</sup> and increasing agonist concentration. The fact that the model predictions were confirmed by the experimental data lends support to this hypothesis, although this evidence is still indirect.</p><p>It has been known for some years that PKA is able to phosphorylate the IP<sub>3</sub>R; more recently, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Wojcikiewicz and Luo (1998)</xref> have shown that type-I, -II, and -III receptors are differentially susceptible to phosphorylation in intact cell lines (AR4-2J rat pancreatoma and RINm5F rat insulinoma cells). Furthermore, it is also known that CCK activates both the adenylate cyclase and phospholipase C pathways in pancreatic acinar cells, while ACh does not appear to activate the adenylate cyclase pathway (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Schulz, 1989</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Petersen and Wakui, 1990</xref>). However, what is far less clear is the exact effect of IP<sub>3</sub>R phosphorylation. In some cell types, it appears that phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R by PKA inhibits Ca<sup>2+</sup> release (Supattapone et al., 1998; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Volpe and Alderson-Lang, 1990</xref>), while in hepatocytes the opposite effect occurs (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Hajn&#x000f3;czky et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Joseph and Ryan, 1993</xref>). In platelets, PKA phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R causes a 30% inhibition of IP<sub>3</sub>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Quinton and Dean, 1992</xref>), while more recent data shows that PKA inhibits IP<sub>3</sub>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release in megakaryocytes (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Tertyshnikova and Fein, 1998</xref>). In a renal epithelial cell line, kinase activators and phosphatase inhibitors decrease the response to carbachol, while kinase inhibitors increase the response to carbachol (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 1996a</xref>), results that are consistent with the assumptions of our model.</p><p>Our experiments on the phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor were performed in both rats and mice, and similar results were obtained. Thus it is reasonable to assume that the model of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor is applicable to both rats and mice. However, there are quantitative differences between the Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses of rat and mice pancreatic acinar cells to agonist stimulation. In the study of <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Tsunoda et al. (1990)</xref> in rat pancreatic acinar cells in intact acini, Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses to application of CCh took the form of low period baseline spiking, similar to the responses to application of CCK. Since most of the studies showing clear differences between the responses to CCK and ACh have been performed in single isolated mouse pancreatic acinar cells (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Osipchuk et al., 1990</xref>; <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1991</xref>; <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Petersen et al., 1991a</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Lawrie et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Thorn et al., 1993b</xref>), it is not clear whether our conclusions are also applicable to rat pancreatic acinar cells in an acinus. For a start, it is known that gap junctional communication modulates the observed Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in rat pancreatic acini (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Stauffer et al., 1993</xref>), but whether this is sufficient to account quantitatively (or even qualitatively) for the differences in the responses of coupled and isolated cells is not known. Furthermore, it is likely that variations in crucial parameter values, such as pumping and influx rates, will lead to quantitatively different model behavior, and such differences may be one way to explain the differing responses of rat and mice pancreatic acinar cells. However, we have not done exhaustive parameter studies and so cannot say for certain. Note, however, that baseline spiking in response to application of ACh is also seen in mouse pancreatic acinar cells, as long as the concentration of ACh is low enough. Hence, our model is consistent with the data from rat pancreatic acinar cells in this low concentration limit. It is thus plausible that the basic mechanisms are similar in both rat and mice pancreatic acinar cells, differing only in the details of certain parameter values.</p><p>In our model, we have assumed that phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R shunts it into a closed state; it is important to note that this is assuming that phosphorylation neither inhibits nor potentiates Ca<sup>2+</sup> release. Hence, the assumptions underlying our model are consistent with both effects of PKA. This can easily be seen by the following argument. If <italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub> were small, then the intrinsic recovery of the IP<sub>3</sub>R from the inactivated state would be slow; if the rates of phosphorylation and dephosphorylation (<italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> and <italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub>) were large enough, it is possible that shunting the receptor through the phosphorylated I<sub>2</sub> state could increase the steady state open probability. Conversely, if <italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub> were large, and thus the intrinsic recovery from inactivation was fast, then shunting the receptor through the phosphorylated state could decrease the steady state open probability. In fact, we can derive an explicit relationship between <italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub>, <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub>, and <italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub> that will determine the exact effects of phosphorylation on the steady state open probability. The steady state proportion of open receptors, <italic>O</italic>, can be easily calculated as <disp-formula id="E9"><label>9</label><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathit{O}}=\frac{{\phi}p}{\frac{k_{-1}+k_{2}}{k_{1}}{\phi}+p},\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>where <disp-formula id="E10"><label>10</label><tex-math id="M10">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\phi}=\frac{1}{1+\frac{k_{2}}{k_{3}+k_{4}} \left( 1+\frac{k_{4}}{k_{5}} \right) }.\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Thus, the function &#x003c6; controls the sensitivity of the IP<sub>3</sub>R to IP<sub>3</sub>; as &#x003c6; increases, the sensitivity of the IP<sub>3</sub>R decreases, and vice versa. A short calculation now shows that &#x003c6; is an increasing function of <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> when 2<italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub> &#x0003e; <italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub> &#x02212; <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub>, and is a decreasing function of <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> when 2<italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub> &#x0003c; <italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub> &#x02212; <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub>. It follows that, depending on the values chosen for <italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub>, <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub>, and <italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub>, the model can reproduce either an increase or a decrease of sensitivity of the IP<sub>3</sub>R upon phosphorylation.</p><p>Oscillations in the model occur for constant [IP<sub>3</sub>], and are the result of cycles of activation and inactivation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R. At present, there is no direct evidence for our assumption that oscillations in [IP<sub>3</sub>] are not necessary to obtain [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations. From experiments using nonmetabolizable analogs of IP<sub>3</sub>, there is indirect evidence that the observed [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations are not governed by underlying oscillations in [IP<sub>3</sub>] (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Wakui et al., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Thorn et al., 1993b</xref>). However, a complete resolution of this question awaits an experimental determination of the kinetic behavior of [IP<sub>3</sub>] during the course of a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillation. During application of an agonist, [IP<sub>3</sub>] will certainly rise and fall as IP<sub>3</sub> is produced and degraded. We do not build these features into our model directly, but just assume that IP<sub>3</sub> is produced and degraded with given rates. Thus, in the simulations, [IP<sub>3</sub>] increases and decreases gradually. This has little effect on the oscillatory behavior of the model, which can be well understood by considering the behavior at fixed [IP<sub>3</sub>].</p><p>Although it appears that ryanodine receptors do exist in pancreatic acinar cells, we have not included in the model any possible effects of ryanodine receptors or IP<sub>3</sub>-independent Ca<sup>2+</sup>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release. <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Kasai et al. (1993)</xref> have shown that the response to ACh is eliminated by heparin, although there is still Ca<sup>2+</sup>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from the granular area. Thus, although it is likely that IP<sub>3</sub>-independent factors are important for modulating the shape of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations, it appears that they cannot, by themselves, support oscillations. <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Nathanson et al. (1992)</xref> have also shown that Ca<sup>2+</sup>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release has an effect on the speed of ACh and CCK-stimulated intracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> waves. However, neither caffeine nor ryanodine eliminates the waves, although they do decrease the wave speed. Furthermore, the intracellular waves are initiated at the apical zone of the cell, which is where the type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptors are mostly found (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Nathanson et al., 1994</xref>). We interpret these results to mean that the oscillatory period and other fundamental oscillation properties are determined primarily by the properties of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptors in the apical zone, with other forms of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release playing only a modulatory role. Hence, for simplicity, in this model we consider only IP<sub>3</sub> receptors.</p><p>One major difference between our model and previous ones is in the assumption of how Ca<sup>2+</sup> affects the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor. Rather than assuming actual Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites on the receptor (which are not well characterized), we assume that the actions of Ca<sup>2+</sup> arise from its effect on IP<sub>3</sub> binding. Thus, although [IP<sub>3</sub>] is constant during an oscillation, IP<sub>3</sub> nevertheless plays an active dynamic role, as oscillations in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> are driven by cycles of IP<sub>3</sub> binding and unbinding from the receptor. In the case of CCK-induced oscillations, the receptor also undergoes periodic cycles of phosphorylation and dephosphorylation; the oscillation period is then set by the rate of receptor dephosphorylation, rather than by the rate of receptor recovery from inactivation. Calcium-induced calcium release also plays an important role. As [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> increases, the rate of IP<sub>3</sub> binding to the receptor is increased (S to O transition), leading to an effective calcium activation of the receptor.</p><p>Another major difference from previous models is our use of the phosphorylation pathway, through which some agonists will shunt the receptor. It has been recognized for some time that a third mechanism, in addition to Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation and inactivation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R, is required to explain the long interspike intervals that occur in some cells (see, for example, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Oancea and Meyer, 1996</xref>, for an excellent discussion of this). Indeed, phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R has previously been proposed as a possible mechanism for setting the interspike interval (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cameron et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 1996</xref>; in these papers, the phosphorylation was assumed to be Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependent, which it does not appear to be in our cell type). We have shown that such a hypothesis is quantitatively consistent with the observed oscillations, we have collected experimental data that show agonist-dependent rates of phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor and have shown that a single mechanism can be used as a framework to understand widely differing experimental results in a single cell type. Ours is not the first model to generate long interspike intervals. <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Laurent and Claret (1997)</xref> constructed a model of Monod-Wyman-Changeux type and showed that, with appropriate choices of the parameters, the model could reproduce long-period oscillations, while <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Dupont and Swillens (1996)</xref> postulated the existence of an intermediate Ca<sup>2+</sup> domain around the mouth of the receptor to achieve a similar result. Our model differs from these in that we present a single mechanism that can generate a wide variety of oscillatory patterns, and then show experimentally that the necessary elements of the model exist in a particular cell type.</p><p>The simplicity of our model can, in some circumstances, be a disadvantage. Our assumption of independent subunits is unlikely to be correct (as pointed out by <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Laurent and Claret, 1997</xref>), and a more detailed allosteric model of the effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on IP<sub>3</sub> binding would presumably increase the model's accuracy. However, we believe that the additional complications introduced by such procedures are unlikely to be a worthwhile expenditure of effort at this stage. More detailed models of the receptor states and phosphorylations can wait until the properties of the pancreatic acinar IP<sub>3</sub> receptors are known in more detail, and until spatial effects are better understood.</p><p>
<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al. (1996)</xref> have presented a qualitative model that, in many respects, is similar to ours. They conclude that histamine-stimulated Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in HeLa cells result from cycles of phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R by CaMK-II. In their model, just as in ours, phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R inhibits Ca<sup>2+</sup> release by closing the channel. They showed that inhibition of the phosphatase by calyculin A or okadaic acid (which corresponds to a reduction in <italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub> in our model) increases the oscillation period, and this result is reproduced by our model (computations not shown). This emphasizes the importance of receptor dephosphorylation for setting the period of CCK-induced oscillations. In addition, our model is easily adapted to simulate phosphorylation of CaMK-II by letting <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub> = <italic>c</italic>
<sup>4</sup>/(0.5<sup>4</sup> + <italic>c</italic>
<sup>4</sup>). This assumes that phosphorylation by CaMK-II is modulated by Ca<sup>2+</sup> in a cooperative fashion, and thus includes the possibility of feedback from the Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal to receptor phosphorylation. In this case, the model again exhibits long-period baseline spiking (computations not shown).</p><p>One principal feature of our model that is supported only indirectly is the assumption that ACh increases membrane transport of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, while CCK increases it to a lesser extent. In other words, when the cell is at steady state (i.e., in the absence of agonist stimulation) there is a continual, but small, flux of Ca<sup>2+</sup> through the cytoplasm, as Ca<sup>2+</sup> leaks into the cell and is quickly removed. Upon ACh stimulation, overall membrane transport of Ca<sup>2+</sup> is greatly increased, in both directions, and this, in combination with activation of the IP<sub>3</sub>R, results in raised-baseline, sinusoidal, oscillations that are dependent on external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. CCK, on the other hand, increases membrane transport of Ca<sup>2+</sup> only slightly, and thus CCK-induced oscillations depend on external Ca<sup>2+</sup> much less. It has been known for some years that the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> turnover is low at steady state, and that agonists such as CCh and CCK increase the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> pumping out of the cytoplasm, as well as increasing the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Muallem and Beeker, 1989</xref>; <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 1992</xref>). However, what is not clear is whether ACh increases the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> turnover more than does CCK. Our model makes the assumption that it does. Although we used our model to make predictions about the effects of removing external Ca<sup>2+</sup> and subsequently increasing [ACh], and these predictions were confirmed experimentally, and although the model provides a consistent framework that can possibly explain the different effects of low extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> on ACh- or CCK-induced oscillations, this is still only indirect evidence for this assumption. One important test of the model will be to compare transmembrane and trans&#x02013;ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> fluxes directly, in the presence of CCK or ACh, or neither.</p><p>
<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Lawrie et al. (1993)</xref> have shown that application of ACh in the absence of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> will initially cause oscillations, but these die away within a few minutes. This particular result is not reproduced by our model because of the simplified way in which it treats Ca<sup>2+</sup> pumping. When Ca<sup>2+</sup> is removed from the cytoplasm by pumps, it can be removed either to the outside or to the ER. It is easy to see that the rate of removal to the ER has no effect on the long term steady state [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> of the cell, which can only be affected by Ca<sup>2+</sup> transport across the plasma membrane. When ACh is applied to a cell in low [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, the kinetics of the IP<sub>3</sub>R can still lead to cycles of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release and uptake from the ER, but each time Ca<sup>2+</sup> is released into the cell cytoplasm, a fraction of it is lost to the outside. Eventually, the cell runs down and oscillations stop, as observed. Thus, over a longer time scale, depletion of the ER plays a role in terminating Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations. The only way to model this is to treat Ca<sup>2+</sup> transport across the ER membrane separately from Ca<sup>2+</sup> transport across the plasma membrane, a feature that is omitted from our model for the sake of simplicity. However, we have constructed an extended version of the model, in which we take into account depletion of the ER (LeBeau, Yule, and Sneyd, unpublished data). The extended model behaves in a similar manner to the model presented here, but can account for a wider array of experimental results, including long-time oscillatory behavior and the application of ACh in the absence of external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Details of this model and comparison with experimental results will be presented in a later paper.</p><p>Another important feature of the model is the assumption that an increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> causes an increase in the binding affinity of IP<sub>3</sub> to its receptor. The experimental data on the properties of IP<sub>3</sub> binding as a function of Ca<sup>2+</sup> are not completely consistent. <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yoneshima et al. (1997)</xref> claim that Ca<sup>2+</sup> increases the binding affinity of IP<sub>3</sub> to type-III receptors, but decreases the binding affinity to type-I receptors. However, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cardy et al. (1997)</xref>, although agreeing that the major effect of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on IP<sub>3</sub> binding is stimulatory for type-III and inhibitory for type-I receptors, claim that these effects are mediated by changes in the maximal binding (although, for type-III receptors, more complex effects occur at higher Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations). Nevertheless, they conclude that Ca<sup>2+</sup> regulates the interconversion of the IP<sub>3</sub>R between two different states, one state with a high IP<sub>3</sub> affinity, and the other with a low affinity. This interpretation is entirely consistent with our results, as our model can in fact be rigorously derived by considering just such a receptor mechanism (Sneyd, LeBeau, and Yule, manuscript submitted for publication).</p><p>As we show in the <xref ref-type="app" rid="N0x1c9a340N0x347d0e0">Appendix</xref>, a decrease in IP<sub>3</sub> binding affinity with increasing Ca<sup>2+</sup> implies that the peak of the steady state open probability curve shifts to the right as [IP<sub>3</sub>] increases. Conversely, an increase in the IP<sub>3</sub> binding affinity with increasing Ca<sup>2+</sup> implies that the steady state open probability curve will shift to the left with increasing [IP<sub>3</sub>]. Thus, since type-I receptors have a decreasing IP<sub>3</sub> binding affinity with increasing Ca<sup>2+</sup>, the model predicts that the steady state open probability curve will shift to the right with increasing [IP<sub>3</sub>], exactly as seen by <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kaftan et al. (1997)</xref>. On the other hand, since type-III receptors have an increasing IP<sub>3</sub> binding affinity with increasing Ca<sup>2+</sup>, we predict that the steady state open probability curve will shift to the left with increasing [IP<sub>3</sub>]. These measurements have yet to be performed. No models to date (at least that we know of) have investigated the effects of changes in the maximal binding. In this context, it is important to note that the open probability curve at infinite [IP<sub>3</sub>] does not give the maximal binding curve. In our model (and all other receptor binding models that we have investigated), the maximal binding fraction is always 1 and, as in the presence of large amounts of IP<sub>3</sub>, all receptors will bind IP<sub>3</sub>.</p><p>As well as the temporal responses to ACh and CCK being quite different, the spatial characteristics of the response are also agonist dependent (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Lawrie et al., 1993</xref>; Thorn et al.; 1993a; <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 1996b</xref>). ACh- induced oscillations are initiated at the secretory pole of the cell, and spread from there across the cell, with the response at the basal pole being consistently of smaller amplitude and slightly delayed. During the course of this intracellular wave, significant Ca<sup>2+</sup> gradients are maintained in the cell cytoplasm. CCK, on the other hand, causes an increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> that is simultaneous across the entire cell, with no change in amplitude from secretory to basal poles. Furthermore, these intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> waves can be transmitted intercellularly when individual cells in acini are coupled to their neighbors via gap junctions (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Yule et al., 1996</xref>). A prerequisite for the study of such intra- and intercellular waves is a detailed understanding of the kinetics underlying the oscillatory response in each individual cell. Thus, although the current study does not address these questions, our model provides a useful framework that can be used to study the problem of wave propagation in this cell type.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank John Williams for helpful discussions. We also thank Dr. Jean-Fran&#x000e7;ois Dufour, The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology Inc., and Cell Calcium for permission to reprint figures.</p><p>This work was supported by grants from the New Zealand Lottery Grants Board (AP047957), the Marsden Fund of the Royal Society of New Zealand, NIGMS grant R01 GM56126 (J. Sneyd), National Science Foundation grant DMS 9706565 (JS) and National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases grant R01 DK54568 (D.I. Yule).</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p>Drs. Yule and Groblewski's present address is Department of Pharmacology and Physiology, University of Rochester, School of Medicine, Rochester, NY.</p></fn></fn-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations used in this paper</title><def-list><def-item><term>Ach</term><def><p>acetylcholine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CaMK-II</term><def><p>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-calmodulin kinase II</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCK</term><def><p>cholecystokinin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPA</term><def><p>cyclopiazonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ER</term><def><p>endoplasmic reticulum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IP<sub>3</sub></term><def><p>inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IP<sub>3</sub>R</term><def><p>IP<sub>3</sub> receptor</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><app-group><app id="N0x1c9a340N0x347d0e0"><title>appendix</title><sec><title>The Steady State Open Probability of the IP<sub>3</sub>R</title><p>In the majority of current models of the IP<sub>3</sub>R, the steady state receptor open probability, <italic>O</italic>, can be expressed in the general form <disp-formula id="E11"><label>11</label><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathit{O}}=\frac{{\theta}_{1}(c)p}{p+{\theta}_{2}(c)}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>for some functions &#x00398;<sub>1</sub> and &#x00398;<sub>2</sub>. The exact form of these two functions differs from model to model. However, we note two things. First, <italic>p</italic> = &#x00398;<sub>2</sub>(<italic>c</italic>) gives the half-maximal IP<sub>3</sub> binding to the receptor, and thus &#x00398;<sub>2</sub>(<italic>c</italic>) is the EC<sub>50</sub> of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor, with respect to IP<sub>3</sub> binding. It thus follows from experimental data (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yoneshima et al., 1997</xref>) that, for type-I receptors, &#x00398;<sub>2</sub> is an increasing function of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, while for type-III receptors, &#x00398;<sub>2</sub> is a decreasing function of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Secondly, &#x00398;<sub>1</sub>(<italic>c</italic>) is the open probability as a function of <italic>c</italic>, when <italic>p</italic> is very large; i.e., in the limit of high [IP<sub>3</sub>].</p></sec><sec><title>Bell-shaped Steady State Curve</title><p>If <italic>O</italic> is a bell-shaped function of <italic>c</italic>, it follows that it must have a turning point, at which place <inline-formula><tex-math id="M12">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{{\partial}{\mathit{O}}}{{\partial}c}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> = 0. Hence, at the turning point, <disp-formula id="E12"><label>12</label><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}(p+{\theta}_{2}){\theta}^{\prime}_{1}={\theta}_{1}{\theta}^{\prime}_{2}.\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>If we let <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub> denote the position of the turning point, then Eq. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E12">12</xref> can be solved to obtain <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub> = <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub>(<italic>p</italic>). We want to know whether <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub> is an increasing or decreasing function of <italic>p</italic>. In other words, does the peak of the bell-shaped curve move to the right or to the left as <italic>p</italic> increases.</p><p>First, we note that an implicit differentiation gives <disp-formula id="E13"><label>13</label><tex-math id="M14">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}c^{\prime}_{0}(p)=\frac{{\theta}^{\prime}_{1}}{{\theta}_{1}{\theta}^{\prime\prime}_{2}-{\theta}^{\prime\prime}_{2}(p+{\theta}_{2})}.\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>It thus follows that the only way <italic>c</italic>&#x02032;<sub>0</sub>(<italic>p</italic>) can change sign is if &#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>1</sub>(<italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub>) changes sign. [We do not let the denominator change sign, because if it did, then <italic>c</italic>&#x02032;<sub>0</sub>(<italic>p</italic>) would become infinite, which is clearly unphysiological. For the same reason, we also exclude singular cases, where both the numerator and denominator vanish together.] Finally, we note that, at the turning point, <italic>p</italic> + &#x00398;<sub>2</sub> = &#x00398;<sub>1</sub>&#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>2</sub>/&#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>1</sub>, and so, from Eq. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E11">11</xref>, it follows that the open probability at the turning point, <italic>O</italic>
<sub>tp</sub>, is given by <disp-formula id="E14"><label>14</label><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathit{O}}_{tp}=\frac{{\theta}_{1}{\theta}^{\prime}_{1}p}{{\theta}_{1}{\theta}^{\prime}_{2}}=\frac{{\theta}^{\prime}_{1}p}{{\theta}^{\prime}_{2}}.\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>We know that, for type-I receptors, &#x00398;<sub>2</sub> is an increasing function of <italic>c</italic>. Hence, for this receptor type, &#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; 0. From Eq. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E14">14</xref>, it now follows that <italic>O</italic>
<sub>tp</sub> is positive only when &#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>1</sub> &#x0003e; 0 at the turning point. However, recall that &#x00398;<sub>1</sub> is just the open probability curve at high <italic>p</italic>. Hence, for lower values of <italic>p</italic>, the peak of the open probability curve must occur at values of <italic>c</italic> for which &#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>1</sub> &#x0003e; 0. Since &#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>1</sub> cannot change sign, neither can <italic>c</italic>&#x02032;<sub>0</sub>(<italic>p</italic>). It remains only to determine which sign it is. However, it is easy to see that, when <italic>p</italic> is large, <italic>c</italic>&#x02032;<sub>0</sub>(<italic>p</italic>) must be positive. Hence, <italic>c</italic>&#x02032;<sub>0</sub>(<italic>p</italic>) is always positive for all <italic>p</italic>, from which it follows that the peak of the bell-shaped curve must move to the right as <italic>p</italic> increases. [It is interesting to note that the same argument works when &#x00398;<sub>2</sub> is a decreasing function of <italic>c</italic>, and thus &#x00398;<sub>1</sub> &#x0003c; 0. In this case, <italic>c</italic>&#x02032;<sub>0</sub>(<italic>p</italic>) is always negative for all <italic>p</italic>, from which it follows that the peak of the bell-shaped curve must move to the left as <italic>p</italic> increases.)</p></sec><sec><title>Monotonic Steady State Curve</title><p>Type-III receptors do not have bell-shaped steady state open probability curves, and thus the above argument does not apply to them. However, a similar argument can be used to show that the steady state open probability curve (i.e., the point of maximum slope) shifts to the left as <italic>p</italic> increases.</p><p>Suppose the steady state open probability curve is monotonically increasing, and define <disp-formula id="E15"><label>15</label><tex-math id="M16">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\theta}^{max}_{1}=\begin{matrix}lim\;{\theta}_{1}(c), \enskip  &#x00026; \\ c{\rightarrow}{\infty} \enskip  &#x00026; \end{matrix}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="E16"><label>16</label><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\theta}^{max}_{2}=\begin{matrix}lim\;{\theta}_{2}(c). \enskip  &#x00026; \\ c{\rightarrow}{\infty} \enskip  &#x00026; \end{matrix}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>For a fixed value of <italic>p</italic>, the steady state open probability curve, <italic>O</italic>, reaches half its maximum value at the point <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub>, where <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub> is found by solving the equation <disp-formula id="E17"><label>17</label><tex-math id="M18">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{{\theta}_{1}(c_{0})p}{p+{\theta}_{2}(c_{0})}=\frac{1}{2}{\cdot}\frac{{\theta}^{max}_{1}p}{p+{\theta}^{max}_{2}}.\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Note that this defines <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub> as a function of <italic>p</italic>; i.e., <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub>(<italic>p</italic>). We now want to find out whether <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub> is an increasing function of <italic>p</italic> (in which case the curves shift to the right as <italic>p</italic> increases), or a decreasing function of <italic>p</italic> (in which case the curves shift to the left as <italic>p</italic> increases).</p><p>Differentiate both sides with respect to <italic>p</italic> to get <disp-formula id="E18"><label>18</label><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{dc_{0}}{dp}=\frac{{\theta}_{1}-\frac{{\theta}^{max}_{1}(p+{\theta}_{2})^{2}}{(p+{\theta}^{max}_{2})^{2}}}{{\theta}^{\prime}_{1}(p+{\theta}_{2})-{\theta}_{1}{\theta}^{\prime}_{2}},\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>where all functions of <italic>c</italic> are evaluated at <italic>c</italic>
<sub>0</sub>.</p><p>For a type-III receptor, &#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>2</sub>(<italic>c</italic>) &#x0003c; 0 (as argued above), and we also suppose that the steady state open probability curve is monotonic for all IP<sub>3</sub> concentrations and thus &#x00398;&#x02032;<sub>1</sub>(<italic>c</italic>) &#x0003e; 0. If, for any <italic>p</italic>, the steady state curve becomes bell-shaped, the previous argument applies. Since <disp-formula id="E19"><label>19</label><tex-math id="M20">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\theta}_{1}-{\theta}^{max}_{1}\frac{(p+{\theta}_{2})^{2}}{(p+{\theta}^{max}_{2})^{2}}&#x0003c;0,\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>it now follows that &#x003b8;<inline-formula><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\begin{matrix}max \enskip  &#x00026; \\ 2 \enskip  &#x00026; \end{matrix}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> &#x0003c; &#x003b8;<sub>2</sub>(<italic>c</italic>), and &#x003b8;<inline-formula><tex-math id="M22">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\begin{matrix}max \enskip  &#x00026; \\ 1 \enskip  &#x00026; \end{matrix}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> &#x0003e; &#x003b8;<sub>1</sub>(<italic>c</italic>), and thus <italic>c</italic>&#x02009;&#x02032;<sub>0</sub>( <italic>p</italic>) &#x0003c; 0.</p><p>In conclusion, we have predicted that, as <italic>p</italic> increases, the steady state open probability curve of a type-III IP<sub>3</sub>R will move to the left. To our knowledge, this has not yet been experimentally measured.</p></sec></app></app-group><ref-list><title>references</title><ref id="B1"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amundson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sneyd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A single-pool model for intra-cellular calcium oscillations and waves in the <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic>oocyte</article-title>
<source>Biophysical J</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>1727</fpage>
<lpage>1739</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8274661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium oscillations</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>265</volume>
<fpage>9583</fpage>
<lpage>9586</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2161835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>BVL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inositol trisphosphate analogues induce different oscillatory patterns in <italic>Xenopus</italic>oocytes</article-title>
<source>Cell Regul</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>675</fpage>
<lpage>681</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1706629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Elementary and global aspects of calcium signalling</article-title>
<source>J Physiol</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>499</volume>
<fpage>291</fpage>
<lpage>306</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9080360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bezprozvanny</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Theoretical analysis of calcium wave propagation based on inositol (1,4,5)-trisphosphate (InsP<sub>3</sub>) receptor functional properties</article-title>
<source>Cell Calc</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>151</fpage>
<lpage>166</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7828170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bezprozvanny</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (InsP<sub>3</sub>) receptor</article-title>
<source>J Membr Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>145</volume>
<fpage>205</fpage>
<lpage>216</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7563022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camello</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Toescu</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Simultaneous presence of cAMP and cGMP exert a co-ordinated inhibitory effect on the agonist-evoked Ca<sup>2+</sup>signal in pancreatic acinar cells</article-title>
<source>Pfl&#x000fc;gers Arch</source>
<year>1966</year>
<volume>432</volume>
<fpage>775</fpage>
<lpage>781</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8772126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskams</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronnett</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcineurin associated with the inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor-FKBP12 complex modulates Ca<sup>2+</sup>flux</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>463</fpage>
<lpage>472</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8521476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardy</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Differential regulation of types-1 and -3 inositol trisphosphate receptor by cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup>
</article-title>
<source>Biochem J</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>328</volume>
<fpage>785</fpage>
<lpage>793</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Young</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Keizer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A single pool IP<sub>3</sub>-receptor based model for agonist stimulated Ca<sup>2+</sup>oscillations</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>9895</fpage>
<lpage>9899</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1329108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate and calcium regulate the calcium channel function of the hepatic inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>272</volume>
<fpage>2675</fpage>
<lpage>2681</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9006903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Swillens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Quantal release, incremental detection and long-period Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in a model based on regulatory Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding sites along the permeation pathway</article-title>
<source>Biophys J</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>1714</fpage>
<lpage>1722</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8889149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium as a coagonist of inositol 1,4,5-trisphospate-induced calcium release</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>252</volume>
<fpage>443</fpage>
<lpage>446</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2017683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grynkiewicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poenie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A new generation of Ca<sup>2+</sup>indicators with greatly improved fluorescent properties</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1985</year>
<volume>260</volume>
<fpage>3440</fpage>
<lpage>3450</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3838314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagar</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgstahler</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathanson</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Type III InsP<sub>3</sub>receptor channel stays open in the presence of increased calcium</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>396</volume>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>84</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9817204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hajn&#x000f3;czky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoek</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Multiple mechanisms by which protein kinase A potentiates inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>mobilization in permeabilized hepatocytes</article-title>
<source>Biochem J</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>293</volume>
<fpage>413</fpage>
<lpage>422</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8393659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hajn&#x000f3;czky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The inositol trisphosphate calcium channel is inactivated by inositol trisphosphate</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>370</volume>
<fpage>474</fpage>
<lpage>477</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8047168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hajn&#x000f3;czky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Minimal requirements for calcium oscillations driven by the IP<sub>3</sub>receptor</article-title>
<source>EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>3533</fpage>
<lpage>3543</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9218795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phosphorylation of the inositol trisphosphate receptor in isolated rat hepatocytes</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>268</volume>
<fpage>23059</fpage>
<lpage>23065</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8226822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The inositol triphosphate receptor family</article-title>
<source>Cell Signal</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8777135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaftan</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Watras</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (InsP<sub>3</sub>) and calcium interact to increase the dynamic range of InsP<sub>3</sub>receptor-dependent calcium signaling</article-title>
<source>J Gen Physiol</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>529</fpage>
<lpage>538</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9348325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Subcellular distribution of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release channels underlying Ca<sup>2+</sup>waves and oscillations in exocrine pancreas</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>669</fpage>
<lpage>677</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8395348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawanishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harootunian</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ca<sup>2+</sup>oscillations induced by hormonal stimulation of individual fura-2&#x02013;loaded hepatocytes</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1989</year>
<volume>264</volume>
<fpage>12859</fpage>
<lpage>12866</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2473983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Claret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Signal-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations through the regulation of the inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup>channel: an allosteric model</article-title>
<source>J Theor Biol</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>186</volume>
<fpage>307</fpage>
<lpage>326</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9219669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawrie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Toescu</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallacher</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Two different spatiotemporal patterns for Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in pancreatic acinar cells: evidence of a role for protein kinase C in Ins(1,4,5)P<sub>3</sub>-mediated Ca<sup>2+</sup>signalling</article-title>
<source>Cell Calc</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>698</fpage>
<lpage>710</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7510580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keizer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojilkovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium oscillations in pituitary gonadotrophs: comparison of experiment and theory</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>91</volume>
<fpage>58</fpage>
<lpage>62</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8278407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Equations for InsP<sub>3</sub> receptor-mediated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] oscillations derived from a detailed kinetic model: a Hodgkin-Huxley like formalism</article-title>
<source>J Theor Biol</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>166</volume>
<fpage>461</fpage>
<lpage>473</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8176949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojilkovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Keizer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sensing and refilling calcium stores in an excitable cell</article-title>
<source>Biophys J</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>1080</fpage>
<lpage>1091</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9138557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loessberg</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Synchronized oscillation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry and Ca<sup>2+</sup>release in agonist-stimulated AR42J cells</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>266</volume>
<fpage>1363</fpage>
<lpage>1366</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1899088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lytton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Westlin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Burk</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>MacLennan</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Functional comparisons between isoforms of the sarcoplasmic or endoplasmic reticulum family of calcium pumps</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>2667</volume>
<fpage>14483</fpage>
<lpage>14489</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1385815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rapid kinetic measurements of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization reveal that Ins(2,4,5)P<sub>3</sub> is a partial agonist at hepatic InsP<sub>3</sub>receptors</article-title>
<source>Biochem J</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>321</volume>
<fpage>573</fpage>
<lpage>576</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9032438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rapid activation and partial inactivation of inositol trisphosphate receptors by inositol trisphosphate</article-title>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>11524</fpage>
<lpage>11533</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9708988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>ICB</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biphasic effects of cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> on Ins(1,4,5)P<sub>3</sub>-stimulated Ca<sup>2+</sup>mobilization in hepatocytes</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>268</volume>
<fpage>13214</fpage>
<lpage>13220</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8514760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeker</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Relationship between hormonal, GTP and Ins(1,4,5)P<sub>3</sub>-stimulated Ca<sup>2+</sup>uptake and release in pancreatic acinar cells</article-title>
<source>Biochem J</source>
<year>1989</year>
<volume>263</volume>
<fpage>333</fpage>
<lpage>339</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2688630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of intracellular calcium in epithelial cells</article-title>
<source>Semin Cell Biol</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>305</fpage>
<lpage>310</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2103515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nathanson</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Padfield</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgstahler</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanism of Ca<sup>2+</sup>wave propagation in pancreatic acinar cells</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>267</volume>
<fpage>18118</fpage>
<lpage>18121</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1517244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nathanson</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fallon</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Padfield</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maranto</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Localization of the type 3 inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor in the Ca<sup>2+</sup>wave trigger zone of pancreatic acinar cells</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>269</volume>
<fpage>4693</fpage>
<lpage>4696</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7508924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oancea</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reversible desensitization of inositol trisphosphate&#x02013;induced calcium release provides a mechanism for repetitive calcium spikes</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>271</volume>
<fpage>17253</fpage>
<lpage>17260</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8663416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osipchuk</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yule</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallacher</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations evoked by receptor stimulation, G-protein activation, internal application of inositol trisphosphate or Ca<sup>2+</sup>: simultaneous microfluorimetry and Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependent C1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>current recording in single pancreatic acinar cells</article-title>
<source>EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>697</fpage>
<lpage>704</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1690123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivorra</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition by Ca<sup>2+</sup> of inositol trisphosphate&#x02013;mediated Ca<sup>2+</sup> liberation: a possible mechanism for oscillatory release of Ca<sup>2+</sup>
</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>260</fpage>
<lpage>264</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2296584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Oscillating intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>signals evoked by activation of receptors linked to inositol lipid hydrolysis: mechanism of generation</article-title>
<source>J Membr Biol</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>93</fpage>
<lpage>105</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2176239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallacher</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yule</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CCH</given-names></name><name><surname>Toescu</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Receptor-activated cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in pancreatic acinar cells: generation and spreading of Ca<sup>2+</sup>signals</article-title>
<source>Cell Calc</source>
<year>1991a</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>135</fpage>
<lpage>144</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1647874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CCH</given-names></name><name><surname>Toescu</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Different patterns of receptor-activated cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in single pancreatic acinar cells: dependence on receptor type, agonist concentration and intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>buffering</article-title>
<source>EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</source>
<year>1991b</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>527</fpage>
<lpage>533</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1705883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinton</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic AMP-dependent phosphorylation of the inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor inhibits Ca<sup>2+</sup>release from platelet membranes</article-title>
<source>Biochem Biophys Commun</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>184</volume>
<fpage>893</fpage>
<lpage>899</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schulz, I. 1989. Signaling transduction in hormone- and neurotransmitter-induced enzyme secretion from the exocrine pancreas. <italic>In</italic> Handbook of Physiology. Section 6, The Gastrointestinal System. Vol. III. American Physiological Society, Washington, DC. 443&#x02013;463.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sienaert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Missiaen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De Smedt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Parys</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sipma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Casteels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular and functional evidence for multiple Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding in the type I inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>272</volume>
<fpage>25899</fpage>
<lpage>25906</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9325322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sneyd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keizer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms of calcium oscillations and waves: a quantitative analysis</article-title>
<source>FASEB J</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>1463</fpage>
<lpage>1472</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7589988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stauffer</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luby-Phelps</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Star</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Gap junction communication modulates [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>oscillations and enzyme secretion in pancreatic acini</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>268</volume>
<fpage>19769</fpage>
<lpage>19775</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8366115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Supattapone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Danoff</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Theibert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic AMP-dependent phosphorylation of a brain inositol trisphosphate receptor decreases its release of calcium</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>1988</year>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>8747</fpage>
<lpage>8750</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2847175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Othmer</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Simplification and analysis of models of calcium dynamics based on IP<sub>3</sub>-sensitive calcium channel kinetics</article-title>
<source>Biophys J</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>246</fpage>
<lpage>263</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8770202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium and inositol trisphosphate receptors</article-title>
<source>J Membr Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>145</volume>
<fpage>109</fpage>
<lpage>118</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7563013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inositol trisphosphate receptors: Ca<sup>2+</sup>-modulated intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>channels</article-title>
<source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>1436</volume>
<fpage>19</fpage>
<lpage>33</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9838027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tertyshnikova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition of inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>release by cAMP-dependent protein kinase in a living cell</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>1613</fpage>
<lpage>1617</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9465064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallacher</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ca<sup>2+</sup>oscillations in pancreatic acinar cells: spatiotemporal relationships and functional implications</article-title>
<source>Cell Calc</source>
<year>1993a</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>746</fpage>
<lpage>757</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8131191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallacher</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Local and global cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup>oscillations in exocrine cells evoked by agonists and inositol trisphosphate</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1993b</year>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>661</fpage>
<lpage>668</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8395347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsunoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuenkel</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Oscillatory model of calcium signaling in rat pancreatic acinar cells</article-title>
<source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>258</volume>
<fpage>C147</fpage>
<lpage>C155</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2301562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Alderson-Lang</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate&#x02013;induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>release II. Effect of cAMP- dependent protein kinase</article-title>
<source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>258</volume>
<fpage>C1086</fpage>
<lpage>C1091</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2163198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wakui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>BVL</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pulsatile intracellular calcium release does not depend on fluctuations in inositol trisphosphate concentration</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>1989</year>
<volume>339</volume>
<fpage>317</fpage>
<lpage>320</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2498663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watras</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezprozvanny</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate&#x02013;gated channels in cerebellum: presence of multiple conductance states</article-title>
<source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>3239</fpage>
<lpage>3245</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1719158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Korc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dormer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Action of secretagogues on a new preparation of functionally intact pancreatic acini</article-title>
<source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1978</year>
<volume>235</volume>
<fpage>E517</fpage>
<lpage>E524</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wojcikiewicz</surname><given-names>RJH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Type I, II, and III inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptors are unequally susceptible to down-regulation and are expressed in markedly different proportions in different cell types</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>270</volume>
<fpage>11678</fpage>
<lpage>11683</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7744807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wojcikiewicz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phosphorylation in inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptors by cAMP-dependent protein kinase. Type I, II, and III receptors are differentially susceptible to phosphorylation and are phosphorylated in intact cells</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>273</volume>
<fpage>5670</fpage>
<lpage>5677</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9488697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Differential regulation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup>influx by heterotrimeric G proteins</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>270</volume>
<fpage>29169</fpage>
<lpage>29175</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7493943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of the inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate&#x02013;activated Ca<sup>2+</sup>by activation of G proteins</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1996a</year>
<volume>271</volume>
<fpage>11737</fpage>
<lpage>11744</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8662624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Spacial compartmentalization of Ca<sup>2+</sup>signaling complexes in pancreatic acini</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1996b</year>
<volume>271</volume>
<fpage>24684</fpage>
<lpage>24690</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8798736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gukovskaya</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandol</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>nNOS and Ca<sup>2+</sup>influx in rat pancreatic acinar and submandibular salivary gland cells</article-title>
<source>Cell Calc</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>217</fpage>
<lpage>228</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9330792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoneshima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyawaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Michikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuichi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikoshiba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ca<sup>2+</sup>differentially regulates the ligand-affinity states of type 1 and type 3 inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptors</article-title>
<source>Biochem J</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>322</volume>
<fpage>591</fpage>
<lpage>596</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9065781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structure and function and inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor</article-title>
<source>Jpn J Pharmacol</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>125</fpage>
<lpage>137</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9243320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yule</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallacher</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Oscillations of cytosolic calcium in single pancreatic acinar cells stimulated by acetylcholine</article-title>
<source>FEBS Lett</source>
<year>1988</year>
<volume>239</volume>
<fpage>358</fpage>
<lpage>362</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3141216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yule</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallacher</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Acetylcholine and cholecystokinin induce different patterns of oscillating calcium signals in pancreatic acinar cells</article-title>
<source>Cell Calc</source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>145</fpage>
<lpage>151</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2059990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yule</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Logsdon</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A cloned CCK-A receptor transduces multiple signals in response to full and partial agonists</article-title>
<source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>265</volume>
<fpage>G999</fpage>
<lpage>G1004</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8238528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yule</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuenkel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Intercellular calcium waves in rat pancreatic acini: mechanism of transmission</article-title>
<source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>271</volume>
<fpage>C1285</fpage>
<lpage>C1294</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8897836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>BX</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Loessberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Activation of the plasma membrane Ca<sup>2+</sup>pump during agonist stimulation of pancreatic acini</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>267</volume>
<fpage>15419</fpage>
<lpage>15425</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1322397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tekle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chock</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reversible phosphorylation as a controlling factor for sustaining calcium oscillations in HeLa cells: involvement of calmodulin-dependent kinase II and a calyculin A-inhibitable phosphatase</article-title>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>7214</fpage>
<lpage>7223</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8679550</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Phosphorylation of type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptor after stimulation by cholecystokinin in rat pancreatic acini: acini were prepared and samples were processed as detailed in the <sc>Methods</sc>. (A) In acini under control conditions, a single phosphorylated band was observed at &#x0223c;300 kD, corresponding to the type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptor. On stimulation by CCK, the intensity of this band increased; the increase was detected at 10 pM CCK and reached a maximum at 100 pM CCK. These concentrations of CCK are physiologically relevant and induce oscillatory [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> signals. In the extreme right lane, samples were processed in an identical manner except that the immunoprecipitating antisera were omitted. (B) Pooled data (mean &#x000b1; SEM) from at least three independent experiments, where samples were run in duplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Phosphorylation of type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptor after stimulation by carbachol in rat pancreatic acini. (A) Stimulation with the muscarinic agonist carbachol also results in increased phosphorylation of the type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptor. Increased phosphorylation of the 300-kD protein could be detected at 1 &#x003bc;M, concentrations of carbachol that induce &#x0201c;peak-and-plateau&#x0201d; type Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses. No phosphorylation could be detected at concentrations of CCh that induce [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations. (B) Pooled data (mean &#x000b1; SEM) from at least three independent experiments, where samples were run in duplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Phosphorylation of type-III IP<sub>3</sub> receptor in rat pancreatic acini after stimulation by agents that modulate second-messenger levels. (A) Increased phosphorylation of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor could be detected from acini samples incubated with CPT-cAMP, a cell-permeable cAMP analogue, but not from samples incubated with agents known to increase [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (30 &#x003bc;m CPA) or activate protein kinase C (10 nM TPA). (B) Pooled data (mean &#x000b1; SEM) from at least three independent experiments, where samples were run in duplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Diagram of the receptor states of the model of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor. Phosphorylation of the receptor by PKA shunts the receptor through the I<sub>2</sub> state, thus shutting off the Ca<sup>2+</sup> current, and leading to long-period oscillations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Data, reproduced from <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al. (1997)</xref>, Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> A and 2 A, showing the effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and IP<sub>3</sub> on Ca<sup>2+</sup> efflux through IP<sub>3</sub> receptors from the rat liver. For the Ca<sup>2+</sup> dose response, the concentration of IP<sub>3</sub> was held at 10 &#x003bc;M and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] was stepped up and held at the indicated concentration. For the IP<sub>3</sub> dose response, [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] was held fixed at 400 nM and [IP<sub>3</sub>] was stepped up and held fixed at the indicated concentrations. The efflux through the receptor was then measured every 70 ms. Figure reprinted with permission.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f5"/></fig><table-wrap id="TI" position="float"><label>Table I</label><caption><p>Parameter Values for the IP<sub>3</sub>R Model </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
<sub>flux</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum IP<sub>3</sub>R flux rate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 &#x003bc;M &#x000b7; s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>J</italic>
<sub>influx</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca<sup>2+</sup> leak rate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.4 (0.025) &#x003bc;M &#x000b7; s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V<sub>p</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum pump rate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;2.6 (0.2) &#x003bc;M &#x000b7; s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>K</italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> for half-maximal pumping</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.54 &#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum rate of <italic>k</italic>
<sub>l</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 &#x003bc;M &#x000b7; s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;<sub>1</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> for half-maximal <italic>k</italic>
<sub>l</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.8 &#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
<sub>&#x02212;1</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate of O to S transition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.88 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
<sub>2</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate of O to I<sub>l</sub> transition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.5 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
<sub>3</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate of I<sub>l</sub> to S transition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.5 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;<sub>4</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum rate of <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0 (0.06) s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;<sub>4</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[IP<sub>3</sub>] for half-maximal <italic>k</italic>
<sub>4</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.01 &#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
<sub>5</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate of I<sub>2</sub> to S transition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.02 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The values in brackets are those used to model CCK-induced oscillations. &#x000a0;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Dose responses, calculated from the model. The same Ca<sup>2+</sup> and IP<sub>3</sub> concentrations as in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> were used, except that the whole range of concentrations was not covered.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f6"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Steady state open probability of the model IP<sub>3</sub> receptor, as a function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], for a range of constant IP<sub>3</sub> concentrations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f7"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Typical ACh-induced oscillations in the model for [IP<sub>3</sub>] = 0.66 &#x003bc;M.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f8"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Bifurcation diagram for ACh-induced model oscillations showing the values of [IP<sub>3</sub>] for which oscillations occur. A dotted line denotes an unstable steady state, while a solid line denotes a stable steady state or a stable oscillation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f9"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Typical CCK-induced oscillations in the model for [IP<sub>3</sub>] = 0.6 &#x003bc;M.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f10"/></fig><fig id="F11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Bifurcation diagram for CCK- induced model oscillations, showing the values of [IP<sub>3</sub>] for which oscillations occur. A dotted line denotes an unstable steady state, while a solid line denotes a stable steady state, or a stable oscillation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f11"/></fig><fig id="F12" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>(A) The effect of reducing external Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the model. ACh-induced oscillations are abolished by reducing to 0.35 &#x003bc;M s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> the Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx from outside the cell. Oscillations are then restored by increasing the IP<sub>3</sub> concentration to 0.75 &#x003bc;M. (B) Experimental test of the prediction in A. Mouse pancreatic acinar cells were first exposed to 70 nM ACh in the presence of 1.2 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>, which initiated oscillations. Reduction of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> to 100 nM abolished the oscillations, but an increase in ACh concentration to 100 nM restored the oscillations, as predicted by the model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7887.f12"/></fig></floats-group></article>