<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Syst Biol</journal-id><journal-title>Molecular Systems Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1744-4292</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19225456</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2657531</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">msb200878</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2008.78</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Harmonic oscillator model of the insulin and IGF1 receptors' allosteric binding and activation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kiselyov</surname><given-names>Vladislav V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="O1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Versteyhe</surname><given-names>Soetkin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="O1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gauguin</surname><given-names>Lisbeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="O1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="O1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="O1"><label>1</label>Receptor Systems Biology Laboratory, Hagedorn Research Institute, Gentofte, Denmark</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label>Receptor Systems Biology Laboratory, Hagedorn Research Institute, Niels Steensens Vej 6, Gentofte 2820, Denmark. Tel.: +44 420 266; Fax: +45 444 392 03; <email>vkis@novonordisk.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>02</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>07</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009, EMBO and Nature Publishing Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><p> This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence, which permits distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. This licence does not permit commercial exploitation or the creation of derivative works without specific permission.</p><!--author-paid--></license></permissions><abstract><p>The insulin and insulin-like growth factor 1 receptors activate overlapping signalling pathways that are critical for growth, metabolism, survival and longevity. Their mechanism of ligand binding and activation displays complex allosteric properties, which no mathematical model has been able to account for. Modelling these receptors' binding and activation in terms of interactions between the molecular components is problematical due to many unknown biochemical and structural details. Moreover, substantial combinatorial complexity originating from multivalent ligand binding further complicates the problem. On the basis of the available structural and biochemical information, we develop a physically plausible model of the receptor binding and activation, which is based on the concept of a harmonic oscillator. Modelling a network of interactions among all possible receptor intermediaries arising in the context of the model (35, for the insulin receptor) accurately reproduces for the first time all the kinetic properties of the receptor, and provides unique and robust estimates of the kinetic parameters. The harmonic oscillator model may be adaptable for many other dimeric/dimerizing receptor tyrosine kinases, cytokine receptors and G-protein-coupled receptors where ligand crosslinking occurs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>activation mechanism</kwd><kwd>binding kinetics</kwd><kwd>harmonic oscillator model</kwd><kwd>insulin receptor</kwd><kwd>mathematical modelling</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Insulin and insulin-like growth factors (IGF) 1 and 2 have similar structures and exert their action by activating two closely related receptor tyrosine kinases&#x02014;the insulin receptor and the IGF1 type I receptor (IGF1 receptor), which share largely overlapping signalling pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Adams <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">De Meyts and Whittaker, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">De Meyts, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Denley <italic>et al</italic>, 2005</xref>). Despite this similarity, the two hormones produce different responses: mostly metabolic for insulin and mitogenic for IGF1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">Kim and Accili, 2002</xref>). Dysregulation of their signalling may lead to two different life-threatening diseases: type II diabetes and cancer, which are among the largest global health challenges in the world. So far, there is poor understanding of how these hormones produce such different biological effects using similar signalling networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">Kim and Accili, 2002</xref>). It has become clear that a systems biology approach is required to understand the combinatorial nature of signalling specificity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">Shymko <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Kholodenko, 2007</xref>). Insulin analogues with altered kinetic properties show enhanced mitogenic potencies, although they bind to the same insulin receptor; they also cross-react to a variable extent with the IGF-I receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">Shymko <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Kurtzhals <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). Differences in kinetics of ligand binding and receptor activation by the insulin and IGF1 receptors may be one of the factors determining their specificity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">Shymko <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>). The two receptors' mechanism of ligand binding and activation displays complex allosteric properties (i.e. negative cooperativity and ligand dependence of the receptor dissociation rate), which no mathematical model has been able to fully account for (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">Jeffrey, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Kohanski and Lane, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Hammond <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">Wanant and Quon, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">Sedaghat <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). Thus, the development of a reliable mathematical model describing the two receptors' binding kinetics and activation is a critical first step in a systems biology approach to understand the function and specificity of these receptors.</p><p>The insulin and IGF1 receptors exist in the membrane as pre-formed covalent dimers of two identical moieties. Their extracellular domains comprise two leucine-rich repeat-containing large domains (L<sub>1</sub> and L<sub>2</sub>) separated by a cystein-rich (CR) domain, followed by three fibronectin type III (Fn<sub>1&#x02013;3</sub>) domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Adams <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">De Meyts and Whittaker, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">De Meyts, 2004</xref>). A crystal structure of this extracellular (unliganded) insulin receptor dimer has recently been solved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">McKern <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Lawrence <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">Ward <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">2008</xref>). The intracellular portion of the two receptors consists of a kinase domain flanked by regulatory regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Hubbard and Miller, 2007</xref>).</p><p>The insulin and IGF1 receptors exhibit complex binding properties. The Scatchard plots for both receptors are concave up, indicating the presence of high- and low-affinity binding sites and/or negative cooperativity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">De Meyts <italic>et al</italic>, 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">De Meyts, 1994</xref>). The receptors bind only one ligand molecule with high affinity and at least another one with lower affinity. The ligand dissociation rate is dependent on its concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">De Meyts <italic>et al</italic>, 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">De Meyts, 1994</xref>). Furthermore, this dependence is bell-shaped for the insulin receptor, whereas for the IGF1 receptor, it is sigmoid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Christoffersen <italic>et al</italic>, 1994</xref>). When the insulin receptor is in a monomeric form, its affinity is reduced 30-fold, the Scatchard plot becomes linear and the dissociation rate of the ligand becomes independent of its concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">De Meyts, 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">De Meyts and Whittaker, 2002</xref>).</p><p>Insulin has two receptor-binding surfaces on the &#x02018;opposite' sides of the molecule. The first &#x02018;classical' binding surface, also involved in insulin dimerization, was defined in the early 1970s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Pullen <italic>et al</italic>, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">De Meyts <italic>et al</italic>, 1978</xref>), and later validated by alanine-scanning mutagenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Kristensen <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>), whereas the second surface, also involved in insulin hexamerization, was mapped by alanine-scanning mutagenesis more recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">De Meyts, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Gauguin <italic>et al</italic>, 2008</xref>). The dimerization surface interacts with a site located in the L<sub>1</sub> module of the insulin receptor, as well as a 12 amino-acid peptide from the insert in Fn<sub>2</sub>, which combine to form &#x02018;site 1' (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">Wedekind <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">Kurose <italic>et al</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">Williams <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">Mynarcik <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">De Meyts and Whittaker, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">Kristensen <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Huang <italic>et al</italic>, 2004</xref>), whereas the hexamerization surface interacts with a site consisting of residues located in the C-terminal portion of L2 and in the Fn<sub>1</sub> and Fn<sub>2</sub> modules (site 2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Fabry <italic>et al</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">De Meyts and Whittaker, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Hao <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Benyoucef <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">Whittaker <italic>et al</italic>, 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">Sch&#x000e4;ffer (1994)</xref> suggested that the high-affinity binding could result from insulin crosslinking site 1 of one receptor half and site 2 of the other half of the receptor dimer, thus leaving the other two sites free for interaction with the ligand. However, this model had difficulty in explaining the ligand dependence of the ligand dissociation rate. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">De Meyts (1994)</xref> suggested that this problem could be solved by assuming that the four sites of the receptor dimer are arranged in a symmetrical antiparallel way, a postulate that was supported by the recent structure determination of the insulin receptor extracellular domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">McKern <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>). Despite its seeming simplicity, this model turned out to be notoriously difficult for a quantitative analysis and some researchers even concluded that it did not explain the ligand dependence of the dissociation rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Hammond <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>). The problem is that the qualitative crosslinking models suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">Sch&#x000e4;ffer (1994)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">De Meyts (1994)</xref> are not detailed enough from a biochemical and structural viewpoint for mathematical modelling (especially concerning the precise mechanism that leads to receptor crosslinking). The modelling problem is further aggravated by combinatorial complexity arising from multivalent ligand binding to the receptor in multiple possible conformations. We have now solved this problem.</p><p>Here, we present the first mathematical model that accurately reproduces all the kinetic properties of the insulin receptor such as negative cooperativity and the bell-shaped ligand dependence of the receptor dissociation rate. On the basis of the available structural information, we develop a physically plausible model of the receptor activation, which is based on the concept of a harmonic oscillator. We justify thermodynamically that the symmetrically arranged subunits of the insulin receptor dimer experience harmonic oscillatory movements. Analysis of the behaviour of an ensemble of such harmonic oscillators in thermal equilibrium with the surrounding milieu allows to model the receptor activation in a simple way and to substantially reduce the combinatorial complexity. This model is the first one that gives a description of the insulin receptor binding and activation mechanism in terms of interactions between the molecular components and fully takes into account the combinatorial binding complexity (employing 35 insulin receptor intermediaries). Fitting of the model to experimental data provides unique and robust estimates of the kinetic parameters. With a small modification, the model can also be used for the IGF1 receptor. Furthermore, the harmonic oscillator model may be adaptable for many other dimeric or dimerizing receptor tyrosine kinases, cytokine receptors and G-protein-coupled receptors where ligand crosslinking occurs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55">De Meyts, 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Theory and results</title><p>Our goal is to develop a physically plausible mathematical model of the insulin receptor-binding and activation mechanism in terms of interactions between the molecular components. This, however, requires the knowledge of the precise mechanism of interaction between the components involved, for which some biochemical and structural details are still missing. Thus, some assumptions are unavoidable. All of the assumptions made in this article are justified from the physicochemical point of view and are therefore physically plausible.</p><sec disp-level="2"><title>Binding of insulin to the inactive conformation of the insulin receptor</title><p>The structure of the insulin receptor dimer in the unliganded conformation displays a symmetrical antiparallel arrangement of the receptor's two binding sites for insulin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">McKern <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1A and C</xref>). From now on, a pair of sites 1 and 2 from the different receptor subunits will be referred to as a &#x02018;crosslink'. The structure shows that the distance between sites 1 and 2 (within the same crosslink) is rather small (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1B</xref>), indicating that if an insulin molecule binds to either of these sites, there is not enough room for binding of a second insulin molecule. Thus, it is reasonable to assume that only one insulin molecule can bind to the same crosslink (either to site 1 or 2), when the receptor dimer is in the <italic>inactive</italic> conformation. Mathematical modelling of insulin binding to the inactive conformation of the insulin receptor is straightforward and requires only four parameters: association rate constants for sites 1 and 2 (designated <italic>a</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>a</italic><sub>2</sub>, respectively) and dissociation rate constants for sites 1 and 2 (designated <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>, respectively). The four sites will from now on be designated as sites 1, 2, 3 and 4, where sites 3 and 4 are identical to sites 1 and 2, respectively, but from a different crosslink (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2A</xref>). Binding of insulin to the inactive conformation of the insulin receptor gives rise to nine intermediaries, designated <italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>3</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>4</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>13</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>14</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>23</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>24</sub> (where indices <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic> in <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> designate the number of the site to which insulin is bound) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2A</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Conformational change in the insulin receptor upon insulin binding</title><p>Currently, the precise mechanism of the insulin receptor crosslinking reaction required for mathematical modelling is not known. Therefore, we will analyse the available structural information from a physicochemical point of view to derive a plausible model.</p><p>In the absence of insulin, the insulin receptor adopts an inactive, symmetrical conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">McKern <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1A and C</xref>). Binding of insulin to both sites of a crosslink is thought to produce a conformational change in the insulin receptor, which is necessary for its activation. The crystal structure of the insulin receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">McKern <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>) is consistent with an assumption (as previously suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">De Meyts, 1994</xref>) that this conformational change is produced by a tilt of the receptor subunits, leading to a movement of sites 1 and 2 towards each other and to a corresponding movement of sites from the second crosslink away from each other. This structural rearrangement is schematically shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1D and E</xref>, in which the symmetrically arranged subunits of the receptor dimer are approximated by rigid bodies. Obviously, the tilted (activated) conformation has higher free energy than the symmetrical, inactive conformation (otherwise there would be a substantial receptor activation in the absence of insulin), probably due to slight distortion of bond angles and lengths. Thus, it is reasonable to assume that receptor molecules can exist in both inactive and active conformations, with equilibrium being strongly shifted towards the inactive (energetically more favourable) conformation in the absence of the ligand. However, when the ligand is present, it may bind simultaneously to sites 1 and 2 of the same crosslink when the receptor molecules are in the tilted conformation and thus stabilize the active conformation.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Insulin receptor as a harmonic oscillator: a physically plausible model of the receptor conformational change</title><p>As discussed above, the tilted (active) conformation of the insulin receptor has higher free energy compared with the non-tilted (inactive) conformation. It is reasonable to assume that larger tilt angles result in larger free energy values, and that the insulin receptor free energy has a local minimum at the zero tilt angle. Therefore, in a sufficiently small vicinity around the zero tilt angle, the system behaviour can be approximated by harmonic oscillations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Bloch, 1997</xref>). Let us consider the energy of the insulin receptor oscillations when the insulin receptor is in thermal equilibrium with the buffer. Then, the receptor molecules will have various energies (received from accidental collisions with the buffer molecules), and their distribution will be according to the Maxwell&#x02013;Boltzmann formula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Bloch, 1997</xref>), which for a one-dimensional harmonic oscillator takes the form:</p><p><inline-graphic id="illus1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-i1.jpg"/> </p><p>where <italic>P</italic>, <italic>E</italic>, <italic>k</italic> and <italic>T</italic> stand for probability, energy, Boltzmann constant and absolute temperature, respectively. As appears from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A</xref>, the most likely state of the receptor is that with the zero energy of oscillations (corresponding to the zero tilt angle, or an inactive conformation), with the probability density of finding receptor molecules with higher energies decreasing exponentially as a function of energy. The Maxwell&#x02013;Boltzmann distribution implies that a small fraction of receptor molecules will have sufficient energy to reach the tilt angle of the activated receptor in the absence of insulin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A</xref>). This fraction can be easily derived from the Maxwell&#x02013;Boltzmann distribution if the activation energy (designated <italic>E</italic><sub>act</sub>), corresponding to the tilt angle of the activated receptor, is known:</p><p><disp-formula id="illus2"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-i2.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>To estimate the fraction of the activated insulin receptor molecules in the absence of insulin, we note that the insulin receptor basal autophosphorylation rate is increased 10- to 20-fold in the presence of insulin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Flores-Riveros <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Kohanski, 1993</xref>). It is reasonable to assume that the autophosphorylation rate is proportional to the fraction of the activated receptor molecules and that the basal rate is proportional to this fraction in the absence of insulin. Thus, around 5&#x02013;10&#x00025; of the receptor molecules are estimated to be activated in the absence of insulin. From this, the activation energy of the insulin receptor can be roughly estimated from the above equation as 5&#x02013;8 kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Interestingly, the conformational change of the EGF receptor also requires about 4&#x02013;8 kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">Ozcan <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>), indicating that the above estimation is reasonable.</p><p>It should be pointed out that large-scale collective motions in a macromolecule are determined mostly by the macromolecule's global topology and are insensitive to structural details, and that the results obtained by assuming subunits to be rigid bodies connected by elastic springs provide a good description of the allosteric dynamics (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Bahar and Rader, 2005</xref>). From this perspective, the rigid body model of the symmetrical insulin receptor dimer with elastic springs attached as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref> (compare it with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1C</xref>) is expected to provide a decent description of the insulin receptor dynamics. Indeed, such a model will be capable of the conformational changes shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1E</xref> and the movement of its subunits will be described by harmonic oscillations. In the following, this rigid body model of the insulin receptor dimer will serve as a basis for modelling of the crosslinking reaction.</p><sec disp-level="3"><title>Definition of the crosslinking constant</title><p>Let us consider the behaviour of the <italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> intermediary in the absence of insulin. The harmonic oscillator model implies that in the absence of insulin there are no intermediaries with a certain stable tilt angle, although the zero tilt angle is most likely (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A</xref>). The tilt angle will be fluctuating (due to collisions of the solvent molecules with the receptor subunits) until an activation state is achieved, which will only be transient because the oscillation will continue its swing in the reverse direction and quickly lose its energy due to interaction with the solvent. The <italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> receptor molecules with energy of oscillations less than the energy of activation, designated <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> (and therefore in the inactive state), will reach an active state, <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub>, on average after a certain time period, &#x003c4;. Then, transition from <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> to <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> can be modelled as a first-order reaction with a rate constant equal to 1/&#x003c4;, designated from now on as the crosslinking constant, <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A</xref>). As approximately 5&#x00025; of receptor molecules are in the active state (see above), the transition from <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> to <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> can be modelled as a first-order reaction with a rate constant equal to 19 <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Activation of the insulin receptor according to the harmonic oscillator model</title><p>Let us consider the activation of an inactive <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> intermediary (activation of all other inactive intermediaries can be considered in a similar way). The most likely state of this intermediary (with zero energy of oscillations) is designated as <sub>o</sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> and those states with energy of oscillations less than activation energy (including <sub>o</sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub>)&#x02014;as <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>), which represent the <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> receptor species in an inactive state. Subunits of the <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> intermediaries will be experiencing random forces acting on them (shown by vectors <bold><italic>F</italic></bold> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>) due to thermal motion of the solvent molecules. These forces will be varying in magnitude, direction and act for various periods of time. When these forces act synergistically for a sufficient period of time, an active state will be achieved, which (as mentioned above) will happen on average after a time period, &#x003c4;, and transition to the active state, designated as <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x0002b;</sup> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>), from the inactive can be modelled as a first-order reaction with a rate constant, <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub>, equal to 1/&#x003c4;. As in the active state, the distance between insulin and site 2 is zero, the local concentration of insulin in the vicinity of site 2 becomes &#x02018;infinite', which means that the subsequent binding of insulin to site 2, and thus formation of <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub>, is &#x02018;instant' (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>). To discriminate between <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x0002b;</sup> and <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub>, the <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x0002b;</sup> intermediary is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref> with a small distance between insulin and site 2, which can also be interpreted as a snapshot of <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x0002b;</sup> just before it reaches the active state. The <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> intermediary will exist until one of the sites of the crosslink dissociates. Let us assume that it is site 2 that dissociates. This leads to the formation of <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>). Similar to the <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x0002b;</sup> intermediary, <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> is shown with a small distance between site 2 and insulin, which can be interpreted as a snapshot of <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> just after dissociation of site 2. There is an important difference between <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> and <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x0002b;</sup>. The two intermediaries have identical tilt angles, the same kinetic and potential energies of oscillations. But in <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x0002b;</sup> the crosslinking subunits move <italic>towards</italic> each other (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>, the direction of movement is indicated by vectors <bold>&#x003c5;</bold>), meaning that <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> will be formed in an instant, whereas in <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> the crosslinking subunits move <italic>away</italic> from each other (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>), meaning that <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> will not be formed because as soon as <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> loses a small fraction of its energy due to interaction with the solvent, its energy becomes less than energy of activation, and thus by definition it becomes <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub>. Thus, transition from <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> to <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>) can be considered as almost instant.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Reaction scheme for the insulin receptor activation in the harmonic oscillator model</title><p>As can be seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>, formation of <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> from <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> is rate limited by the first reaction (<sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> &#x02192; <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x0002b;</sup>) with a rate constant, <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub>, and dissociation of <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> into <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> is also rate limited by the first reaction (<italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> &#x02192; <sup>&#x0002a;</sup><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>), which is a rate constant for dissociation of site 2 in <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub>, designated <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02032;</sup>. As the concentration of <sub><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></sub><italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> is practically the same as that of <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> (approximately 95&#x00025; of that), the activation scheme shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref> can be reduced to a very simple scheme: <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x021c4;<italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4A</xref>), where the forward reaction has a rate constant equal to <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub>, and the reverse&#x02014;<italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032;. By analogy, formation of <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> from <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub> is described by a similar scheme: <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x021c4;<italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4A</xref>), where the rate constant of the reverse reaction (dissociation of site 1 in <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub>) is designated as <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032;.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Binding of insulin to the crosslinked insulin receptor intermediaries</title><p>The crosslinking reaction leads to the formation of another six crosslinked/activated intermediaries, designated <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>3 &#x000d7; 4</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 23</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 24</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>13 &#x000d7; 4</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>23 &#x000d7; 4</sub> (where sign &#x02018; &#x000d7; ' in 1 &#x000d7; 2 (or 3 &#x000d7; 4) means that insulin crosslinks sites 1 and 2 (or sites 3 and 4) from the inactive intermediaries (<italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>3</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>4</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>13</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>14</sub>, <italic>r</italic><sub>23</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>24</sub>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2B</xref>). Everything described so far for the insulin receptor can also be applied to the IGF1 receptor. Because of the tilt of the insulin receptor subunits in <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub>, the distance between sites 3 and 4 is increased (compared with the inactive conformation) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1D and E</xref>), indicating that the insulin receptor may now bind two more insulin molecules (to sites 3 and 4), in contrast to inactive <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> (which can only bind one more insulin molecule, either to site 3 or 4). Thus, we make an assumption that the insulin receptor can bind up to three insulin molecules, only when it is in the active state. As will be shown later, this assumption leads to a bell-shaped ligand dependence of the dissociation rate. Without this assumption, this dependence becomes sigmoid. Thus, for the IGF1 receptor it will be assumed that a third IGF1 molecule cannot bind to the receptor, which is reasonable because IGF1 is larger in size compared with insulin. In addition, the geometry of the binding sites in the IGF1 receptor is somewhat different from that of the insulin receptor, which could also be the reason why the third IGF1 molecule cannot bind to the receptor. Site 1 is more extensive in the IGF1 receptor complex because in addition to the &#x02018;classical' binding surface binding to L1, the C-peptide of IGF1 (absent in insulin) binds to the CR region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">Keyhanfar <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>). Other structural differences between site 1 of the insulin and IGF1 receptors in the L1 domain are reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Lou <italic>et al</italic> (2006)</xref>. Binding of the third insulin molecule to the insulin receptor leads to two more intermediaries: <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 234</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>123 &#x000d7; 4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2C</xref>). The <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> intermediary will exist until one of the sites of the crosslink dissociates, leading to either <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> (dissociation of site 2) or <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub> (dissociation of site 1), with the corresponding dissociation rate constants, <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032; for site 2, and <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032; for site 1. It is tempting to assume that <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032;=<italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032;=<italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>. This is not necessarily so. For dissociation of insulin from <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> to take place, some energy should be supplied to <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> for breaking the binding of insulin from site 1 (the energy comes from random collisions with the solvent molecules). However, it is obvious that slightly less energy is required when the insulin receptor is in <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> conformation, because this conformation is &#x02018;strained' (in contrast to the &#x02018;relaxed' <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> conformation), and the pull of the &#x02018;strained' receptor subunits contributes to breaking the binding of insulin from site 1. Thus, <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032; is expected to be larger than <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>. Using the same reasoning, <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032; is expected to be larger than <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>. Because the energy of the &#x02018;strained' <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> conformation is expected to be rather small (7.5 kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), one may expect that <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032; (<italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032;) is not much larger than <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> (<italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>). But as it is not possible to predict precisely how much larger, two cases will be considered. In the first, it will be assumed that the increase is insignificant, or <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032;=<italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032;=<italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>. In the second case, there will be no such assumption.</p><sec disp-level="3"><title>Effect of insulin dimerization</title><p>Insulin dimerizes in solution with a <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> value of approximately 7 &#x003bc;M (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">Pekar and Frank, 1972</xref>). After insulin dimerization, only the hexamerization site is available for interaction of the insulin dimer with sites 2 and 4. It is not known whether the insulin dimer can bind to the receptor. However, if we make an assumption that the dimer can bind to the receptor when it is in the active state, then simulations show that this binding is negligible. Thus, we can use our modelling results as evidence that the dimer does not bind to the receptor. However, as it is not possible to predict this result in advance, binding of the dimer is considered in the model. The insulin dimer could potentially bind only to site 2 of <italic>r</italic><sub>3 &#x000d7; 4</sub> and site 4 of <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub>, leading to another two intermediaries <italic>r</italic><sub>2d3 &#x000d7; 4</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 24d</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2C</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Modelling the insulin receptor binding kinetics</title><p>Binding of insulin to the insulin receptor leads to the formation of 19 intermediaries (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>) through a network of 72 individual interactions (if one counts all possible interactions between these 19 intermediaries). The essential features of this network (with 12 intermediaries and 32 interactions) are demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4B</xref>. The complete network is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref> and the corresponding differential equations in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>. It should be noted that the model does not &#x02018;allow' direct dissociation of the crosslinking insulin (binding sites 1 and 2 simultaneously) from <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 234</sub> until one of the insulin molecule dissociates from sites 3 or 4. This is a consequence of the assumption that the third molecule can bind <italic>only</italic> when the receptor is in the active state (see above). This means that as long as the third molecule is bound, the receptor is in the active state (if not, the third molecule would be bound to the receptor in the <italic>inactive</italic> state, contradicting the assumption). If one of the receptor's sites binding to the crosslinking insulin dissociates, the active conformation will still be maintained (as the third insulin molecule is bound). However, as the local concentration of the crosslinking insulin in the vicinity of the dissociated site is &#x02018;infinite' (because the active state is still maintained), the crosslinking insulin is expected to &#x02018;instantly' rebind. Another reason is that the crosslinking insulin could be entrapped between the receptor subunits when the receptor is in the active state (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1B</xref>), and as long as the active state is maintained, insulin may not be able to escape from the binding cavity due to steric hindrances. However, the crosslinking insulin is &#x02018;allowed' to dissociate indirectly, for example, as follows: <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 234</sub> &#x02192; <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 23</sub> &#x02192; <italic>r</italic><sub>13</sub> &#x02192; <italic>r</italic><sub>3</sub> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>), leading to dissociation of the insulin molecule, which was initially crosslinking sites 1 and 2 in <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 234</sub>.</p><p>Modelling the ligand dependence of the receptor dissociation rate requires explicit consideration of the binding of two types of ligand: unlabelled (&#x02018;cold') and radioactively labelled (&#x02018;hot'), which leads to the formation of 77 distinct receptor intermediaries. The number of intermediaries can be reduced to 35 if the initial conditions of the used experimental set-up are imposed. Mathematical modelling of the interactions between these 35 intermediaries (employing a system of the corresponding 35 differential equations) is described in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Modelling the IGF1 receptor binding kinetics</title><p>The IGF1 receptor kinetics can be modelled in essentially the same way as described for the insulin receptor except that (1) the third IGF1 molecule (as justified before) is not &#x02018;allowed' to bind to the receptor and (2) IGF1 does not dimerize (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Brzozowski <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Experimental data used for modelling</title><p>Two sets of data were used for modelling. In the first one (a competition experiment), IM9 and 293 EBN cells were incubated for 2.5 h with hot insulin and 4 h with hot IGF1, respectively, in the presence of various concentrations of the respective cold ligand. Concentration of the hot ligand was 7 pM in both cases. Thereafter, the amount of bound radioactivity was measured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5A and B</xref>). In the second set (quantification of the ligand dependence of the dissociation rate), IM9 and 293 EBN cells were pre-incubated for 2 h with 24 pM hot insulin and IGF1, respectively. Thereafter, the hot ligand was removed and cells were incubated in a 40-fold dilution for various periods of time with various concentrations of the respective cold ligand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">De Meyts <italic>et al</italic>, 1973</xref>). The amount of the remaining pre-bound radioactivity was then measured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5C and D</xref>). To minimize the effect of receptor recycling on the apparent kinetics, the data were obtained at 15&#x000b0;C. The recycling rate at 15&#x000b0;C is expected to be reduced 50- to 100-fold compared with that at 37&#x000b0;C. The reduced rate is still too high to be totally ignored because of long incubation times (up to 4 h). Modelling receptor recycling is described in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Fitting of the insulin receptor model to the experimental data</title><p>Fitting of the insulin receptor kinetics was carried out in Mathematica 5.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">Wolfram Research, 2005</xref>) using a genetic algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Mitchell, 1996</xref>) (with random initial values of all of the parameters) in combination with gradient minimization (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>). The fitting procedure was repeated 25 times (every time with a different set of randomly selected initial parameters) and the average values of the fitted parameters and their standard deviations are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>. As appears from <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>, the genetic algorithm converges to very similar solutions, regardless of the initial choice of parameters, which indicates that all of the used parameters can be identified uniquely. As can be seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5A and C</xref>, there is a very good fit between the simulated and experimental data points for the competition experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5A</xref>) (shown also as a Scatchard plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5A</xref>) and for the ligand dependence of the dissociation rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5C</xref>), which reflects the fact that on average the simulated data points are within &#x000b1;0.53 standard deviations from the experimental data points. If one does not assume that <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032;=<italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032;=<italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>, then the best fit is produced when <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032; and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032; are approximately three times greater than <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>, respectively. However, the fit is improved only marginally, and the values of the other parameters are not changed significantly, which means that for practical purposes the assumption that <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02032;=<italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02032;=<italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub> is reasonable. The <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> values for the two sites are approximately 6.4 and 400 nM. As the experimentally determined <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> for site 1 is approximately 10 nM, and for site 2 in the sub-micromolar range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">Sch&#x000e4;ffer, 1994</xref>), it is reasonable to assign the 6.4 nM <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> to site 1, and the 400 nM <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> to site 2. Crosslinking of sites 1 and 2 leads to an apparent high-affinity binding with a 0.19 nM <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> (determined from the initial slope of the simulated Scatchard plot), which is in good agreement with the experimentally determined value for these cells (approximately 0.2 nM). It is obvious that simulation of insulin binding to the monomeric insulin receptor would result in approximately 34-fold (6.41/0.19) reduction of the apparent affinity (in good agreement with a 30-fold reduction observed experimentally), and the monomeric form would show no ligand dependence for the dissociation rate (also in accordance with the experiments). However, the simulated Scatchard plot of the monomeric receptor would be curvilinear (because sites 1 and 2 have different affinity), whereas the experimental one seems to be linear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">De Meyts, 1994</xref>). It should be noted that site 2 consists of residues located in three insulin receptor domains (L<sub>2</sub>, Fn<sub>1</sub> and Fn<sub>2</sub>) and disruption of the insulin receptor quaternary structure (due to reduction of the covalent S&#x02013;S bonds, necessary for production of the monomeric form) is quite likely to disrupt this site.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Fitting of the IGF1 receptor model to the experimental data</title><p>Initial fitting of the IGF1 receptor kinetics in the same way as for the insulin receptor produced a good data fit, but converged to similar solutions only for the <italic>a</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> parameters (data not shown). It should be noted that the <italic>a</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub> parameters in the insulin receptor fitting are constrained by the upturn of the curve for the ligand dependence of the receptor dissociation rate (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5C</xref>), which happens at insulin concentrations of higher than 100 nM (this corresponds to binding of the third insulin molecule at site 2 with 400 nM <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>). However, this upturn is absent in the curve for the IGF1 receptor (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5D</xref>), and as a result, the site 2 parameters are not constrained sufficiently to produce a unique determination from the binding data alone.</p><p>To estimate the site 2 parameters, we made an assumption that the crosslinking constant, <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub>, of the IGF1 receptor is similar to that of the insulin receptor. The plausibility of this assumption is based on the fact that <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub> depends on the dynamics of the large-scale collective motions in the receptor, which are essentially determined by the macromolecule's global topology and are insensitive to structural details (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Bahar and Rader, 2005</xref>). The structure of the IGF1 receptor dimer has not yet been determined, but the structure of the IGF1 receptor L1-CR-L2 fragment is very similar to the equivalent insulin receptor fragment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Lou <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>). Taking also into account high sequence similarity between the two receptors and the fact that the hybrid insulin&#x02013;IGF1 receptors bind IGF-I with high affinity, there is no doubt that the global topology of the two receptors is very similar. Thus, the assumption that the crosslinking constants of the two receptors are similar is quite reasonable.</p><p>Fitting data with the fixed <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub> parameter (equal to the <italic>k</italic><sub>cr</sub> for the insulin receptor) results in similar solutions regardless of the initial choice of the other parameters (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>) and a good data fit (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5B and D</xref>). The only parameter that is not well defined is <italic>a</italic><sub>2</sub>. Compared with the insulin receptor, the IGF1 receptor appears to have 1.6 higher apparent affinity, but slower association and dissociation kinetics: <italic>a</italic><sub>1</sub> is lower 1.4-fold, <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> is unchanged, <italic>a</italic><sub>2</sub> appears to be lower 3.2-fold (but this result is not very reliable due to a large uncertainty in <italic>a</italic><sub>2</sub>) and <italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub> is lower 2.4-fold. A comparison in the ligand dependence of the receptor dissociation for the insulin and IGF1 receptors, based on the estimated parameter values (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>), is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5E and F</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this article, we present the first mathematical model that accurately reproduces all the kinetic properties of the insulin and IGF1 receptors. In previous models of the insulin receptor binding kinetics (kinetics of the IGF1 receptor has not been modelled before) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Hammond <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">Wanant and Quon, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">Sedaghat <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>), a two-site binding model was used to generate a curvilinear Scatchard plot resembling that of the insulin receptor, but modelling of the ligand dependence of the dissociation rate was not even attempted. Our model is different from the previous ones not only because it is capable of accurately reproducing all the kinetic properties of the insulin and IGF1 receptors but also because it is the first model that gives a physically plausible description of the two receptors' binding and activation in terms of interactions between the molecular components and takes fully into account the combinatorial complexity arising from multivalent binding to multiple receptor conformations.</p><p>The presented mathematical model builds on a structurally and thermodynamically justified assumption that the insulin receptor conformational change (required for the receptor activation) can be described by harmonic oscillations of the receptor subunits. By analysis of the behaviour of an ensemble of the insulin receptor &#x02018;harmonic oscillators' in thermal equilibrium with the surrounding milieu, we developed a physically plausible model of the receptor crosslinking (activation), which allows to model the latter in a simple way, using only one parameter. As description of insulin binding to two different sites requires four parameters, the harmonic oscillator model requires only five parameters. In spite of this, the model gives a very accurate description of the insulin receptor binding kinetics, and with a minor modification&#x02014;of the IGF1 receptor as well.</p><p>The presented model uses a rather complex network of interactions for description of the insulin kinetics. However, now that the parameters have been determined, this network may be reduced substantially depending on the experimental set-up. Simulations show that at physiological concentrations of the two ligands (i.e. lower than 0.1 nM), the kinetic network shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4B</xref> simplifies to a very simple scheme, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>, in which the major route (accounting for 77&#x00025; at equilibrium) is shown by solid lines, and the supplementary (accounting for 23&#x00025;)&#x02014;by dashed lines. If the supplementary route is ignored, the equilibrium level of <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> can be calculated as follows:</p><p><disp-formula id="illus3"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-i3.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>L</italic> is the insulin concentration and <italic>r</italic><sub>tot</sub> is the total receptor level. By comparing this expression with the formula for a single site binding:</p><p> <inline-graphic id="illus4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-i4.jpg"/></p><p> we obtain that the insulin receptor <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> can be calculated from the values of the individual parameters as </p><p><disp-formula id="illus5"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-i5.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>Using the determined parameter values (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>), we obtain from this formula that the insulin receptor <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> can be estimated as 0.186 nM (in good agreement with experiments). The scheme shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref> is also valid for the physiological concentrations of IGF1, and applying the above formula to the estimated IGF1 parameters (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>), the IGF1 receptor <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> can be estimated as 0.114 nM (also in good agreement with experiments).</p><p>Our model represents an essential first step in building a systems biology analysis of the insulin/IGF-I signalling networks to explain the combinatorial nature of their biological specificity. It has been demonstrated previously that mitogenic potencies of insulin analogues with altered kinetic properties correlate well with the analogues' dissociation rate from the receptor: the slower the dissociation, the higher the mitogenic potency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">Shymko <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Kurtzhals <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). In this study, we have shown that IGF1 dissociates from its receptor much slower than insulin (compare dissociations shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5C</xref> with D at physiological concentrations of the two ligands, i.e. below 0.1 nM). The apparent dissociation rates for IGF1 and insulin (in the presence of the two ligands at physiological concentrations) can be estimated from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5C and D</xref> as 0.16 and 0.54 h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively. Thus, IGF1 also complies with the above-mentioned correlation of mitogenicity versus dissociation rate, as IGF1 dissociates slower and it is more mitogenic than insulin. This suggests that kinetic proofreading could be one of the factors determining the signalling specificity of insulin, IGF1 and the insulin analogues (at least as far as mitogenicity is concerned). In the kinetic proofreading model of signalling specificity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">McKeithan, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">Hlavacek <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>), the activated receptor must complete a cascade of reversible modifications before a cellular response can occur. If the ligand dissociates before the full set of modifications is complete, the receptor reverts to its basal unmodified state. Thus, the average lifetime of the receptor in the activated state (which is equal to the reciprocal of the ligand dissociation rate constant) determines whether or not a particular biological response occurs in a signalling cascade that is under a strict kinetic proofreading control. However, application of the kinetic proofreading concept to the insulin/IGF1 signalling appears to be problematic, because the average lifetime of the insulin and IGF1 receptors in the ligand-bound state is approximately 2 and 6 h (calculated from the rate constants estimated above), respectively, whereas all of the insulin/IGF1 receptor effectors require at most 20 min for maximum activation in brown adipocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Kr&#x000fc;ger <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>) and 45 min in white adipocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">Schmelzle <italic>et al</italic>, 2006</xref>), with the majority of the effectors requiring only from 1 to 5 min for the maximum activation.</p><p>However, according to the presented model, the active state is maintained continuously for a much shorter period of time than the ligand-bound state. If we consider an insulin receptor intermediary with one insulin molecule bound (which corresponds to the binding under physiological insulin concentrations), then the insulin receptor molecule is expected to shuttle between the active <italic>r</italic><sub>1 &#x000d7; 2</sub> state and the inactive <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub> states (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>). On the basis of the determined rate constants (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>), it is easy to calculate that the insulin receptor is expected to be continuously in the active state on average for approximately 76 s, whereas the IGF1 receptor for approximately 135 s. Thus, the difference in the average lifetime of the activated states of the two receptors is approximately two-fold. This two-fold difference, as demonstrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">Hlavacek <italic>et al</italic> (2001)</xref>, can result in high signalling specificity depending on the kinetic parameters of a particular signalling pathway. As the majority of the insulin/IGF1 receptor's effectors reach maximum activation with a delay of 1&#x02013;5 min after stimulation with the ligand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Kr&#x000fc;ger <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>), the predicted lifetimes of the active states of the two receptors are sufficiently short to have a potential effect on some of the effectors due to kinetic proofreading. Whether or not a particular effector is under control of kinetic proofreading requires a careful kinetic analysis of the signalling pathway involved, which is not the aim of this study. However, it is interesting to note that activation of the Ras&#x02013;MAP kinase pathway, responsible for the control of cell growth, results in a maximum activation of the ERK1 and ERK2 kinases with a delay of approximately 5 min (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Kr&#x000fc;ger <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>). If we hypothesize that this pathway is under control of kinetic proofreading, and use the 5 min delay as a rough estimate of the time period necessary for activation of the two MAP kinases, then IGF1 is expected to activate this pathway more efficiently than insulin, as the average lifetime of the activated state of the IGF1 receptor is two-fold smaller than the time period required for the MAP kinase activation, whereas in the case of the insulin receptor it is four-fold smaller. The above observation provides a possible explanation for the fact that IGF1 is more mitogenic than insulin, and in general for the correlation between the mitogenicity of insulin analogues and the kinetics of their dissociation. Whether or not it is true requires further investigation.</p><p>The soluble insulin receptor has a 10-fold higher affinity than the receptor expressed in the cell membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">Sch&#x000e4;ffer, 1994</xref>). The reason for this interesting phenomenon has until now been lacking. However, the presented model provides a natural explanation for it. As discussed before, the crosslinking constant depends on the dynamics of the receptor conformational change. As the conformational change is coupled with some movement of the receptor transmembrane subunits in the membrane, the dynamics in solution are expected to be faster due to lower viscosity of the buffer solution (used in the binding experiments) in comparison with the cell membrane. The faster dynamics are expected to result in a larger value for the crosslinking constant, and thus higher affinity. For more discussion of this topic as well as an analysis of the receptor dissociation routes leading to the ligand dependence of the receptor dissociation, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>.</p><p>It should be pointed out that the scope of our model is far from being purely theoretical. It has in fact wide-ranging applications due to its ability to provide robust determination of experimental binding parameters. Thus, we have now evaluated the five constants that define the model for the two alternatively spliced isoforms of the insulin receptor and solved some kinetic issues that had been controversial for many years (Knudsen <italic>et al</italic>, manuscript in preparation). We have shown that the insulin receptor A isoform (lacking exon 11) has 1.5-fold higher affinity and slightly faster apparent association and dissociation kinetics compared with the insulin receptor B isoform (containing exon 11). The differences between the two isoforms appear to be entirely due to the parameters of the site 1: the <italic>a</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> are larger three- and two-fold, respectively, in the A isoform compared with the B-isoform. We have also started a detailed evaluation of the kinetics of binding of a number of &#x02018;supermitogenic' insulin analogues to both insulin receptor isoforms, to determine which parameters correlate with enhanced mitogenicity. This is a critical issue in the molecular toxicology of insulin analogues, which are increasingly replacing regular insulin in the therapy of diabetes mellitus; enhanced mitogenicity <italic>in vitro</italic> of some analogues has been an issue of great concern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Kurtzhals <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">Hansen, 2008</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, we present the first model that allows to explain mathematically all the kinetic properties of the insulin and IGF1 receptors. The model may be adaptable to other RTKs as well as cytokine receptors. Also, there is growing evidence that many receptors of the GPCR family (containing more than 800 members in humans) function as pre-bound dimers, and some of them have been shown to display negative cooperativity in ligand binding similar to that of the insulin receptor/IGF1R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">Springael <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>). The present model may thus be used for modelling not only the insulin and IGF1 receptors' binding but also a large number of other receptors in which ligand crosslinking occurs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="N0x1e03460N0x3515d40" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>1. General remarks 
2. Rule based model of the insulin receptor binding 3. Rule based model of the IGF1 receptor binding 
4. Reaction scheme for the insulin/IGF1 receptor binding 5. Modelling receptor recycling 6. Modelling of the competition experiment 7. Modelling of the ligand dependence of the dissociation rate 8. Fitting of the model to the experimental data 9. Supplementary Discussion 10. Supplementary figures</p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The Hagedorn Research Institute is an independent basic research component of Novo Nordisk A/S. Soetkin Versteyhe and Lisbeth Gauguin were supported by a joint PhD scholarship from the Danish Ministry of Science, Technology and Development, and Novo Nordisk A/S (CORA).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="b1"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Epa</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Structure and function of the type 1 insulin-like growth factor receptor</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1050</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10961344</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b2"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bahar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rader</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Coarse-grained normal mode analysis in structural biology</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16143512</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b3"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Benyoucef</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Surinyia</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hadaschik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siddle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Characterization of insulin/IGF hybrid receptors: contributions of the insulin receptor L2 and Fn1 domains and the alternatively spliced exon 11 sequence to ligand binding and receptor activation</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>403</volume>: <fpage>603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17291192</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b4"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Introduction to Classical and Quantum Harmonic Oscillators</source>. New York: John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Inc.</citation></ref><ref id="b5"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Brzozowski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murshudov</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turkenburg</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Bree</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dauter</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Structural origins of the functional divergence of human insulin-like growth factor-I and insulin</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>9389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12135360</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b6"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Christoffersen</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bornfeldt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rotella</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vissing</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shymko</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>ten Hoeve</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Groffen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heisterkamp</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Negative cooperativity in the insulin-like growth factor-I (IGF-I) receptor and a chimeric IGF-I/insulin receptor</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8013387</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b7"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The structural basis of insulin and insulin-like growth factor-I (IGF-I) receptor binding and negative cooperativity, and its relevance to mitogenic versus metabolic signaling</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <volume>37</volume> <issue>(Suppl 2)</issue>: <fpage>S135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7821729</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b8"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Insulin and its receptor: structure, function and evolution</article-title>. <source>BioEssays</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15551269</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b55"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The insulin receptor: prototype of dimeric, allosteric membrane receptors</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>376</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18640841</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b9"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Site&#x02013;site interactions among insulin receptors: characterization of the negative cooperativity</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>251</volume>: <fpage>1877</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5434</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b10"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neville</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Lesniak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Insulin interactions with its receptors: experimental evidence for negative cooperativity</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Comm</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4361269</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b11"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Obberghen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wollmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandenburg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Mapping of the residues of the receptor binding region of insulin responsible for the negative cooperativity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>273</volume>: <fpage>504</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">661960</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b12"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Structural biology of insulin and IGF1 receptors: implications for drug design</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12360255</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b13"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Denley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Molecular interactions of the IGF system</article-title>. <source>Cytokines Growth Factor Rev</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>439</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b14"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Fabry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kojzo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fahrenholz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandenburg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Detection of a new hormone contact site within the insulin receptor ectodomain by the use of a novel photoreactive insulin</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>8950</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1577732</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b15"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Flores-Riveros</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kastelic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Substrate phosphorylation catalyzed by the insulin receptor tyrosine kinase. Kinetic correlation to autophosphorylation of specific sites in the beta subunit</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>264</volume>: <fpage>21557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2557333</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b16"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gauguin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delaine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alvino</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Alanine scanning of a putative receptor binding surface of insulin-like growth factor-I (IGF-I)</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>20821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18502759</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b54"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Insulin analogues with increased mitogenic potency&#x02014;are they safe?</article-title>. <source>Horm Metab Res</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>3618</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3626</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b17"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a second ligand binding site of the insulin receptor</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source> <volume>347</volume>: <fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16814253</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b18"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tikerpae</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>An evaluation of the cross-linking model for the interaction of insulin with its receptor</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source> <volume>272</volume>: <fpage>E1136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E1144</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b19"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hlavacek</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Redondo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wofsy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Kinetic proofreading models for cell signaling predict ways to escape kinetic proofreading</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>7295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390967</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b20"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theede</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katsoyannis</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>How insulin binds: the B-Chain alpha-helix contacts the L1 beta-helix of the insulin receptor</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>341</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15276842</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b21"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Receptor tyrosine kinases: mechanisms of activation and signaling</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17306972</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b22"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Jeffrey</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>The interaction of insulin with its receptor: crosslinking via insulin association as the source of receptor clustering</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6757028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b23"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Keyhanfar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Precise mapping of an IGF-I binding site on the IGF1-R</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>401</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16981855</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b24"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kholodenko</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Untangling the signalling wires</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17330115</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b25"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Accili</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Signalling through IGF-I and insulin receptors: where is the specificity?</article-title> <source>Growth Horm IGF Res</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12175645</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b26"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kohanski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Insulin receptor autophosphorylation. I. Autophosphorylation kinetics of the native receptor and its cytoplasmic kinase domain</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>5766</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8504095</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b27"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kohanski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Binding of insulin to solubilized insulin-receptor from human placenta&#x02013;&#x02013;evidence for a single class of noninteracting binding sites</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>258</volume>: <fpage>7460</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6345524</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b28"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ostergaard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Functional reconstitution of insulin receptor binding site from non-binding receptor fragments</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>18340</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11901156</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b29"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kjeldsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiberg</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>havelund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Alanine scanning mutagenesis of insulin</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>272</volume>: <fpage>12978</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9148904</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b30"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kratchmarova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blagoev</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Dissection of the insulin signaling pathway via quantitative phosphoproteomics</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>2451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18268350</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b31"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pashmforoush</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshimasa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katsoyannis</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Cross-linking of a B25 azidophenylalanine insulin derivative to the carboxyl-terminal region of the &#x003b1;-subunit of the insulin receptor</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>269</volume>: <fpage>29190</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7961885</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b32"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurtzhals</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>S&#x000f8;rensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jonassen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tr&#x000fc;b</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Correlations of receptor binding and metabolic and mitogenic potencies of insulin analogues designed for clinical use</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>999</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10866053</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b33"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKern</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Insulin receptor structure and its implications for the IGF-1 receptor</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17851071</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b34"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garett</surname><given-names>TPJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKern</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoyne</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Epa</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lovrecz</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frenkel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The first three domains of the insulin receptor differ structurally from the insulin-like growth factor-1 receptor in the regions governing ligand specificity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>12429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16894147</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b35"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>McKeithan</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Kinetic proofreading in T-cell receptor signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>5042</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7761445</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b36"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>McKern</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Streltsov</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lovrecz</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elleman</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>Km</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pilling</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoyne</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cartledge</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sankowich</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stoichevska</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frenkel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name> <etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Structure of the insulin receptor ectodomain reveals a folded-over conformation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>443</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16957736</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b37"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <source>An Introduction to Genetic Algorithms</source>. Cambridge, MA and London, UK: The MIT Press</citation></ref><ref id="b38"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Mynarcik</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Alanine-scanning mutagenesis of a C-terminal ligand binding domain of the insulin receptor &#x003b1; subunit</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>2439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8576204</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b39"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ozcan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lax</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlessinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>On the nature of low- and high-affinity EGF receptors on living cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>5735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16571657</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b40"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Pekar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name> (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Conformation of proinsulin. A comparison of insulin and proinsulin self-association at neutral pH</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>4013</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4673642</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b41"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Pullen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woos</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tickle</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blundell</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wollmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krail</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandenburg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gliemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gammeltoft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Receptor-binding region of insulin</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>259</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">175286</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b42"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>A model for insulin binding to the insulin receptor</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source> <volume>221</volume>: <fpage>1127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8181471</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b44"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Schmelzle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gridley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lienhard</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Temporal dynamics of tyrosine phosphorylation in insulin signaling</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>2171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16873679</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b43"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sedaghat</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A mathematical model of metabolic insulin signaling pathways</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>E1084</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E1101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376338</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b45"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Shymko</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Meyts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Logical analysis of timing-dependent receptor signalling specificity: application to the insulin receptor metabolic and mitogenic signalling pathways</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>326</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9291119</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b46"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Springael</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urizar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Costagliola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vassart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parmentier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Allosteric properties of G protein-coupled receptor oligomers</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>410</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17655934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b47"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Wanant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Insulin receptor binding kinetics: modeling and simulation studies</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source> <volume>205</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882558</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b48"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Streltsov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKern</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lovrecz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Structural insights into ligand-induced activation of the insulin receptor</article-title>. <source>Acta Physiol</source> <volume>192</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b49"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Streltsov</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKern</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The insulin and EGF receptor structures: new insights into ligand-induced receptor activation</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17280834</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b50"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Wedekind</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baer-Pontzen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bala-Mohan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandenburg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Hormone binding site of the insulin receptor: an analysis using photoaffinity-mediated avidin complexing</article-title>. <source>Biol Chem Hoppe Seyler</source> <volume>370</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2540769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b51"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>High-affinity insulin binding: insulin interacts with two ligand binding sites</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>12900</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18991400</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b52"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mynarcik</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Mapping of an NH2-terminal ligand binding site of the insulin receptor by alanine scanning mutagenesis</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7814360</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b53"><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Wolfram Research, Inc</surname></name>. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Mathematica Edition: Version 5.2</source>. Wolfram Research, Inc. Champaign, Illinois, USA</citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Insulin receptor structure. In all of the panels, the individual monomers of the insulin receptor dimer are coloured in green and blue, respectively, and location of the binding sites is shown approximately, as the residues involved in binding to insulin are not known precisely. (<bold>A</bold>) Crystal structure of the ecto-domain of the insulin receptor dimer (PDB code: 2DTG). Labelling of the modules is shown only for the blue-coloured monomer. (<bold>B</bold>) Half of the insulin receptor dimer is shown. The placement of insulin in the binding cavity is shown approximately. (<bold>C</bold>) A view of the insulin receptor dimer (shown in (A)) as seen from the &#x02018;top'. (<bold>D</bold>) Simplified representation of the insulin receptor dimer, in which the insulin-binding subunits are represented as rigid bodies. (<bold>E</bold>) Crosslinked (tilted) conformations of the rigid-body representation of the insulin receptor dimer. Insulin is depicted as a black dot.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Inactive (<bold>A</bold>) and crosslinked (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold>) insulin receptor intermediaries used in the model. S1 and S2 stand for sites 1 and 2, respectively. Insulin is depicted as a black dot.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Harmonic oscillator model of the insulin receptor activation mechanism. (<bold>A</bold>) Plot of the Maxwell&#x02013;Boltzmann distribution for a one-dimensional harmonic oscillator and reaction scheme for the spontaneous receptor activation. The 5&#x00025; fraction of the activated receptor molecules (with energy of oscillations ranging from the activation energy to &#x02018;infinity') is indicated by the hatched region. (<bold>B</bold>) Reaction scheme for the insulin receptor activation. The forces acting to restore the inactive/symmetrical conformation of the receptor subunits are represented by elastic springs, which can be compressed and stretched during movement of the receptor subunits. <italic>E</italic> stands for energy of oscillations, <italic>E</italic><sub>activation</sub>&#x02014;activation energy, <bold><italic>F</italic></bold>&#x02014;random force vector acting on the receptor subunits, <bold>&#x003c5;</bold>&#x02014;vector showing direction of movement of the crosslinking subunits. S1 and S2 stand for sites 1 and 2, respectively. Insulin is depicted as a black dot.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Reaction scheme for the insulin receptor binding. (<bold>A</bold>) Scheme of the crosslinking reaction. (<bold>B</bold>) Simplified scheme of the insulin receptor kinetic network. S1 and S2 stand for sites 1 and 2, respectively. Insulin is depicted as a black dot.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Fitting of the model to the experimental data for the insulin/IGF1 binding. (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>) Competition experiments for the insulin and IGF1 binding, respectively (shown also as Scatchard plots in the insets). (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold>) Percentages of hot insulin and IGF1, respectively, remaining after dissociation for 20 and 60 min in the presence of various concentrations of the respective cold ligand. (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>) Simulation of the ligand dependence of the receptor dissociation for insulin and IGF1, respectively, using the estimated parameter values.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-f5"/></fig><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Scheme of the insulin receptor binding at physiological insulin concentrations.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb200878-f6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Fitted parameter values for the insulin and IGF1 receptor kinetics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Parameters</th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">Insulin kinetics</th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">IGF1 kinetics</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Apparent <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> (nM)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.19&#x000b1;0.005</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.12&#x000b1;0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>K</italic><sub>cr</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.33&#x000b1;0.099</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Site 1 <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> (nM)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">6.41&#x000b1;0.78</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">9.09&#x000b1;0.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Site 2 <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> (nM)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">399&#x000b1;76</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">490&#x000b1;460</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>a</italic><sub>1</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">490 000&#x000b1;26 000</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">347 000&#x000b1;7600</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>d</italic><sub>1</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.0031&#x000b1;0.00031</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.0032&#x000b1;0.000091</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>a</italic><sub>2</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">27 900&#x000b1;12 100</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">8700&#x000b1;8200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>d</italic><sub>2</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.010&#x000b1;0.0024</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.0042&#x000b1;0.00014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Endocytosis rate (&#x00025; per h)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">12.1&#x000b1;3.2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">20.6&#x000b1;0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Exocytosis rate (&#x00025; per h)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">8.3&#x000b1;12.1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.2&#x000b1;0.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-wrap></article>


