<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pnas</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">pnas</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PNAS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0027-8424</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1091-6490</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Academy of Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32616574</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7382213</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">202006520</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2006520117</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>530</subject><subject>1</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Applied Mathematics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><series-title>Inaugural Article</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The challenges of modeling and forecasting the spread of COVID-19</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0396-7391</contrib-id><name><surname>Bertozzi</surname><given-names>Andrea L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>Elisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohler</surname><given-names>George</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>Martin B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>e</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sledge</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>f</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>a</sup>Department of Mathematics, University of California, Los Angeles, <addr-line>CA</addr-line> 90095;</aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>b</sup>Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, University of California, Los Angeles, <addr-line>CA</addr-line> 90095;</aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>c</sup>Department of Bioengineering, University of California, Los Angeles, <addr-line>CA</addr-line> 90095;</aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>d</sup>Department of Computer Science, Indiana University&#x02013;Purdue University Indianapolis, Indianapolis, <addr-line>IN</addr-line> 46202;</aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>e</sup>Department of Mathematics, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, <addr-line>GA</addr-line> 30332;</aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>f</sup>Department of Political Science, University of Texas at Arlington, Arlington, <addr-line>TX</addr-line> 76019</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>1</sup>To whom correspondence may be addressed. Email: <email>bertozzi@ucla.edu</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>This contribution is part of the special series of Inaugural Articles by members of the National Academy of Sciences elected in 2018.</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Contributed by Andrea L. Bertozzi, April 15, 2020 (sent for review April 7, 2020; reviewed by Tapio Schneider, Chad Topaz, and Thomas P. Witelski)</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Author contributions: A.L.B., E.F., G.M., and M.B.S. designed research; A.L.B., E.F., G.M., M.B.S., and D.S. performed research; A.L.B., E.F., G.M., and M.B.S. analyzed data; and A.L.B., E.F., G.M., M.B.S., and D.S. wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Reviewers: T.S., California Institute of Technology; C.T., Williams College; and T.P.W., Duke University.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>21</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>117</volume><issue>29</issue><fpage>16732</fpage><lpage>16738</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 the Author(s). Published by PNAS.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="vor">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This open access article is distributed under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CC BY)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="pnas.202006520.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><title>Significance</title><p>The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has placed epidemic modeling at the forefront of worldwide public policy making. Nonetheless, modeling and forecasting the spread of COVID-19 remain a challenge. Here, we present and detail three regional-scale models for forecasting and assessing the course of the pandemic. This work is intended to demonstrate the utility of parsimonious models for understanding the pandemic and to provide an accessible framework for generating policy-relevant insights into its course. We show how these models can be connected to each other and to time series data for a particular region. Capable of measuring and forecasting the impacts of social distancing, these models highlight the dangers of relaxing nonpharmaceutical public health interventions in the absence of a vaccine or antiviral therapies.</p></abstract><abstract><p>The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has placed epidemic modeling at the forefront of worldwide public policy making. Nonetheless, modeling and forecasting the spread of COVID-19 remains a challenge. Here, we detail three regional-scale models for forecasting and assessing the course of the pandemic. This work demonstrates the utility of parsimonious models for early-time data and provides an accessible framework for generating policy-relevant insights into its course. We show how these models can be connected to each other and to time series data for a particular region. Capable of measuring and forecasting the impacts of social distancing, these models highlight the dangers of relaxing nonpharmaceutical public health interventions in the absence of a vaccine or antiviral therapies.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>pandemic</kwd><kwd>branching process</kwd><kwd>compartmental models</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="gs1"><funding-source id="sp1">National Science Foundation (NSF)<named-content content-type="funder-id">100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">2027438</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Andrea L. Bertozzi</principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient>George Mohler</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="gs2"><funding-source id="sp2">National Science Foundation (NSF)<named-content content-type="funder-id">100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp2">1737770</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Andrea L. Bertozzi</principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient>George Mohler</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="gs3"><funding-source id="sp3">National Science Foundation (NSF)<named-content content-type="funder-id">100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp3">1737585</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Andrea L. Bertozzi</principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient>George Mohler</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="gs4"><funding-source id="sp4">National Science Foundation (NSF)<named-content content-type="funder-id">100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp4">1737996</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Andrea L. Bertozzi</principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient>George Mohler</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="gs5"><funding-source id="sp5">Simons Foundation<named-content content-type="funder-id">100000893</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp5">510776</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Andrea L. Bertozzi</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>access-type</meta-name><meta-value>free</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p content-type="flushleft">The world is in the midst of an ongoing pandemic, caused by the emergence of a novel coronavirus. Pharmaceutical interventions such as vaccination and antiviral drugs are not currently available. Over the next year, addressing the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak will depend critically on the successful implementation of public health measures including social distancing, shelter in place orders, disease surveillance, contact tracing, isolation, and quarantine (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). On 16 March, Imperial College London released a report (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) predicting dire consequences if the United States and the United Kingdom did not swiftly take action against the pandemic. In both nations, governments responded by implementing more stringent social distancing regulations (<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). We now have substantially more case data from the United States, as well as the benefit of analyses performed by scientists and researchers across the world (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Nonetheless, modeling and forecasting the spread of COVID-19 remain a challenge.</p><p>Here, we present three basic models of disease transmission that can be fit to data emerging from local and national governments. While the Imperial College study employed an agent-based method (one that simulates individuals getting sick and recovering through contacts with other individuals in the population), we present three macroscopic models: 1) exponential growth, 2) self-exciting branching process, and 3) the susceptible&#x02013;infected&#x02013;resistant (SIR) compartment model. These models have been chosen for their simplicity, minimal number of parameters, and for their ability to describe regional-scale aspects of the pandemic. In presenting these models, we demonstrate how they are connected and note that in different cases one model may fit better than another. Because these models are parsimonious, they are particularly well suited to isolating key features of the pandemic and to developing policy-relevant insights. We order them according to their usefulness at different stages of the pandemic&#x02014;exponential growth for the initial stage, a self-exciting branching process when one is still analyzing individual count data going into the development of the pandemic, and a macroscopic mean-field model going into the peak of the disease. The branching process can also track changes over time in the dynamic reproductive number.</p><p>These models highlight the significance of fully implemented and sustained social distancing measures. Put in place at an early stage, distancing measures that reduce the virus&#x02019;s reproduction number&#x02014;the expected number of individuals who an infected person will spread the disease to&#x02014;may allow much-needed time for the development of pharmaceutical interventions. By slowing the speed of transmission, such measures may also reduce the strain on health care systems and allow for higher-quality treatment for those who become infected. Importantly, the economic consequences of such measures may lead political leaders to consider relaxing them. The models presented here, however, demonstrate that relaxing these measures in the absence of pharmaceutical interventions may allow the pandemic to reemerge. Where this takes place, social distancing efforts that appear to have succeeded in the short term will have little impact on the total number of infections expected over the course of the pandemic.</p><p>The epidemiological perspective on modeling infectious disease spread involves consideration of a larger number of modeling parameters detailing the spread of and recovery from the disease, additional compartments corresponding to age categories, and other related choices (e.g., refs. <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). A data-driven approach to modeling COVID-19 has also emerged, in which statistical and machine learning models are used for forecasting cases, hospitalizations, deaths, and impacts of social distancing (<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Our work demonstrates the utility of parsimonious epidemic models for understanding the pandemic and provides an accessible framework for a larger group of quantitative scientists to follow and forecast the COVID-19 pandemic. It includes explanations that will help allow scientific researchers to develop insights that may contribute to public health policy making, including contributing to public health forecasting teams. Importantly, the branching process model that we detail is relatively new and underutilized in epidemiology. It provides a method for quantitatively estimating dynamic reproduction numbers, which can be critical in assessing the impact of distancing measures over time. The results from the parsimonious models presented here are consistent with recent analyses from public health officials in California (<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and with the original Imperial College model (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>We present examples of forecasts for viral transmission in the United States. Where other studies have typically developed and presented one model (choosing to fit parameters within the chosen model), our analysis compares three different forecasting models using a fitting criterion. The results of these models differ depending on whether the data employed cover confirmed cases or mortality. In addition, many aspects of disease spread, such as incubation periods, fraction of asymptomatic but contagious individuals, seasonal effects, and the time between severe illness and death, are not considered here. In some cases (e.g., seasonal), relevant data do not exist, and in other cases (e.g., age of patients), we choose not to include additional parameters in favor of parsimony.</p><sec sec-type="results" id="s1"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2"><title>A. Exponential Growth.</title><p>Epidemics naturally exhibit exponential behavior in the early stages of an outbreak, when the number of infections is already substantial but recoveries and deaths are still negligible. If at a given time <inline-formula><mml:math id="i1"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> there are <inline-formula><mml:math id="i2"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> infected individuals and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i3"><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the rate constant at which they infect others, then at early times (neglecting recovered individuals), <inline-formula><mml:math id="i4"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>. The time it takes to double the number of cumulative infections (doubling time) is a common measure of how fast the contagion spreads: if we start with <inline-formula><mml:math id="i5"><mml:mi>&#x0012a;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> infections, then at time <inline-formula><mml:math id="i6"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> we achieve <inline-formula><mml:math id="i7"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x0012a;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> infections. For the COVID-19 outbreak, exponential growth is seen in data from multiple countries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>), with remarkably similar doubling times in the early stages of the epidemic. For COVID-19, we expect an exponential growth phase during the first 15 to 20 d of the outbreak in the absence of public health interventions such as social distancing, isolation, or quarantine. This estimate is based on patient data from the Wuhan outbreak, which indicate that the average time from illness onset to death or discharge is between 17 and 21 d for hospitalized patients (<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Because deaths are a fraction of infections, they initially increase at a similar exponential pace, with some delay relative to the beginning of the outbreak. These observed doubling time estimates (2 to 4 d) are significantly smaller than early estimates (<inline-formula><mml:math id="i8"><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>7 d) obtained using data collected in Wuhan (<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><fig id="fig01" fig-type="featured" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>(<italic>Upper</italic>) Exponential model applied to new infection and death data for Italy, Germany, France, Spain, the United Kingdom, and the United States, normalized by the total country population (<xref rid="r54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). <italic>Insets</italic> show the same data on a logarithmic scale. Both the normalized infection <inline-formula><mml:math id="i9"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and death <inline-formula><mml:math id="i10"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> data were thresholded to comparable initial conditions for each country; fits are to the first 15 to 20 d of the epidemic after exceeding the threshold. The fitted doubling time is shown for both infections (<inline-formula><mml:math id="i11"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) and death (<inline-formula><mml:math id="i12"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) data. Data from Japan and South Korea are shown for comparison. (<italic>Lower</italic>) Dynamic reproduction number (mean and 95% CI) of COVID-19 for China, Italy, and the United States estimated from reported deaths (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) using a nonparametric branching process (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Current estimates are as of 1 April 2020 of the reproduction number in New York (NY), California (CA), and Indiana (IN; confirmed cases used instead of mortality for Indiana). Reproduction numbers of COVID-19 vary in different studies and regions of the world (in addition to over time) but have generally been found to be between 1.5 and 6 (<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) prior to social distancing.</p></caption><graphic id="gra1" xlink:href="pnas.2006520117fig01"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3"><title>B. Self-Exciting Branching Process.</title><p>A branching point process (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) can also model the rate of infections over time. Point process models are data driven and allow for parametric or nonparametric estimation of the reproduction number and transmission timescale. They also facilitate estimation of the probability of extinction at early stages of an epidemic. These models have been used for various social interactions including spread of Ebola (<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), retaliatory gang crimes (<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), and email traffic (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The intensity (rate) of infections can be modeled as<disp-formula id="eq1"><mml:math id="me1"><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo largeop="true" movablelimits="false" symmetric="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><label>[1]</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="i13"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the current time and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i14"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are the times of previous infection incidents. Here, the dimensionless reproduction number, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i15"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, evolves in time (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) to reflect changes in disease reproduction in response to public health interventions (e.g., school closings, social distancing, closures of nonessential businesses, isolation, and quarantine). The distribution of interevent times <inline-formula><mml:math id="i16"><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a gamma or Weibull distribution (<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) with shape parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="i17"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and scale parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="i18"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Finally, the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="i19"><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> allows for exogenous infection cases. The point process in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1">Eq. <bold>1</bold></xref> is an approximation to the common SIR model of infectious diseases (described later) during the initial phase of an epidemic when the total number of infections is small compared with the overall population size (<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).</p><p>Given <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1">Eq. <bold>1</bold></xref>, the quantity<disp-formula id="eq2"><mml:math id="me2"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>[2]</label></disp-formula>gives the probability of secondary infection <inline-formula><mml:math id="i20"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> having been caused by primary infection <inline-formula><mml:math id="i21"><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The dynamic reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="i22"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can then be estimated via expectation&#x02013;maximization (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) using a histogram estimator:<disp-formula id="eq3"><mml:math id="me3"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo largeop="true" movablelimits="false" symmetric="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math><label>[3]</label></disp-formula>Here, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i23"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are intervals discretizing time, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i24"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of such intervals. The reproduction number, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i25"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, in each interval <inline-formula><mml:math id="i26"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is determined by<disp-formula id="eq4"><mml:math id="me4"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo largeop="true" movablelimits="false" symmetric="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><label>[4]</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="i27"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of events in interval <inline-formula><mml:math id="i28"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>, <italic>Lower</italic> shows the estimated dynamic reproduction number (<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) of COVID-19 in China, Italy, and the United States during the early stage of the pandemic, from late January 2020 to early April 2020. The branching point process is fit to mortality data (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) using an expectation&#x02013;maximization algorithm (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Public health measures undertaken in China appear to have reduced <inline-formula><mml:math id="i29"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to below the self-sustaining level of <inline-formula><mml:math id="i30"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> by the middle of February. In Italy, public health measures brought the local value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="i31"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> down; as of early April, however, it remained above <inline-formula><mml:math id="i32"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. The estimated reproduction number in the United States as a whole stood at around 2.5. The reproduction number, however, varies notably by location.</p><p>This model can be adapted to capture the long-term evolution of the pandemic by incorporating a prefactor that accounts for the dynamic decrease in the number of susceptible individuals (<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>):<disp-formula id="eq5"><mml:math id="me5"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo largeop="true" movablelimits="false" symmetric="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math><label>[5]</label></disp-formula>Here, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i33"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the cumulative number of infections that have occurred up to time <inline-formula><mml:math id="i34"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i35"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total population size. This version of the branching process model, referred to as HawkesN, represents a stochastic version of the SIR model; with large <inline-formula><mml:math id="i36"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, the results of HawkesN are essentially deterministic. When projecting, we use our estimated <inline-formula><mml:math id="i37"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at the last known point for all times going forward. Since the <inline-formula><mml:math id="i38"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> term is the number of infections, if our estimates for <inline-formula><mml:math id="i39"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are based on mortality numbers, we must also choose a mortality rate to interpolate between the two counts; although existing estimated rates vary significantly, we choose 1% as a plausible baseline (<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) (discussion in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s6"><italic>Materials and Methods</italic></xref>). Alternatively, we also create forecasts for three US states based on fits to reported case data (<xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Model Fits to Early Time Data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="pnas.2006520117fx01.jpg"/></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>(<italic>Left</italic>) Fit of confirmed case (conf.) or mortality (mort.) data from California (CA), Indiana (IN), and New York (NY) states to three different models (SIR, SEIR, and branching process) using Poisson regression. The table shows the log likelihood and the relative likelihood exp(<inline-formula><mml:math id="i40"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) based on the Akaike information criteria (AIC) (<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). The blue lettering corresponds to the lowest AIC value. The branching process parameters include a Weibull shape <inline-formula><mml:math id="i41"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and scale <inline-formula><mml:math id="i42"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><mml:math id="i43"><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, along with the exogenous rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="i44"><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The table also shows parameters from the fit and the projected date for the peak in new cases for each of these datasets; the projected peak date for the branching process is made using the HawkesN model. For each state, we run the fit on both confirmed case data and mortality data, taken from ref. <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>. (<italic>Right</italic>) Shown are the actual data points compared with the fitted curves.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4"><title>C. Compartmental Models.</title><p>The SIR model (<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref><xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) describes a classic &#x0201c;compartmental&#x0201d; model with SIR population groups. A related model, susceptible&#x02013;exposed&#x02013;infected&#x02013;resistant (SEIR), includes an &#x0201c;exposed&#x0201d; compartment that models a delay between exposure and infectiousness. The SEIR model was shown to fit historical death record data from the 1918 influenza epidemic (<xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), during which governments implemented extensive social distancing measures, including bans on public events, school closures, and quarantine and isolation measures. The SIR model can be fit to the predictions made in ref. <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> for agent-based simulations of the United States. The SIR model assumes a population of size <inline-formula><mml:math id="i45"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="i46"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of susceptible individuals, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i47"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of infected individuals, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i48"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of resistant individuals. For simplicity of modeling, we view deaths as a subset of resistant individuals, and deaths can be estimated from the dynamics of <inline-formula><mml:math id="i49"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>; this is reasonable for a disease with a relatively small death rate. We also assume a timescale short enough such that humans&#x02019; natural resistance to the disease does not introduce new susceptible people after recovery.</p><p>The SIR model equations are<disp-formula id="eq6"><mml:math id="me6"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02003;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02003;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math><label>[6]</label></disp-formula>Here, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i50"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the transmission rate constant, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i51"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the recovery rate constant, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i52"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the reproduction number. One integrates <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq6">Eq. <bold>6</bold></xref> forward in time from initial values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="i53"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i54"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i55"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> at time 0. The SEIR model includes an exposed category <inline-formula><mml:math id="i56"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="uneq1"><mml:math id="me7"><mml:mtable columnalign="left" class="align-star"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02003;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02003;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Here, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i57"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the inverse of the average incubation time. Both models are fit, using maximum likelihood estimation with a Poisson likelihood, to data for three US states (California, New York, and Indiana) (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> compares the results with the branching process. We use the relative likelihood based upon the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) (<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) to measure model performance for each dataset; AIC is biased against models with more parameters. The SEIR model performs better on the confirmed data for California and Indiana, possibly due to the larger amount of data, compared with mortality for which SIR is the best for all three states. The branching process performs best for confirmed cases in New York. Our choice of fitting follows the method in ref. <xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> for the 1918 pandemic death data. Our focus is on model comparison rather than measuring uncertainty of parameters in a specific model, as is currently being done for hospital demand forecasts in Los Angeles (<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). For interval forecasts with uncertainty quantification, one may consider a negative binomial alternative to Poisson regression that captures overdispersion in case and death counts (<xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>).</p><p>We can further understand the role of parameters in our models via a dimensionless formulation of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq6">Eq. <bold>6</bold></xref>. There are two timescales dictated by <inline-formula><mml:math id="i58"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i59"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Therefore, if time is rescaled by <inline-formula><mml:math id="i60"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="i61"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i62"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i63"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i64"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> represent fractions of the population in each compartment, then in the case of a novel outbreak with no initially resistant individuals, we obtain<disp-formula id="eq7"><mml:math id="me8"><mml:mtable columnalign="left" class="align"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><label>[7]</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="i65"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> is the initial fraction of the infected population at the start time, and the system retains only one dimensionless parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="i66"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> that, in conjunction with the initial conditions, completely determines the resulting behavior. For <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq7">Eq. <bold>7</bold></xref>, the shapes of the solution curves <inline-formula><mml:math id="i67"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> do not depend on <inline-formula><mml:math id="i68"><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, other than exhibiting a time shift that depends logarithmically on <inline-formula><mml:math id="i69"><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>). This is a universal solution for the SIR model in the limit of small <inline-formula><mml:math id="i70"><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>), depending only on <inline-formula><mml:math id="i71"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Critically, the height of the peak in <inline-formula><mml:math id="i72"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the total number of resistant/susceptible people by the end of the epidemic are determined by <inline-formula><mml:math id="i73"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> alone. However, the sensitivity of the time translation to the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="i74"><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and the dependence of true time values of the peak on parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="i75"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> make SIR challenging to fit to data at the early stages of an epidemic when Poisson statistics and missing information are prevalent. When using early-time death data to fit SIR, the estimate of the percentage of deaths per total number of infections (chosen as 1% here) has a sensitivity that can be understood directly in terms of this shift in the time to peak. This is important information for public health officials, policy makers, and for political leaders interested in decreasing <inline-formula><mml:math id="i76"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> for substantial periods of time. This sensitivity to parameters helps explain why projections of the outbreak can display such large variability and highlights the need for extensive disease testing within the population to more accurately track the epidemic curve. After the surge in infections, the model asymptotes to an end state in which <inline-formula><mml:math id="i77"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> approaches the end value <inline-formula><mml:math id="i78"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i79"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> approaches <inline-formula><mml:math id="i80"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and the infected population approaches 0. The value <inline-formula><mml:math id="i81"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> satisfies a well-known transcendental equation (<xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref><xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). A phase diagram of the universal solutions for several <inline-formula><mml:math id="i82"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> values is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>, <italic>Upper Right</italic>. The dynamics start in the bottom right corner where <inline-formula><mml:math id="i83"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is almost 1 and follow the colored line to terminate on the <inline-formula><mml:math id="i84"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> axis at the value <inline-formula><mml:math id="i85"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. A rigorous derivation of the limiting state under the assumptions here can be found in refs. <xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref><xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>.</p><fig id="fig02" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Solution of the dimensionless SIR model (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="i86"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. <italic>Upper Left</italic> shows the graphs of <inline-formula><mml:math id="i87"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (blue), <inline-formula><mml:math id="i88"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (orange), and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i89"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (gray) on the vertical axis vs. <inline-formula><mml:math id="i90"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> on the horizontal axis, for different <inline-formula><mml:math id="i91"><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The corresponding values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="i92"><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> from left to right are <inline-formula><mml:math id="i93"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i94"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i95"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i96"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively. <italic>Upper Center</italic> shows the time until peak infections vs. <inline-formula><mml:math id="i97"><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the values shown in <italic>Upper Left</italic>. This asymptotic tail to the left makes it challenging to fit data to SIR in the early stages. <italic>Upper Right</italic> is a phase diagram for fraction of infected vs. fraction of susceptible with the direction of increasing <inline-formula><mml:math id="i98"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> indicated by arrows, for three different values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="i99"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. <italic>Lower</italic> displays a typical set of SIR solution curves over the course of an epidemic, with important quantities labeled.</p></caption><graphic id="gra2" xlink:href="pnas.2006520117fig02"/></fig><fig id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Scenarios for the impact of short-term social distancing: fraction of population vs. date. (<italic>Left</italic>) California SIR model based on mortality data with parameters from <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="i100"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.7</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i101"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i102"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) under two scenarios: <inline-formula><mml:math id="i103"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> constant in time (light blue) and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i104"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> cut in half from 27 March (1 wk from the start of the California shutdown) to 5 May but then returned to its original value, to represent a short-term distancing strategy (dark blue). (<italic>Right</italic>) New York SIR model with parameters from <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="i105"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4.1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i106"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i107"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>05</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) under the same two scenarios but with short-term distancing occurring over the dates of 30 March (1 wk from the start of the New York shutdown) to 5 May. In both states, the distancing measures suppress the curve and push the peak infected date into the future, but the total number of cases is only slightly reduced.</p></caption><graphic id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.2006520117fig03"/></fig><p>Under the SIR (and similar) model(s), if <inline-formula><mml:math id="i108"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is decreased during the middle of an outbreak, through social distancing and other public health measures, the rate of new infections will decrease. However, unless the number of infected individuals is brought down to zero, the outbreak will likely reemerge, and the total number of infections may still be a large fraction of the population. This is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>, where we present scenarios of no social distancing vs. short-term social distancing with parameters from <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for death data up through the end of March, fit to the SIR model. We caution that the goal of these scenarios is not to produce highly accurate percentages but rather, to present scenarios under different basic assumptions that illustrate the usefulness of social distancing measures and the potential danger in easing them too soon.</p><p>For the New York state scenario, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="i109"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> presumed to decrease by a factor of two with distancing measures, the outbreak is not completely controlled by distancing, and the number of infections continues to rise to approximately 10% by mid-April. In contrast, without distancing measures the scenario shows four times that number of infected individuals by mid-April, a level that would have represented a potentially disastrous strain on the hospital system. In the California scenario, distancing measures bring the effective <inline-formula><mml:math id="i110"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> closer to one, thus keeping infections at a much smaller portion of the population than the scenario with no social distancing, at least during the period when the distancing is still in effect. We take these scenarios one step further by suddenly stopping distancing on 5 May (this is both extreme and hypothetical, but it serves to illustrate the model). Because of the low initial infected count in California, bringing <inline-formula><mml:math id="i111"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> back to the original predistancing level produces a curve that follows the original peak scenario, just shifted later in time. For New York state, because a nontrivial fraction of the population is initially infected, there are fewer to infect, and the new peak is less steep than the scenario without any distancing.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s5"><title>Discussion</title><p content-type="flushleft">Our analysis, employing parsimonious models, illustrates several key points. 1) The reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="i112"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is highly variable both over time and by location, and this variability is compounded by distancing measures. These variations can be calculated using a stochastic model, and lower <inline-formula><mml:math id="i113"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is critical to decreasing strains on health care systems and to creating time to develop effective vaccines and antiviral therapies. 2) Mortality data and confirmed case data have statistics that vary by location and by time depending on testing and on accurate accounting of deaths due to the disease. Differences in collection methods and in the accuracy of morbidity and mortality data can lead to different projected outcomes. 3) Nonpharmaceutical public health interventions (NPIs) such as social distancing and shelter in place orders offer an important means of reducing the virus&#x02019;s reproduction number. Nonetheless, NPIs may not have a substantial impact on the total number of infections unless sustained over time. Policy makers should be cautious about scaling back distancing measures after early signs of effectiveness.</p><p>During the 1918 influenza pandemic, the early relaxation of social distancing measures led to a swift uptick in deaths in some US cities (<xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The models presented here help to explain why this effect might occur, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>. Already, policy makers in many jurisdictions have started to implement new social protocols that allow for increased economic activity. In the United States, where public health authority is vested largely in states and localities, key decisions about such measures will be in the hands of local officials, with national agencies such as the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention playing a coordinating role and offering guidance (<xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Nationally, policy makers may also consider funding mechanisms and regulatory measures that might facilitate a more unified approach to the pandemic (<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), as well as fiscal measures aimed at ameliorating the economic effects of social distancing and shelter in place orders.</p><p>Of the models presented here, only the point process model tracks the reproductive number changing over time (although compartmental models can be modified to do the same). Dynamic change in the reproductive number is the major challenge in forecasting such a pandemic. Some new approaches to forecasting long-term trends in the COVID-19 pandemic attempt to address this concern by fitting curves in countries in the later stages of spread (after social distancing) and then applying those fitted models to regions in earlier stages (<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The long-term SIR curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref> are idealized counterfactuals in the event of no social distancing, rather than forecasts of the actual peak date and total infected. Moreover, in the absence of distancing policies, people may still choose to distance out of fear driven by an upswing in recent deaths, as was modeled in ref. <xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> in the 1918 pandemic.</p><p>The models presented here are parsimonious, making a variety of assumptions in order to increase understanding and to avoid overfitting the limited and incomplete data available; more complex models have been introduced and are currently in use (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Even with these simple models, however, the parameters obtained from our fits (<xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) can vary significantly for a given location. Although we have in each case determined which of these fits appears to have most validity, in many cases these are not strong indicators. These models have several sources of uncertainty, including parameter uncertainty, variation based on data or model type used, and most importantly, uncertainty in the severity and length of social distancing measures, which can change the peak date by months or even create multiple peaks. This variability in outcomes highlights the challenges of modeling and forecasting the course of a pandemic during its early stages and with only limited data. This uncertainty is a major challenge for policy makers, who must consider the social and economic consequences of disruptive public health interventions while recognizing that relaxing them may swiftly lead to the reemergence of a devastating disease.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s6"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s7"><title>Relation between the Exponential Model and Compartment Models.</title><p>The exponential model is appropriate during the first stages of the outbreak, when recoveries and deaths are negligible: in this case, the SIR compartment model can be directly reduced to an exponential model. If we assume <inline-formula><mml:math id="i114"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq6">Eq. <bold>6</bold></xref>, then <inline-formula><mml:math id="i115"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, with the exponential solution <inline-formula><mml:math id="i116"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="i117"><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i118"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> the initial number of infections. We expect at very early times <inline-formula><mml:math id="i119"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> that the recovery will lag infections so one might see <inline-formula><mml:math id="i120"><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> at very early times and then reduce to <inline-formula><mml:math id="i121"><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> after <inline-formula><mml:math id="i122"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Reports and graphs disseminated by the media typically report cumulative infections, which include recoveries and deaths. Using the SIR model, the total cumulative infections are <inline-formula><mml:math id="i123"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and evolve as <inline-formula><mml:math id="i124"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Integrating this, we see that <inline-formula><mml:math id="i125"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> likewise grows exponentially with the same rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="i126"><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. An important observation is that the doubling time for cumulative infections [<inline-formula><mml:math id="i127"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>] will change during the early times, with a shorter doubling time when <inline-formula><mml:math id="i128"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and a longer doubling time when <inline-formula><mml:math id="i129"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Relation between the HawkesN and SIR Models.</title><p>Following refs. <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> and <xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, first a stochastic SIR model can be defined where a counting process <inline-formula><mml:math id="i130"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> tracks the total number of infections up to time <inline-formula><mml:math id="i131"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i132"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the population size, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i133"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of susceptible individuals. The process satisfies<disp-formula id="uneq2"><mml:math id="me9"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="uneq3"><mml:math id="me10"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>which then gives the rate of new infections and new recoveries as (<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)<disp-formula id="uneq4"><mml:math id="me11"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02003;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>It is shown in ref. <xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> that the continuum limit of the counting process approaches the solution to the SIR model in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq6">Eq. <bold>6</bold></xref>. Furthermore, for an exponential kernel <inline-formula><mml:math id="i134"><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the HawkesN model in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq5">Eq. <bold>5</bold></xref> with parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="i135"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and constant reproduction number (<inline-formula><mml:math id="i136"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>), then <inline-formula><mml:math id="i137"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="i138"><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i139"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (ref. <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> has further details).</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Fitting the SIR, SEIR, and Branching Process Models.</title><p>The parameters for SIR and SEIR in <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> were found using maximum Poisson likelihood regression (as in ref. <xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> for death data from the 1918 pandemic in US cities) via grid search with ranges <inline-formula><mml:math id="i140"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>005</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i141"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="i142"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>01</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="i143"><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>01</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>The branching process was fit using a nonparametric expectation maximization algorithm, the details of which can be found in ref. <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>. Models were fit to empirical new infections per day or new mortality counts per day. We assumed that 1% of those labeled as resistant in the simulations were fatal cases. For morality rates in the range of 0.3 to 3%, the peak date changes by up to 2 wk. Data quality is an issue during the COVID-19 pandemic due to lack of uniform testing. Uncertainty in estimates of the total number infected leads to uncertainty in forecasting results. The likelihood is somewhat flat at the maximum for models in <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, with multiple parameter combinations yielding plausible fits. Fitting SIR type models is known to be challenging due to parameter identifiability issues (<xref rid="r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). However, the peak date only varies by 1 to 3 d for parameters within two units of the maximum log likelihood.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Data Sources</title><p content-type="flushleft">The data used in this manuscript were downloaded on 1 April 2020 from ref. <xref rid="r54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>, <italic>Upper</italic>, 16 June 2020 from ref. <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>, <italic>Lower</italic>, and on 2 April 2020 from ref. <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> for <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Data from both refs. <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> and <xref rid="r54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> are publicly available. Case and death counts for COVID-19, such as those reported in ref. <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> that are used in the present study, are well known to suffer from ascertainment issues (<xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). The data also have other sources of error due to the nature in which they are aggregated from primary sources, where reporting is often lagged. Policy decisions based upon models fit to these data must take these ascertainment and data quality issues into account. The code and data used to generate <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>, <italic>Upper</italic> can be downloaded from GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/francoelisa/PNAS2020" xlink:show="new">https://github.com/francoelisa/PNAS2020</ext-link>. The code to download data and generate <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>, <italic>Lower</italic> can be downloaded from GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/gomohler/pnas2020/tree/master/dynamic_R" xlink:show="new">https://github.com/gomohler/pnas2020/tree/master/dynamic_R</ext-link>. The code to generate <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> is available in GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/gomohler/pnas2020" xlink:show="new">https://github.com/gomohler/pnas2020</ext-link>.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Mark Lewis and Mason Porter for helpful comments on early drafts of the manuscript. We also thank Mark Lewis and Ron Brookmeyer for expert advice from the mathematical biology and epidemiology perspectives, respectively. This research was supported by NSF Grants DMS-2027438, DMS-1737770, SCC-1737585, and ATD-1737996 and Simons Foundation Math + X Investigator Award 510776.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no competing interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Data deposition: The code and data used to generate <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>, <italic>Upper</italic> can be downloaded from GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/francoelisa/PNAS2020" xlink:show="new">https://github.com/francoelisa/PNAS2020</ext-link>. The code to download data and generate <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>, <italic>Lower</italic> can be downloaded from GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/gomohler/pnas2020/tree/master/dynamic_R" xlink:show="new">https://github.com/gomohler/pnas2020/tree/master/dynamic_R</ext-link>. The code to generate <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> is available in GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/gomohler/pnas2020" xlink:show="new">https://github.com/gomohler/pnas2020</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gostin</surname><given-names>L. O.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>The novel coronavirus originating in Wuhan, China: Challenges for global health governance</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<volume>323</volume>, <fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>710</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Association of public health interventions with the Epidemiology of the COVID-19 outbreak in Wuhan, China</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<volume>323</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <comment>&#x0201c;Impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) to reduce COVID-19 mortality and healthcare demand&#x0201d; (Report 9, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom, 2020; </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25561/77482</pub-id><comment>)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <comment>Behind the virus report that jarred the U.S. and the U.K. to action. <italic>NY Times</italic>, 17 March 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/17/world/europe/coronavirus-imperial-college-johnson.html" xlink:show="new">https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/17/world/europe/coronavirus-imperial-college-johnson.html</ext-link>. Accessed 24 March 2020</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <comment>&#x0201c;Transmissibility of 2019-nCoV&#x0201d; (Report 3, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom, 2020; </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25561/77148</pub-id><comment>)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>, <comment>Simulating the spread of epidemics in China on the multi-layer transportation network: Beyond the coronavirus in Wuhan. arXiv:2002.12280 (27 February 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Althaus</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Pattern of early human-to-human transmission of Wuhan 2019-NCOV</article-title>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.01.23.917351</pub-id><comment> (24 January 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Estimating unobserved SARS-CoV-2 infections in the United States</article-title>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.15.20036582</pub-id><comment> (26 March 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kucharski</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Early dynamics of transmission and control of COVID-19: A mathematical modelling study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>558</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32171059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tindale</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Transmission interval estimates suggest pre-symptomatic spread of COVID-19</article-title>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.03.20029983</pub-id><comment> (6 March 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellewell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Feasibility of controlling COVID-19 outbreaks by isolation of cases and contacts</article-title>. <source>Lancet Global Health</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>488</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>496</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>P. G. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Nowcasting and forecasting the potential domestic and international spread of the 2019-nCoV outbreak originating in Wuhan, China: A modelling study</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>395</volume>, <fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>697</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32014114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>A mathematical model for the spatiotemporal epidemic spreading of COVID19</article-title>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.21.20040022</pub-id><comment> (23 March 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altieri</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Curating a COVID-19 data repository and forecasting county-level death counts in the United States</article-title>. <comment>arXiv:2005.07882 (16 May 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IHME COVID-19 Health Service Utilization Forecasting Team</collab></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>C. J. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Forecasting COVID-19 impact on hospital bed-days, ICU-days, ventilator-days and deaths by US state in the next 4 months</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/early/2020/03/30/2020.03.27.20043752" xlink:show="new">https://www.medrxiv.org/content/early/2020/03/30/2020.03.27.20043752</ext-link> (30 March 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Projections of hospital based healthcare demand due to COVID-19 in Los Angeles county. County DHS COVID 19 Predictive Modeling Team: May 6 update</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dhs.lacounty.gov/wps/portal/dhs/covid19/mp" xlink:show="new">http://dhs.lacounty.gov/wps/portal/dhs/covid19/mp</ext-link>. Accessed 10 April 2020</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>An interactive web-based dashboard to track COVID-19 in real time</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>534</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32087114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenberg</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Short</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sledge</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Analyzing the world-wide impact of public health interventions on the transmission dynamics of COVID-19</article-title>. <comment>arXiv:2004.01714 (3 April 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gayle</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilder-Smith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rockl&#x000f6;v</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>The reproductive number of COVID-19 is higher compared to SARS coronavirus</article-title>. <source>J. Trav. Med.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>taaa021</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Time course of lung changes on chest CT during recovery from coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source>, <volume>295</volume>, <fpage>715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>721</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32053470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: A retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>395</volume>, <fpage>1054</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1062</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32171076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus&#x02013;infected pneumonia</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<volume>382</volume>, <fpage>1199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1207</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31995857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Held</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000f6;hle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Spatio-temporal analysis of epidemic phenomena using the R package surveillance</article-title>. <source>J. Stat. Softw.</source>
<volume>77</volume>, <fpage>6981</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanaan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Branching process models for surveillance of infectious diseases controlled by mass vaccination</article-title>. <source>Biostatistics</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>295</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12925522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenberg</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrigan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>A recursive point process model for infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>Ann. Inst. Stat. Math.</source>
<volume>71</volume>, <fpage>1271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1287</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrigan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Real-time predictions of the 2018-2019 Ebola virus disease outbreak in the Democratic Republic of Congo using Hawkes point process models</article-title>. <source>Epidemics</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>100354</fpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31395373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stomakhin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Short</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertozzi</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Reconstruction of missing data in social networks based on temporal patterns of interactions</article-title>. <source>Inverse Probl.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>115013</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Modeling e-mail networks and inferring leadership using self-exciting point processes</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Stat. Assoc.</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>584</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zipkin</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenberg</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coronges</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertozzi</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Point-process models of social network interactions: Parameter estimation and missing data recovery</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Appl. Math.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>502</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>529</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cauchemez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Real-time estimates in early detection of SARS</article-title>. <source>Emerg. Infect. Dis.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallinga</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teunis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Different epidemic curves for severe acute respiratory syndrome reveal similar impacts of control measures</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Epidemiol.</source>
<volume>160</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>516</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15353409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forsberg White</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>A likelihood-based method for real-time estimation of the serial interval and reproductive number of an epidemic</article-title>. <source>Stat. Med.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>2999</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3016</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18058829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obadia</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haneef</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bo&#x000eb;lle</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>The <inline-formula><mml:math id="i144"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> package: A toolbox to estimate reproduction numbers for epidemic outbreaks</article-title>. <source>BMC Med. Inform. Decis. Mak.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23249562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>The effective reproduction number of pandemic influenza: Prospective estimation</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>842</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>846</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20805752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizoiu</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>SIR-Hawkes: Linking epidemic models and Hawkes processes to model diffusions in finite populations</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.01679" xlink:show="new">https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.01679</ext-link> (21 February 2018)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Estimation of the time-varying reproduction number of COVID-19 outbreak in China</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3539694" xlink:show="new">https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3539694</ext-link> (19 February 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Transmission dynamics of the etiological agent of SARS in Hong Kong: Impact of public health interventions</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>300</volume>, <fpage>1961</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1966</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12766206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verity</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Estimates of the severity of COVID-19 disease</article-title>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.09.20033357</pub-id><comment> (13 March 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akaike</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>A new look at the statistical model identification</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>723</lpage> (<year>1974</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo-Chavez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Mathematical Models in Epidemiology</source> (<publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kermack</surname><given-names>W. O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKendrick</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics</article-title>. <source>Proc. Roy. Soc. A</source>
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>700</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>721</lpage> (<year>1927</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolles</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luong</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Modeling epidemics with compartmental models</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.8420</pub-id> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bootsma</surname><given-names>M. C. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>The effect of public health measures on the 1918 influenza pandemic in U.S. cities</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>7588</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7593</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frasso</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Bayesian inference in an extended SEIR model with nonparametric disease transmission rate: An application to the Ebola epidemic in Sierra Leone</article-title>. <source>Biostatistics</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>779</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>792</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27324411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Angelov</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slavtchova-Bojkova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Bayesian estimation of the offspring mean in branching processes: Application to infectious disease data</article-title>. <source>Comput. Math. Appl.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>235</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>A note on the derivation of epidemic final sizes</article-title>. <source>Bull. Math. Biol.</source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>2125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2141</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22829179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Mathematical models of SIR disease spread with combined non-sexual and sexual transmission routes</article-title>. <source>Infect. Dis. Model.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29928728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>F. S. N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Exact analytical solutions of the susceptible-infected-recovered (SIR) epidemic model and of the SIR model with equal death and birth rates</article-title>. <source>Appl. Math. Comput.</source>
<volume>236</volume>, <fpage>184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sledge</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Health Divided: Public Health and Individual Medicine in the Making of the Modern American State</source> (<publisher-name>University Press of Kansas</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Lawrence, KS</publisher-loc>, <year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haffajee</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Thinking globally, acting locally&#x02014;the U.S. response to COVID-19</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<volume>382</volume>, <fpage>e75</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32240580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Distribution theory, stochastic processes and infectious disease modelling</article-title>&#x0201d; in <source>Mathematical Epidemiology</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Driessche</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, J. Wu</person-group>, Eds. (<publisher-name>Lecture Notes in Mathematics</publisher-name>, <volume>vol. 1945</volume>, <publisher-loc>Springer, Berlin</publisher-loc>, <year>2008</year>), pp. <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>293</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Godfrey</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>The structural identifiability of the susceptible infected recovered model with seasonal forcing</article-title>. <source>Math. Biosci.</source>
<volume>194</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15854675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roosa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowell</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Assessing parameter identifiability in compartmental dynamic models using a computational approach: Application to infectious disease transmission models</article-title>. <source>Theor. Biol. Med. Model.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30642334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>, <comment>Coronavirus disease (COVID-2019) situation reports. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/situation-reports" xlink:show="new">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/situation-reports</ext-link>. Accessed 1 April 2020</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Estimating clinical severity of COVID-19 from the transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China</article-title>. <source>Nat. Med.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>506</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>510</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32284616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>