<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26390403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4577101</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-16462</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Kinetics on Demand Is a Simple Mathematical Solution that Fits Recorded Caffeine-Induced Luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> Changes in Smooth Muscle Cells</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Kinetics on Demand Ca<sup>2+</sup> Release</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Rosas</surname><given-names>Norma C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez-Viquez</surname><given-names>Norma L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dagnino-Acosta</surname><given-names>Adan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santillan</surname><given-names>Moises</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guerrero-Hernandez</surname><given-names>Agust&#x000ed;n</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Unidad Monterrey, Cinvestav, Apodaca, Nuevo Leon, Mexico</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Farmacobiolog&#x000ed;a, Unidad Sur, Cinvestav, Mexico City, Mexico</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Centro Universitario de Investigaciones Biom&#x000e9;dicas, Universidad de Colima, Colima, Colima, Mexico</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Bioqu&#x000ed;mica, Cinvestav, Mexico City, Mexico</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Laver</surname><given-names>Derek</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Newcastle, AUSTRALIA</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MS AGH. Performed the experiments: NLGV ADA. Analyzed the data: NCPR NLGV ADA MS AGH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: NCPR NLGV ADA MS AGH. Wrote the paper: NCPR MS AGH. Mathematical modelling: NCPR MS.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>aguerrero@cinvestav.mx</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e0138195</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 Perez-Rosas et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Perez-Rosas et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0138195.pdf"/><abstract><p>The process of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from sarcoplasmic reticulum (SR) comprises 4 phases in smooth muscle cells. Phase 1 is characterized by a large increase of the intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>) with a minimal reduction of the free luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>). Importantly, active SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> ATPases (SERCA pumps) are necessary for phase 1 to occur. This situation cannot be explained by the standard kinetics that involves a fixed amount of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites. A new mathematical model was developed that assumes an increasing SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering capacity in response to an increase of the luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] that is called Kinetics-on-Demand (KonD) model. This approach can explain both phase 1 and the refractory period associated with a recovered [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>. Additionally, our data suggest that active SERCA pumps are a requisite for KonD to be functional; otherwise luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins switch to standard kinetics. The importance of KonD Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding properties is twofold: a more efficient Ca<sup>2+</sup> release process and that [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-bound to SR proteins ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>BSR</sub>) can be regulated separately allowing for Ca<sup>2+</sup> release to occur (provided by Ca<sup>2+</sup>-bound to luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins) without an initial reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnologia (MX) grant 128735 to AGH and grant 266919 to NCPR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.conacyt.mx/">http://www.conacyt.mx/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="22"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. The mathematical model was deposited in Biomodels Database and assigned the identifier MODEL 1406180001.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. The mathematical model was deposited in Biomodels Database and assigned the identifier MODEL 1406180001.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The main internal Ca<sup>2+</sup> store is the sarcoplasmic reticulum (SR) in muscle cells and the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) in non-muscle cells. These membrane organelles are distributed throughout the cell and are endowed with three main elements 1) SERCA pumps, 2) different types of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release channels [Ryanodine or inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptors (RyRs and IP<sub>3</sub>Rs, respectively)], and 3) luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins (calsequestrin or calreticulin). All these different types of proteins produce and modulate Ca<sup>2+</sup> release events that can be either localized in nature or traveling Ca<sup>2+</sup> waves [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>SERCA pumps refill internal Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores via ATP hydrolysis [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. These ATPases are regulated by the free luminal SR/ER [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>) and by different type of proteins [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Although the role of SERCA pumps in Ca<sup>2+</sup> refilling of SR stores is well established, there are also data indicating that SERCA pumps facilitate Ca<sup>2+</sup> release by a mechanism unrelated to the replenishment of internal Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Ikemoto&#x000b4;s group has shown that activation of RyRs produces an increase in the turnover rate of SERCA pumps before any reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Additionally, they have found that low concentrations of polylysine that activate a small number of RyRs, can induce an initial increase in the luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> level [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and activation of SERCA pumps [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In pancreatic acinar cells, it was shown that inhibition of SERCA pumps with thapsigargin decreases the rate of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release and eliminates [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> gradients before any reduction of the ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> store [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. More recently, it was reported that rapid inhibition of SERCA pumps by UV-mediated uncaging of thapsigargin produces a significantly slower Ca<sup>2+</sup> wave in heart cells [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In HeLa cells, the rapid inhibition of SERCA pumps to avoid any reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>, reduces the histamine-induced potentiation of IP<sub>3</sub>-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In smooth muscle cells, thapsigargin decreases the amplitude and the rate of rise of caffeine- and carbachol-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Moreover, inhibition of SERCA pumps decreased the coordinated Ca<sup>2+</sup> release process even in overloaded Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores of smooth muscle cells [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Interestingly, there is also evidence that increased activity of SERCA pumps enhances Ca<sup>2+</sup> release. For instance, RGS2<sup>-/-</sup> knockout displayed facilitation in the agonist-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release, but due to increased expression of SERCA pump instead of the expected, but absent, larger IP<sub>3</sub> production [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Overexpression of &#x003b2; adrenoceptors increases both SERCA pump activity and Ca<sup>2+</sup> spark frequency in heart cells, in the absence of an overloaded SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> store [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Collectively, these data suggest that SERCA pumps play an important role not only in refilling internal Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores but also, in facilitating activation of release channels.</p><p>SR and ER also contain a large variety of proteins that bind Ca<sup>2+</sup> with low affinity and high capacity, for instance calsequestrin and calreticulin. Interestingly, the Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffer capacity of calsequestrin increases with the degree of polymerization, from monomer to dimer and to polymer [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These characteristics of calsequestrin suggest a possible explanation for the observation that SR and ER are able to supply large quantities of Ca<sup>2+</sup> with minimal reductions in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] i.e. the transition from dimer to monomer, for instance, releases a large quantity of Ca<sup>2+</sup> with minimal modification of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The presence of these concealed sources of Ca<sup>2+</sup> is evident in cardiac cells as well, because the overexpression of calsequestrin containing a point mutation (CASQ2<sup>R33Q</sup>) produces Ca<sup>2+</sup> sparks of larger amplitude, although the SR seems to be partially depleted because a reduced resting [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> is observed [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Additionally, the reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> is similar for the smaller Ca<sup>2+</sup> sparks than for the larger Ca<sup>2+</sup> waves [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. All these data imply that the change in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> cannot be correlated with the total amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> released by the SR so we have hypothesized that there is a concealed source of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> for release channels [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>Since it is not feasible yet to look simultaneously at both [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and the amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-bound to luminal proteins ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>BSR</sub>), to test this hypothesis a simple deterministic mathematical model was developed, in order to understand how release channels (particularly RyRs), luminal SR proteins and SERCA pumps work together to facilitate Ca<sup>2+</sup> release in smooth muscle cells. This new model suggests that luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins are working different to what it is commonly believed, since the number of apparent Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites increases as a function of the free luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], this situation we have called Kinetics on Demand (KonD), and requires active SERCA pumps to have an efficient Ca<sup>2+</sup> release event.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Ethics statement on animal use</title><p>All animal care and experimental procedures were performed in compliance with the Mexican Official Norm for the Use and Care of Laboratory Animals (NOM-062-ZOO-1999) and the protocol was approved by the local Ethics Committee on Animal Experimentation (CICUAL-Cinvestav) with the reference number 0306&#x02013;06 and renewed with the reference number 0131&#x02013;15. Animals were bred and housed in Cinvestav Animal facility with clean air and controlled both light and temperature. Food and water was given ad libitum. Precautions were implemented to minimize animal use and reduce pain and distress.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Cell isolation and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> recordings</title><p>Male albino guinea pigs of 400 to 490g weight (all from Cinvestav animal facility) were killed by decapitation followed by exsanguination. Single smooth muscle cells were isolated from guinea pig urinary bladder and loaded with fura-2 to record [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> as previously reported [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Simultaneous recording of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and the free luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> level ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>) in these cells was carried out using fura-2 and Mag-Fluo-4, respectively; as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Ca<sup>2+</sup> release was induced by application of 2 or 20 mM caffeine with a puffer pipette [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Inhibition of SERCA pump with short pulses of thapsigargin was carried out as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The development of the mathematical model is described below.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Model development</title><p>For the purpose of the present model we have considered that smooth muscle cells consist of two compartments: the cytoplasm and the SR (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>), and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>Ti</sub> and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> represent the total [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] in the respective compartments. Let J<sub>1</sub> be the Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux from the cytoplasm to outside the cell together with all cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> removal mechanisms (except SERCA pumps) that are involved in keeping a constant basal concentration of this ion, J<sub>2</sub> be the Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux from the SR to the cytoplasm via RyRs present in the SR membrane, and J<sub>3</sub> be the Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux from the cytoplasm to the SR via SERCA pumps located in the SR membrane. It follows from these considerations that
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e001.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e001g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.1)</label></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e002"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e002.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e002g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.2)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>All fluxes have units of concentration/time which are referred to the volume of the cytoplasm. Accordingly, the factor &#x003b3; denotes the volume ratio between the SR and the cytoplasm.</p><p>As indicated above, J<sub>1</sub> considers all plasma membrane Ca<sup>2+</sup> removal mechanisms and based on the observation that this process has a first order kinetics, as shown by Guerrero et al. [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], we have assumed that
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e003"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e003.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e003g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.3)</label></disp-formula>
where [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> is the free cytoplasmic [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], while <inline-formula id="pone.0138195.e004"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e004.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e004g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the resting basal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, and <italic>a</italic> is the first order kinetic constant for this flux. We have assumed that no membrane potential exists across the SR membrane [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], therefore the flux J<sub>2</sub> is driven by the gradient of free Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions across this membrane:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e005"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e005.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e005g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.4)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>b</italic> is a constant parameter proportional to the maximum [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] flow through a single RyR, <italic>P</italic>
<sub><italic>o</italic></sub>([<italic>Ca</italic>
<sup>2+</sup>]<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>,[<italic>Caff</italic>]) is the probability that a single RyR is open as a function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and of the caffeine concentration ([Caff]) used to induce Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from SR store, [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> is the concentration of free Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the SR, and <inline-formula id="pone.0138195.e006"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e006.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e006g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is a proportionality constant for the number of RyR based on <italic>&#x003b3;</italic> being the volume ratio between SR and cytoplasm. SR appears to have a complex fractal-like structure, hence its surface should scale with respect to the volume according to a power law <inline-formula id="pone.0138195.e007"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e007.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e007g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <italic>n</italic>
<sub><italic>v</italic></sub> is a parameter related to the SR fractal dimension [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Accordingly, if we assume that the density of RyR on SR surface is constant, the number of these ion channels results to be proportional to <inline-formula id="pone.0138195.e008"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e008.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e008g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p><p>Regarding J<sub>3</sub> flux, we have modeled SERCA pump activity following Lyton et al. [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and it follows that:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e009"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e009.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e009g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.5)</label></disp-formula>
with <italic>c</italic> representing the maximum Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux through SERCA pumps, <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>s</italic></sub> the corresponding half saturation constant, and <italic>n</italic>
<sub><italic>s</italic></sub> a Hill coefficient.</p><p>In the cytoplasm, Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions can be either free or bound to buffering proteins. By definition Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffer (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>) is the ratio between the increment in Ca<sup>2+</sup> bound to proteins and the increment in free [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], so it follows that:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e010"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e010.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e010g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.6)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>Assuming infinitesimal small increments, Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e010" ref-type="disp-formula">1.6</xref>) can be solved by Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">1.7</xref>).
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e011"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e011.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e011g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.7)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>B</italic>
<sub><italic>T</italic></sub> represents the total amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites with a dissociation constant K<sub>D</sub>.</p><p>However, this definition is rather impractical because is very difficult to determine the amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> bound to proteins in a cell. However, it is rather easy to determine the total amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> added to the cell [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and then a new Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering capacity can be defined as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e012"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e012.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e012g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.8)</label></disp-formula>
and in this case, it turns out that Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e012" ref-type="disp-formula">1.8</xref>) is related to Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">1.7</xref>) by the following:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e013"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e013.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e013g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.9)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>Interestingly, the cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering of smooth muscle and chromaffin cells appears to be constant [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. We have modeled the relation between free and total cytoplasmic [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e014"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e014.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e014g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.10)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>Regarding the RyR open probability, it is known that it increases when Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions bind this channel on its cytoplasmic side, a process regarded as Ca<sup>2+</sup> induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release (CICR), which functions at low efficiency in smooth muscle cell [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In this work we have used caffeine to increase the Ca<sup>2+</sup> affinity of smooth muscle&#x02019;s RyR so they open even when Ca<sup>2+</sup> is at basal level. To account for the above described phenomenon we have assumed that each of the four subunits of RyR has binding sites for Ca<sup>2+</sup> and caffeine, and these molecules interact cooperatively when they are bound. From this consideration and the assumption of chemical equilibrium, the probability that there is a Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion bound to its corresponding binding site, regardless of the state of the caffeine site is:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e015"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e015.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e015g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>
where <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>C</italic></sub> is the dissociation constant of RyR-Ca<sup>2+</sup> complex, <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>F</italic></sub> is the dissociation constant of the RyR-caffeine complex, and <italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>F</italic></sub> &#x0003e; 1 accounts for the cooperativity between Ca<sup>2+</sup> and caffeine. Under the assumption that [<italic>Caff</italic>]/<italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>F</italic></sub> &#x0226a; 1, the above expression can be rewritten as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e016"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e016.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e016g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>
with <italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>f</italic></sub> = <italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>F</italic></sub> / <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>F</italic></sub>. Finally, considering that Ca<sup>2+</sup> needs to be bound to all four subunits in order for the channel to open, and that there is a certain amount of cooperativity among subunits, the RyR open probability can be written as [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e017"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e017.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e017g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.11)</label></disp-formula>
with <italic>n</italic>
<sub><italic>F</italic></sub> being a Hill coefficient. The Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion in the SR can be either free or bound to proteins.</p><p>Let P denote concentration of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites within the SR, and P<sub>C</sub> the concentration of sites already occupied with Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Under the assumption of chemical equilibrium, it follows that:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e018"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e018.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e018g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.12)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>R</italic></sub> is the corresponding dissociation constant of this protein P. Moreover, let P<sub>E</sub> denote the concentration of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites in the absence of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Hence, it follows from the assumption that the total number of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites remains constant that
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e019"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e019.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e019g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M19"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.13)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>By solving for P<sub>C</sub> from Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e018" ref-type="disp-formula">1.12</xref>) and Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e019" ref-type="disp-formula">1.13</xref>) we obtain
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e020"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e020.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e020g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.14)</label></disp-formula>
and because Ca<sup>2+</sup> can only be free or bound then,
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e021"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e021.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e021g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.15)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>Hence, by solving for [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> from Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e020" ref-type="disp-formula">1.14</xref>) and Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e021" ref-type="disp-formula">1.15</xref>) we get the following expression for the concentration of free luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> in terms of the total Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration in the SR:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e022"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e022.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e022g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.16)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>&#x003be;</italic> = [<italic>Ca</italic>
<sup>2+</sup>]<sub><italic>TSR</italic></sub> &#x02212; <italic>P</italic>
<sub><italic>E</italic></sub> &#x02212; <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>R</italic></sub>. This is the classical approach for saturable kinetics (Standard Kinetics, SK) because, as seen in Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e019" ref-type="disp-formula">1.13</xref>), the amount of free binding sites is depleted as the amount of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> increases and the available sites are bound. In this case the Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffer capacity can be estimated by Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">1.7</xref>) (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2A Fig</xref>). This graph shows that <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> is a decreasing function of Ca<sup>2+</sup> that approaches zero when <italic>Ca</italic>
<sup>2+</sup> &#x0003e;&#x0003e; <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>D</italic></sub>. Nonetheless, this type of kinetics cannot explain phase 1 of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release observed in smooth muscle [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We have come to realize that Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to calsequestrin shows an increase of B<sub>max</sub> as Ca<sup>2+</sup> was elevated (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>). Based on fitting, previously published data [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], to binding curves with different values of B<sub>max</sub>. We have observed that B<sub>max</sub> value increases as a function of the window of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] that was used to calculate the binding curve (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>). Base on this type of behavior, we have suggested a new kinetic model called <bold>Kinetics on Demand (KonD)</bold>. Additionally, there are data using X-ray microanalysis showing that sections of the ER behave as if the buffering capacity is extremely large [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] in combination with regions in which the free luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] does not change, a situation that might reflect the ability of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering proteins to have a KonD type of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding. This observation is compatible with the assumption that new Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites become apparent as the already available ones are bound to Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Since there is no mathematical framework to model this type of behavior, we decided to test this new paradigm by assuming that Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e019" ref-type="disp-formula">1.13</xref>) can be substituted with the following:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e023"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e023.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e023g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M23"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.17)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>If we take this new relation and repeat the procedure leading to Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e022" ref-type="disp-formula">1.16</xref>) we have obtained the following expression relating the free and the total SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations:
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e024"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e024.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e024g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.18)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>&#x003be;</italic> = [<italic>Ca</italic>
<sup>2+</sup>]<sub><italic>TSR</italic></sub> + <italic>P</italic>
<sub><italic>E</italic></sub> + <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>R</italic></sub>.</p><p>Interestingly, this new type of kinetics displays a growing Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering capacity (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2B Fig</xref>), as long as Ca<sup>2+</sup> is below the dissociation constant because
<disp-formula id="pone.0138195.e025"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.e025.jpg" id="pone.0138195.e025g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M25"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1.19)</label></disp-formula>
when Ca<sup>2+</sup> is above <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>D</italic></sub> then the buffering power is also a decreasing function as it is the case of Standard Kinetics.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Parameter estimation</title><p>The parameters used in the model are shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. These were obtained by adjusting data using [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses induced by 20 mM caffeine and by assuming that the amount of SR responding to caffeine varied from cell to cell and was between 1 and 10% of the cell volume.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0138195.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Parameters used for KonD mathematical model simulation of variability of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses to caffeine for control condition (20 mM caffeine), lower caffeine (2 mM) and inhibited SERCA pump with thapsigargin.</title><p>All parameters values were the same as those obtained with 20mM caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response except where indicated with bold letters. The description of parameters can be found in Supporting Information (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0138195.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0138195.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 mM caffeine</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 mM caffeine</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thapsigargin + 20 mM caffeine</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 s<sup>-1</sup>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 s<sup>-1</sup>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 s<sup>-1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.2 s<sup>-1</sup>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.2 s<sup>-1</sup>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.2 s<sup>-1</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.25 &#x003bc;M/s</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.25 &#x003bc;M/s</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.25 &#x003bc;M/s</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 nM</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 nM</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 nM</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;10%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;10%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;10%</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n<sub><italic>v</italic></sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>s</sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300 nM</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300 nM</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300 nM</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n<sub>s</sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n<sub>F</sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">k<sub>f</sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 mM<sup>-1</sup>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 mM<sup>-1</sup>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.3 mM</bold>
<sup><bold>-1</bold></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Caffeine]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 mM</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2 mM</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 mM</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 mM</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 mM</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.75 mM</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 &#x003bc;M</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 &#x003bc;M</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 &#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>R</sub>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.5 &#x003bc;M</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.5 &#x003bc;M</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.5 &#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thapsigargin</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calsequestrin</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec007"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec008"><title>Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from the SR involved four different phases in smooth muscle cells</title><p>Simultaneous recordings of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> in smooth muscle cells have demonstrated that activation of RyRs by caffeine induces a large increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> before any reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> (phase 1), which is followed by a large reduction of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and a plateau of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> increase (phase 2). Additionally, it was found that rapid inhibition of SERCA pump reduces both the amplitude and the rate of rise of the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. <xref rid="pone.0138195.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref> shows the effect of 5-sec stimulation with caffeine on the simultaneous recording of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (upper trace) and the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> (middle trace) before and after the inhibition of SERCA pumps with thapsigargin. Application with a second puffer pipette of 10 &#x003bc;M thapsigargin for 5 sec was enough to inhibit completely the recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> after terminating the second application of caffeine (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref>). This effect agrees with, the already described, irreversible inhibitory action of thapsigargin on SERCA pump activity [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. <xref rid="pone.0138195.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref> blue line indicates those four phases of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release for data shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref> in the absence of thapsigargin. The effect of inhibiting SERCA pumps with thapsigargin on the phase diagram is shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref> (green line). Interestingly, phase 1 and 2 are fused together in a single phase showing now a linear correlation between the reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and the diminished increase in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response.</p><fig id="pone.0138195.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release involves four phases that require active SERCA pumps in smooth muscle cells.</title><p>Single freshly isolated smooth muscle cells from guinea pig urinary bladder were loaded with both fura-2 and Mag-Fluo-4 to measure [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>, respectively. (A) Caffeine application (20 mM with a puffer pipette for 5 seconds) induced a transient increase of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and a transient reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>. Inhibition of SERCA pumps with thapsigargin reduced both the amplitude and the rate of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response; however, (B) close examination of these responses show that caffeine induced an increase in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> before any reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> (phase 1) followed by a sharp reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> without any effect on the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (phase 2). Interestingly, the inhibition of SERCA pumps with thapsigargin fused phase1 and phase 2 in a linear reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> associated with a smaller increase of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. Ca<sup>2+</sup> recording were carried out as previously described (10).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Kinetics on demand model fitted the caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release</title><p>To get an insight on how SERCA pumps might control SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> release in smooth muscle cells we have developed a simple deterministic mathematical model based on the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response to two different caffeine concentrations (2 and 20 mM) and the effect of rapid inhibition of SERCA pump with thapsigargin on the 20 mM caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response. The mathematical model is based on a new concept named Kinetics-on-Demand (KonD), where Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding sites of SR Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins are an increasing function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (see <xref rid="sec005" ref-type="sec">Model development</xref>). RyRs were modeled as homotetrameric channels activated by Ca<sup>2+</sup> and caffeine. Application of 20 mM caffeine with a puffer pipette to freshly isolated smooth muscle cells loaded with Fura-2 produced a transient [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response with large variability in the amplitude, the rate of rise and the time to peak. Our mathematical model was able to reproduce this variability by assuming that the SR volume responding to caffeine varied between 1 and 10% of cell volume. The values for the rest of the parameters are shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and were determined using those that fitted [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses induced by 20 mM caffeine. <xref rid="pone.0138195.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2A</xref> shows the relationship between the amplitude of 20 mM caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses and the corresponding maximal rate of rise for 66 different cells and how the model fitted this relationship by varying the fraction of responding SR volume (blue line). The KonD model was also able to reproduce the relation between the peak rate of rise and the rise time of the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2B</xref>). This model was used also to simulate the time course of caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2C</xref>, blue line) together with the changes in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2C</xref>, green line).</p><fig id="pone.0138195.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses induced by 20 mM caffeine and their fitting by KonD model.</title><p>(A) Variability of the amplitude and the rate of rise of caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses for 66 different cells and the fitting by KonD model (blue line) of these responses. (B) Same responses as shown in (A) but comparing the time to peak and the rate of rise that was fitted by the model. (C) Time course of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response (open circles) fitted by the model (blue line) and the reduction in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> predicted by the KonD model (green line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.g002"/></fig><p>To assess the robustness of our mathematical model, we used the parameters found for fitting 20 mM-caffeine induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses to model the responses obtained with 2 mM caffeine. In this case the same parameters shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> were used, except for the concentration of caffeine. The application of 2 mM caffeine produced on average smaller and slower [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses that were reproduced by the KonD model. There were also good fittings between the maximal rate of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> rise and either the peak [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A</xref>) or the rise time (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>). These parameters also fitted the time course of the 2 mM caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3C</xref>, blue line) and show the time-course for the reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3C</xref>, green line). These results with 2 mM caffeine suggest that the KonD model is robust enough to evaluate which parameters play a role in the SERCA-inhibited [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses induced by caffeine.</p><fig id="pone.0138195.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses induced by 2 mM caffeine and their fitting by KonD model.</title><p>(A) Variability of the amplitude and rate of rise of the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses for 49 different cells and the fitting by KonD model (blue line) of these responses. (B) Comparison of the rise time vs rate of rise for the same [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses and fitting by KonD model (blue line). (C) Time course for both [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and KonD model (blue line) together with the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> response derived from the model (green line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Inhibition of SERCA Ca<sup>2+</sup> pumps changed caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from KonD model to SK model</title><p>Application of thapsigargin (10 &#x003bc;M) with a second puffer pipette for 5 seconds and 30 seconds before the application of caffeine resulted, as expected, in smaller (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>) and slower (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses. In this case the reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> occurred at a higher rate than when SERCA pumps are active and yet, the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response was both smaller and slower (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4C</xref>, green line).</p><fig id="pone.0138195.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Effect of SERCA pump inhibition by thapsigargin on 20 mM caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses.</title><p>(A) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses of 12 different cells that were exposed to thapsigargin for 5 seconds, 30 seconds before the application of caffeine, were smaller in amplitude and slower and (B) with a larger rise time. The mathematical model fitted this relationship but only after switching from KonD model to SK model (blue lines). (C) Time course of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response to 20 mM caffeine from a cell that had been previously exposed to thapsigargin together with fitting by modified SK model (blue line) and the resulting reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>SR</sub> from this model (green line). Notice there was no recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> as expected for inhibited SERCA pumps.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.g004"/></fig><p>The phase diagram displayed in <xref rid="pone.0138195.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref> shows that inhibition of SERCA pump combined phases 1 and 2 resulting now in a linear relation between the increase in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and the reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>. We have used KonD model to determine which parameters need to be changed to reproduce the effect of thapsigargin. This exercise is shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>. Where <xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref> is the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses to the application of 20 mM caffeine where indicated, while <xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref> corresponds to the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and <xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5C</xref> shows the total SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub>) which corresponds to the sum of both [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>BSR</sub> and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>. The complete inhibition of SERCA pump by itself did not importantly alter (red line) the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response to the application of 20 mM caffeine (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>, blue line) but as expected, completely eliminated the recovery of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> after caffeine application (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>, red line). However, we observed a significant reduction in the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response by changing the way that luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins interact with Ca<sup>2+</sup> by using now SK condition instead of KonD (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>, green line). Interestingly, the main difference is that the delay for the reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> has disappeared (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>, green line) and although the total amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> released by the SR is the same in both conditions; in the SK condition occurs at a slower rate than at KonD (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5C</xref>, green line vs blue line). This slower kinetics of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release increased the effect of cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> removal mechanisms on the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response. The effect of thapsigargin on caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response is a reduction of both the peak amplitude and the rate of rise. While the former was accomplished by switching from KonD to SK, the latter required a reduction of both <italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>f</italic></sub> parameter (see <xref rid="sec005" ref-type="sec">Model development</xref>) and the amount of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins involved during Ca<sup>2+</sup> release (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>, solid line). Since the time taken by thapsigargin to produce these two effects is rather short, we think that the concentration of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins is not modified and instead there is a reduction in the number of RyRs that are coupled to the luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins and responding to caffeine. This situation effectively reduces the amplitude of the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response without any reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub>. However, to achieve this effect in our model we decided to reduce the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> to fit the recorded data (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5C</xref> solid line).</p><fig id="pone.0138195.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Inhibition of SERCA pump switches Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from KonD condition to SK situation.</title><p>The control response to application of 20 mM caffeine using KonD model is shown for (A) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, (B) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and (C) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> (blue lines). Inhibition of SERCA pump with thapsigargin (B, C, red line) impaired recovery of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> but did not alter the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response (A, red line). Switching from KonD to SK significantly reduced the amplitude of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (A, green line) because decreased the reduction of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> (C, green line) although accelerated the reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> (B, green line). To reduce both the amplitude and the rate of rise, it was reduced the number of release channels involved (<italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>f</italic></sub>, magenta line) and accordingly we have to reduce also the amount of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins involved (LCBC, solid line). Caffeine was present for a period of 5 seconds to activate RyRs beginning at the time point of 10 seconds as indicated by the dashed bar.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.g005"/></fig><p>The KonD model can reproduce the four phases of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release, particularly the transition from phase 1 to phase 2 (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6A</xref>, blue line). Importantly, switching from KonD to SK showed that phase 1 and 2 disappeared and resulted now in a linear relationship between the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6A</xref>, red line). Comparison between the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> clarifies why KonD condition is more efficient in increasing [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> than SK. In KonD the Ca<sup>2+</sup> supplied to the cytoplasm comes mainly from Ca<sup>2+</sup> bound to proteins with minimal reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6B</xref>, blue line) while in the SK situation happens exactly the opposite (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6B</xref>, red line). This is very important because explains why the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> does not correlate with the supply of Ca<sup>2+</sup> to the cytoplasm. Additionally, our mathematical model suggests that SERCA pump modulates the number of release channels coupled to luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins, such that inhibition of SERCA can produce also a reduction of the amplitude of Ca<sup>2+</sup> response by decreasing the number of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins participating in Ca<sup>2+</sup> release response (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6B</xref>, green line).</p><fig id="pone.0138195.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>KonD model reproduces phase diagram of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release.</title><p>(A) KonD model reproduces phase diagram seen in caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release (blue line) and this is altered by inhibiting SERCA pump and switching to SK condition (red line). Reducing the number of RyRs participating and the amount of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins (LCBC) reduces even further the amplitude of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response but with a similar phase diagram (green line) that compares very well with experimental data (<xref rid="pone.0138195.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). (B) KonD condition generated a luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering power curve with a positive curvature as has been observed in skeletal muscle (blue line). This explains a large supply of Ca<sup>2+</sup> to the cytoplasm (due to a large reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> with minimal reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>). Switching to SK condition generated a negative curvature that means a larger reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> but a much smaller reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> (red line) and accordingly a smaller increase in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. Reducing the amount of luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding protein participating in response to caffeine decreased the total amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> supplied by SR (green line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>KonD model explained the refractory period associated with the recovery of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> after caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release</title><p>The activation of ryanodine receptors by a saturating concentration of caffeine produced a transient increase in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> due to Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from the SR. The application of a second pulse of caffeine just 30 seconds after the first pulse, produced a significantly smaller transient [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response of only 20% in amplitude [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. A straightforward explanation would be that the SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> store did not have enough time to recover after caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release. However, the recorded [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> shows that this time of 30 seconds was enough to reach the initial level of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. This is a paradox because the SK condition says that recovery of the free luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] implies the complete recovery of total SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], which in turn should generate a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response of similar amplitude to the one produced by the first application of caffeine. <xref rid="pone.0138195.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref> shows the fitting by either the KonD model (red line) or the SK model (green line) of the simultaneous recording (blue line) of both the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (upper traces) and the changes in the free luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (lower traces) in response to the dual application of saturating concentrations of caffeine (middle trace). The parameters used here are exactly the same to those shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and employed for fitting the response to 20 mM caffeine shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref> except, that here, the ratio between the SR and the cytoplasm was modify to fit the amplitude of the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response. The same parameters were used for the SK model. Since caffeine released the same amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> from the SR for both models, the reduced amplitude of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response seen with the standard model was due to the competition for Ca<sup>2+</sup> between the luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins and the release channels, a situation that is not observed in the KonD model as demonstrated in <xref rid="pone.0138195.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>. Since the SK model does not have phase 1, the reduction in the luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] slightly precedes the recorded reduction of the luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. On the other hand, KonD model shows an exaggerated phase 1. Interestingly, the KonD model shows a rapid recovery of the free luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] that does not involve the recovery of the total SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (see <xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>) while in the SK model, since these two parameters go together; there is only a minimal recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>. This result is also true even when using parameters that best fit the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Fig</xref>). This discrepancy between these two models, allows KonD model to explain the apparent paradox of having a recovered free luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] with a still reduced total SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. It appears then that KonD describes much better how the SR luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins behave during caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release in smooth muscle cells.</p><fig id="pone.0138195.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138195.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title>Refractory [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response to the application of caffeine.</title><p>A set of experimental results (blue line) of simultaneous recording of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (upper trace) and SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels (bottom trace) in response to the application of two pulses of caffeine (middle trace) are presented. Notice that by 30 s after the first application of caffeine both [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels have recovered to resting levels. A second application of caffeine produce the same response in the SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> with minimal effect on the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. The numerical simulations of KonD model (red line) and SK model (green line) are also shown. The simulation for both models was calculated by solving numerically the differential equations with the parameters shown in <xref rid="pone.0138195.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for 20mM of caffeine with parameter gamma equals to 2.54%. Changing parameter gamma helps SK model to fit the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> transient but does not show the same time course for the recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Fig</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0138195.g007"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec012"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec013"><title>New Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding kinetic model based on how calsequestrin binds Ca<sup>2+</sup>
</title><p>A deterministic mathematical model has been developed to simulate Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from the SR and the role of SERCA pump in facilitating this release. The main contribution of this model is the realization that experimental data cannot be fitted using the SK condition for Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to proteins. We have assumed a new type of kinetics, KonD, where the number of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites increases in response to the binding of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and the opposite happens when there is a reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>). This idea is supported by the work done with calsequestrin [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], where our own analysis of their Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding data suggest that B<sub>max</sub> (the total amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites) increases as [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] is increased, i.e. B<sub>max</sub> = 22 in the range of 0 to 0.5 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], and goes to 40 between 0.5 and 3 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], B<sub>max</sub> increases to 65 for the range of 3 to 7 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] and increases again to 79 from 7 to 20 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (see <xref rid="sec018" ref-type="sec">Supporting Information</xref>). Moreover, it has been shown that this increase in B<sub>max</sub> requires protein oligomerization because using a calsequestrin mutant incapable of aggregation shows a saturable constant B<sub>max</sub> of 22 all the way to 20 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0138195.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>) Additionally, the use of energy-dispersive X-ray microanalysis to determine Ca<sup>2+</sup> storage in the ER of pyramidal neurons show that certain regions of the ER can accumulate Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the excess of 100 mM/Kg of dry weight, more importantly, these regions are in continuity with regions of the ER that do not accumulate Ca<sup>2+</sup>, this implies that the buffering regions of the ER are not in equilibrium with the non-buffering regions of the ER since the former can accumulate large amounts of Ca<sup>2+</sup> without any change in the total amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup> of the nearby non-buffering regions of the ER [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release by smooth muscle involves four phases that are reproduced by KonD model</title><p>One key element that the model needed to reproduce is the phase 1 observed during SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> release and the transition from phase1 to phase 2. Phase 1 represents a condition of a very high Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffer capacity since there are large changes in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> with non-existent (particularly for IP<sub>3</sub>Rs, [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]) or minimal reduction in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> which is followed by phase 2 characterized by an abrupt reduction of the luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering capacity, because there is a large reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> with a minimal effect on the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. These two phases and the transition between them cannot be reproduced using SK condition of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins, i.e. a condition where there is a fixed number of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites that reach saturation on increasing the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. Interestingly, in skeletal muscle, a transition between phase 1 and phase 2 also produces an SR titration curve with a positive curvature instead of the negative curvature that is expected from the SK condition [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, in this situation it has been argued that there is an increase of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding cooperativity of the luminal SR proteins, which produces positive curvature for the relationship between the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR.</sub> The main disadvantage of this solution is that the higher the Hill coefficients, the smaller the window where the luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins can effectively buffer the luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup>. This goes in the opposite direction to what has been described for both SR and ER in the sense that they have a large Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering capacity [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Accordingly, our KonD condition can explain both an increasing Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffer capacity and an SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering curve with a positive curvature. Both situations have been observed experimentally [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. A very important difference between SK situation and KonD condition that becomes evident in <xref rid="pone.0138195.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>, is that in SK the reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] increases the competition for free Ca<sup>2+</sup> between the empty Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites of the luminal proteins and the release channel, while this is not the case with the KonD condition because there is an obligatory reduction in the number of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites due to the reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>. Additionally, this situation also explains why phase 1 is characterized by a large increase in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> with a minimal reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub>. Actually, in some cases it has been observed that elevation of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, due to Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from internal stores, is associated with an increase in the luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Importantly, this is basically impossible to achieve with the SK condition, but the KonD model will work, provided that the number of release channels that are open is not too large. Indeed, Ikemoto described how the activation of few RyRs in SR microsomes of skeletal muscle by low concentrations of polylysine produces a transient increase in the luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] and that this effect is not seen when using saturating concentrations of polylysine [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This effect was due to the presence of calsequestrin associated to the membrane of the microsomes [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Likewise, we have observed that low concentrations of heparin, to partially inhibit IP<sub>3</sub>Rs, induced a transient increase in the luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> in response to the activation of muscarinic receptors in the same type of smooth muscle cell used in this work [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Interestingly, this partial inhibition of IP<sub>3</sub>Rs resulted in larger, but short-lived, [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses to carbachol in agreement with the situation that the driving force for Ca<sup>2+</sup> release was larger due to a higher luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>SR</sub> but involved a lower number of IP<sub>3</sub>Rs [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Later on, it has been shown that spontaneous, slow Ca<sup>2+</sup> waves in heart cells, unexpectedly associate with a simultaneous elevation of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR;</sub> while the coordinated activation by membrane depolarization of a larger number of RyRs shows the expected reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and the increase of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. We think that this characteristic of RyRs and the fact that some RyRs are not associated with SR luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins might explain why KonD model produces an exaggerated phase 1 for caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release. Moreover, stimulation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release by activation of purinergic receptors in globet cells showed a clear elevation of the luminal ER [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] before any increase in the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In this case it was suggested that K<sup>+</sup> plays a key role as a counterion in Ca<sup>2+</sup> release, a situation that has been already demonstrated since the Ca<sup>2+</sup> release is strongly inhibited in the absence of K<sup>+</sup> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Interestingly, HeLa cells incubated in the absence of external [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] show a similar amplitude of the histamine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response whether the free luminal ER [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] was either high or low [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. These data suggest that release channels have access to a Ca<sup>2+</sup> source that is different to the free luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], most likely the Ca<sup>2+</sup> bound to luminal ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins. Since globet and HeLa cells do not express calsequestrin, these observations also imply that there are other luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins that function similarly to calsequestrin but in the ER. Actually, the double KO of calsequestrin did not inhibit Ca<sup>2+</sup> release in skeletal muscle [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>KonD model explains the refractory period of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release despite normal luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> level</title><p>We have noticed that KonD model predicts a fast recovery of luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> and a much slower recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> (compare solid line of <xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B versus 5C</xref> and see <xref rid="pone.0138195.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>). This establishes a refractory period where there is recovery of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> but not of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub> so a second [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response would be greatly diminished [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The opposite situation might happen where [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> can be reduced by leak but not the Ca<sup>2+</sup> bound to proteins [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>It has been suggested that Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from the luminal proteins is more an &#x0201c;active&#x0201d; process than a &#x0201c;passive&#x0201d; one [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In other words, SK condition (which is a passive process) cannot explain the transient increase in the luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. Additionally, Ikemoto proposes that Ca<sup>2+</sup> release involves 3 stages: 1) conformational activation of release channels, 2) induction of Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from the luminal proteins and the subsequent increase in the luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] and 3) opening of release channels and Ca<sup>2+</sup> moving from the SR to the cytoplasm [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In this regard, it has been described that a conserved glutamate in both RyRs and IP<sub>3</sub>Rs can function as a luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensor, where the increase in the luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] would trigger the opening of the release channel and allow Ca<sup>2+</sup> movement to the cytoplasm [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>Role of SERCA pumps in facilitating Ca<sup>2+</sup> release</title><p>Inhibition of SERCA pumps reduces Ca<sup>2+</sup> release and in general it has been assumed that this is due to depletion of the internal Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores. However, this is not always the case, in pancreatic acinar cells the inhibition of SERCA pumps resulted in a slower Ca<sup>2+</sup> release and disappearance of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> gradients by a mechanism that does not involve the reduction of the luminal ER [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Additionally, SERCA pump activity potentiates histamine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> release in HeLa cells [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Rapid inhibition of SERCA pump in heart cells results in a slower velocity of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> wave without any reduction in the caffeine-sensitive store [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The opposite is also true, increased activity of SERCA pump due to overexpression of adrenergic receptors in heart cells results in higher and faster Ca<sup>2+</sup> release in the absence of an increased loading of SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> store [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. SERCA pump inhibition in guinea pig urinary bladder smooth muscle cells results in a decreased amplitude and slower Ca<sup>2+</sup> release for both RyRs and IP<sub>3</sub>Rs [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], this was the case even when there is no reduction of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Collectively, these data suggest that inhibition of SERCA pump slows Ca<sup>2+</sup> release while its activation has the opposite effect. However, there is no clear explanation for this effect of SERCA pump. Our mathematical model suggest that inhibition of SERCA pump changes Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from KonD condition to the less efficient SK situation, so this might explain the slower Ca<sup>2+</sup> release. Additionally, it appears that there is also a reduction in the number of the release channels participating (k<sub>f</sub>), so this might be the reason behind a lower amplitude of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> transient.</p></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>Alternative models to KonD conditions</title><p>KonD condition is the simplest solution, we were able to visualize for an SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering capacity with a positive curvature; however, although likely in the right direction might not be the right solution. This is because another characteristic of SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores is that Ca<sup>2+</sup> freely diffuses in the lumen, a condition that is not expected from the KonD condition. The most likely solution is that the trapping of Ca<sup>2+</sup> by luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins does not occur instantaneously because it depends on the conformational changes and aggregation of proteins, a situation that might take a longer time than the one required for free diffusion of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the lumen of SR, so KonD model should consider that the kinetics of dissociation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> from luminal SR proteins is rather fast while the kinetics of association is rather slow.</p><p>A mathematical model of Ca<sup>2+</sup> spark termination in heart cells has contemplated Ca<sup>2+</sup> diffusion inside the SR [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Interestingly, this model says that Ca<sup>2+</sup> diffusion coefficient in the non-junctional SR is 0.6 x 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup> m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> (as previously estimated, [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]) but considers that this coefficient is 5-fold larger in junctional SR, that is 3.5 x 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup> m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. However, this contrasts with the concentration of non-mobile calsequestrin. The model says that calsequestrin in the non-junctional SR is 6 mM (as previously estimated, [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]) while it says is 5-fold higher in the junctional SR (30 mM [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]). This situation is rather paradoxical because we think that a higher concentration of a non-mobile calsequestrin should become a barrier for Ca<sup>2+</sup> diffusion. However, this apparent paradox stresses the importance of limiting the competition between calsequestrin and RyRs for free luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> to achieve an efficient Ca<sup>2+</sup> release event. Here, we have obtained the same result by reducing the number of luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites driven by a reduction of the luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. Alternatively, our results can be reproduced if the luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins diffuse away from the RyRs during the opening of release channels. However, we think that this scenario is unlikely since there is no driving force for this to happen and this process might not be fast enough to avoid competition with RyRs for the free luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Another scenario involves restricted diffusion of both Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Mag-Fluo-4 (they are maintained in the bulk of the SR away from the RyRs), so they are not in rapid equilibrium with the calsequestrin, which is known to be associated with RyRs [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. If the diffusion of Ca<sup>2+</sup> between these two compartments is very low, then it is expected to see recovery of the free luminal SR Ca<sup>2+</sup> level (provided that SERCA pumps are located where Mag-Fluo-4 is) even when the RyRs are still open (a situation that have not been observed). Alternatively, if the diffusion barrier is not that important, then the transition between phase 1 and phase 2 will not be clear. A situation that was observed only in the presence of thapsigargin. In conclusion, we think that our mathematical model stresses the importance of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding proteins rapidly switching from high to low Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering capacity during Ca<sup>2+</sup> release event, and this provides enough free luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> for an efficient release by RyRs. How exactly this process is achieved inside the SR is not clear and deserves further studies.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec018"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0138195.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Schematic representation.</title><p>Graphical model of smooth muscle, not at scale, of the two intracellular compartments of interest, as well as those Ca<sup>2+</sup> fluxes between these two compartments.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0138195.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0138195.s002"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>Buffer capacity as a function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>].</title><p>(A) Typical relationship for a 3 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding protein with a K<sub>D</sub> of 151.1<italic>&#x003bc;M</italic> using Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">1.7</xref>). (B) Ca<sup>2+</sup> buffering capacity for the same [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] as in A but using KonD model and Eq (<xref rid="pone.0138195.e025" ref-type="disp-formula">1.19</xref>) with values indicated in the text.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0138195.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0138195.s003"><label>S3 Fig</label><caption><title>Fitting of different Ca<sup>2+</sup> saturation levels of calsequestrin.</title><p>Models of Ca<sup>2+</sup> bound to calsequestrin as a function of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]; data replotted from <xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref> of reference [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Data were fitted to a Hill equation. Fitting results suggests that the maximal number of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites (B<sub>max</sub>) is increasing as a function of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. The inset shows the fitting for [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] in the range of 0&#x02013;0.6mM. Park et al. have shown that blocking polymerization of calsequestrin inhibits this effect of increasing B<sub>max</sub>, so B<sub>max</sub> value stays around 22 for the whole range of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] tested (triangle line) [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. At least 5 points were used to calculate B<sub>max</sub> value higher than 70.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0138195.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0138195.s004"><label>S4 Fig</label><caption><title>SK model cannot follow the recovery of the free luminal SR [Ca<sup>2+</sup>].</title><p>In this case the gamma value used in the SK model (red line) was modified to fit the caffeine-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> response (blue line). Although there is now a good fitting of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> responses induced by caffeine, the time course of recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> is much slower in the SK model than is recorded by the Mag-Fluo-4 indicator. This can be explained by considering that free and total Ca<sup>2+</sup> go together in the SK model, while in the KonD model (see Figs <xref rid="pone.0138195.g005" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0138195.g007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) there is a rapid recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> that precedes the recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>TSR</sub>, which explains the presence of a refractory period due to the recovery of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>FSR</sub> but not of the total, so the second caffeine-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> response is much smaller.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0138195.s004.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0138195.s005"><label>S1 Text</label><caption><title>Parameter estimation.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0138195.s005.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This model was deposited in Biomodels Database [<xref rid="pone.0138195.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] and assigned the identifier MODEL 1406180001.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0138195.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Clapham</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Calcium signaling</article-title>, <source>Cell</source>. <volume>80</volume> (<year>1995</year>) <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(95)90408-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7834745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Steenbergen</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name>, <article-title>The quantal nature of calcium release to caffeine in single smooth muscle cells results from activation of the sarcoplasmic reticulum Ca(2+)-ATPase.</article-title>, <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>271</volume> (<year>1996</year>) <fpage>1821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1824</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.271.4.1821</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8567621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vangheluwe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raeymaekers</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dode</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wuytack</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Modulating sarco(endo)plasmic reticulum Ca2+ ATPase 2 (SERCA2) activity: cell biological implications.</article-title>, <source>Cell Calcium</source>. <volume>38</volume> (<year>2005</year>) <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceca.2005.06.033</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16105684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Viquez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerrero-Serna</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerrero-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <article-title>SERCA pump optimizes Ca2+ release by a mechanism independent of store filling in smooth muscle cells.</article-title>, <source>Biophys. J</source>. <volume>85</volume> (<year>2003</year>) <fpage>370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(03)74481-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <article-title>The luminal Ca2+ transient controls Ca2+ release/re-uptake of sarcoplasmic reticulum.</article-title>, <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
<volume>279</volume> (<year>2000</year>) <fpage>858</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2000.4031</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11162440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antoniu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meszaros</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronjat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Intravesicular calcium transient during calcium release from sarcoplasmic reticulum</article-title>, <source>Biochemistry</source>. <volume>30</volume> (<year>1991</year>) <fpage>5230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5237</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00235a017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2036390</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Meszaros</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Conformational changes of the Ca2+-ATPase as early events of Ca2+ release from sarcoplasmic reticulum.</article-title>, <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>260</volume> (<year>1985</year>) <fpage>16076</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16079</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org/content/260/30/16076.short">http://www.jbc.org/content/260/30/16076.short</ext-link> (accessed April 9, 2015).
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2933405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wuytack</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>Polarized Expression of Ca2+ Pumps in Pancreatic and Salivary Gland Cells: ROLE IN INITIATION AND PROPAGATION OF [Ca2+] i WAVES</article-title>, <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>272</volume> (<year>1997</year>) <fpage>15771</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15776</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.25.15771</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9188473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>J.P.Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niggli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Calcium waves driven by &#x0201c;sensitization&#x0201d; wave-fronts.</article-title>, <source>Cardiovasc. Res.</source>
<volume>74</volume> (<year>2007</year>) <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cardiores.2007.02.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17336953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Aguilar-Maldonado</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Viquez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Del Angel</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arias-Monta&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerrero-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Histamine potentiates IP3-mediated Ca2+ release via thapsigargin-sensitive Ca2+ pumps</article-title>, <source>Cell. Signal.</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<year>2003</year>) <fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>697</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0898-6568(03)00012-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12742229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dagnino-Acosta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerrero-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Variable luminal sarcoplasmic reticulum Ca(2+) buffer capacity in smooth muscle cells.</article-title>, <source>Cell Calcium</source>. <volume>46</volume> (<year>2009</year>) <fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceca.2009.07.005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19679350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Viquez</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerrero-Serna</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arvizu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerrero-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Inhibition of SERCA pumps induces desynchronized RyR activation in overloaded internal Ca2+ stores in smooth muscle cells.</article-title>, <source>Am. J. Physiol. Cell Physiol.</source>
<volume>298</volume> (<year>2010</year>) <fpage>C1038</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpcell.00222.2009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20107042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penninger</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muallem</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Role of regulator of G protein signaling 2 (RGS2) in Ca(2+) oscillations and adaptation of Ca(2+) signaling to reduce excitability of RGS2-/- cells.</article-title>, <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>279</volume> (<year>2004</year>) <fpage>41642</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M406450200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lakatta</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Constitutive beta2-adrenergic signalling enhances sarcoplasmic reticulum Ca2+ cycling to augment contraction in mouse heart.</article-title>, <source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>521</volume>
<issue>Pt 2</issue> (<year>1999</year>) <fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10581307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>I.Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunker</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>Comparing skeletal and cardiac calsequestrin structures and their calcium binding: a proposed mechanism for coupled calcium binding and protein polymerization.</article-title>, <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>279</volume> (<year>2004</year>) <fpage>18026</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M311553200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Guerrero-Hernandez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dagnino-Acosta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verkhratsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <article-title>An intelligent sarco-endoplasmic reticulum Ca2+ store: Release and leak channels have differential access to a concealed Ca2+ pool</article-title>, <source>Cell Calcium</source>. <volume>48</volume> (<year>2010</year>) <fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceca.2010.08.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20817294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zima</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Picht</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bers</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blatter</surname><given-names>L. a.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Termination of cardiac Ca2+ sparks: Role of intra-SR [Ca2+], release flux, and intra-SR Ca2+ diffusion</article-title>, <source>Circ. Res.</source>
<volume>103</volume> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.107.183236</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Launikonis</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brum</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>R&#x000ed;os</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Depletion &#x0201c;skraps&#x0201d; and dynamic buffering inside the cellular calcium store.</article-title>, <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
<volume>103</volume> (<year>2006</year>) <fpage>2982</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2987</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0511252103</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Barrero</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Dynamics of [Ca2+] in the Endoplasmic Reticulum and Cytoplasm of Intact HeLa Cells: A COMPARATIVE STUDY</article-title>, <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>272</volume> (<year>1997</year>) <fpage>27694</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27699</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.44.27694</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9346910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Terentyev</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubalova</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nori</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vedamoorthyrao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terentyeva</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>Modulation of SR Ca release by luminal Ca and calsequestrin in cardiac myocytes: effects of CASQ2 mutations linked to sudden cardiac death.</article-title>, <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>95</volume> (<year>2008</year>) <fpage>2037</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2048</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.107.128249</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>a Guerrero</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>F.S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fay, Simultaneous measurement of Ca2+ release and influx into smooth muscle cells in response to caffeine. A novel approach for calculating the fraction of current carried by calcium.</article-title>, <source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>104</volume> (<year>1994</year>) <fpage>395</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>422</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.104.2.395</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7807055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fill</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Is ryanodine receptor a calcium or magnesium channel? Roles of K+ and Mg2+ during Ca2+ release</article-title>, <source>Cell Calcium</source>. <volume>51</volume> (<year>2012</year>) <fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>433</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceca.2012.02.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22387011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Havlin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>V Buldyrev</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberger</surname><given-names>a L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mantegna</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ossadnik</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>Fractals in biology and medicine.</article-title>, <source>Chaos. Solitons. Fractals.</source>
<volume>6</volume> (<year>1995</year>) <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jcp.48.1.93-b</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11539852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lytton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westlin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burk</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacLennan</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Functional comparisons between isoforms of the sarcoplasmic or endoplasmic reticulum family of calcium pumps</article-title>, <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>267</volume> (<year>1992</year>) <fpage>14483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14489</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1385815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Mobile and immobile calcium buffers in bovine adrenal chromaffin cells.</article-title>, <source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>469</volume> (<year>1993</year>) <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>273</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8271200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kirber</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerrero-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>a</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fogarty</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tuft</surname><given-names>R. a</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>Multiple pathways responsible for the stretch-induced increase in Ca2+ concentration in toad stomach smooth muscle cells.</article-title>, <source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>524</volume>
<issue>Pt 1</issue> (<year>2000</year>) <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.2000.t01-4-00003.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Santillan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <article-title>On the Use of the Hill Functions in Mathematical Models of Gene Regulatory Networks</article-title>, <source>Math. Model. Nat. Phenom.</source>
<volume>3</volume> (<year>2008</year>) <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names><suffix>Il</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunker</surname><given-names>a. K.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>Comparing skeletal and cardiac calsequestrin structures and their calcium binding: A proposed mechanism for coupled calcium binding and protein polymerization</article-title>, <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>279</volume> (<year>2004</year>) <fpage>18026</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18033</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M311553200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pozzo-Miller</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pivovarova</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Correlated measurements of free and total intracellular calcium concentration in central nervous system neurons.</article-title>, <source>Microsc. Res. Tech.</source>
<volume>46</volume> (<year>1999</year>) <fpage>370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0029(19990915)46:6&#x0003c;370::AID-JEMT5&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10504214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Manno</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sztretye</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>R&#x000ed;os</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Dynamic measurement of the calcium buffering properties of the sarcoplasmic reticulum in mouse skeletal muscle.</article-title>, <source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>591</volume> (<year>2013</year>) <fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2012.243444</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23148320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verdugo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Role of Ca2+/K+ ion exchange in intracellular storage and release of Ca2+.</article-title>, <source>Nature</source>. <volume>395</volume> (<year>1998</year>) <fpage>908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>912</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/27686</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9804425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>a Blatter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Facilitation of cytosolic calcium wave propagation by local calcium uptake into the sarcoplasmic reticulum in cardiac myocytes.</article-title>, <source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>590</volume> (<year>2012</year>) <fpage>6037</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2012.239434</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22988145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlue</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Curci</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Machen</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Spatial distribution and quantitation of free luminal [Ca] within the InsP3-sensitive internal store of individual BHK-21 cells: ion dependence of InsP3-induced Ca release and reloading.</article-title>, <source>FASEB J</source>. <volume>9</volume> (<year>1995</year>) <fpage>788</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7601343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Canato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scorzeto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giacomello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Protasi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reggiani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stienen</surname><given-names>G.J.M.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Massive alterations of sarcoplasmic reticulum free calcium in skeletal muscle fibers lacking calsequestrin revealed by a genetically encoded probe.</article-title>, <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
<volume>107</volume> (<year>2010</year>) <fpage>22326</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22331</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1009168108</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21135222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Brochet</surname><given-names>D.X.P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Di Maio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lederer</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franzini-Armstrong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Ca2+ blinks: rapid nanoscopic store calcium signaling.</article-title>, <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
<volume>102</volume> (<year>2005</year>) <fpage>3099</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0500059102</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15710901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronjat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meszaros</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koshita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Postulated role of calsequestrin in the regulation of calcium release from sarcoplasmic reticulum</article-title>, <source>Biochemistry</source>. <volume>28</volume> (<year>1989</year>) <fpage>6764</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6771</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00442a033</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2790030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>The ryanodine receptor store-sensing gate controls Ca2+ waves and Ca2+-triggered arrhythmias.</article-title>, <source>Nat. Med.</source>
<volume>20</volume> (<year>2014</year>) <fpage>184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.3440</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24441828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Laver</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>C.H.T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imtiaz</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cannell</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Termination of calcium-induced calcium release by induction decay: an emergent property of stochastic channel gating and molecular scale architecture.</article-title>, <source>J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol.</source>
<volume>54</volume> (<year>2013</year>) <fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2012.10.009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23123322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cannell</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>C.H.T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imtiaz</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laver</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Control of sarcoplasmic reticulum Ca2+ release by stochastic RyR gating within a 3D model of the cardiac dyad and importance of induction decay for CICR termination</article-title>, <source>Biophys. J.</source> (<year>2013</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2013.03.058</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bers</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Sarcoplasmic reticulum and nuclear envelope are one highly interconnected Ca2+ store throughout cardiac myocyte</article-title>, <source>Circ. Res.</source> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.RES.0000233386.02708.72</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mollica</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knollmann</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Quantification of calsequestrin 2 (CSQ2) in sheep cardiac muscle and Ca2+-binding protein changes in CSQ2 knockout mice.</article-title>, <source>Am. J. Physiol. Heart Circ. Physiol.</source> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.00902.2010</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Baddeley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crossman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossberger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheyne</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jayasinghe</surname><given-names>I.D.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>4D super-resolution microscopy with conventional fluorophores and single wavelength excitation in optically thick cells and tissues.</article-title>, <source>PLoS One</source>. <volume>6</volume> (<year>2011</year>) <fpage>e20645</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020645</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21655189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0138195.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Le Nov&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broicher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Courtot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donizelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dharuri</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <article-title>BioModels Database: a free, centralized database of curated, published, quantitative kinetic models of biochemical and cellular systems.</article-title>, <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>34</volume> (<year>2006</year>) <fpage>D689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D691</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkj092</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>